{
    "questions": [
        {
            "Question": "The artificial kidney is a",
            "optionA": "  Transplant ",
            "optionB": "  Machine ",
            "optionC": "  Another's kidney ",
            "optionD": "  Other kidney from same body ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe artificial kidney is a machine. ",
            "keyString": "131684s35m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "With reference to the work of human kidney consider the following statements1. After the waste is removed in the kidney the clean blood is sent back through renal artery.2. From Bowman's capsule, the filtered liquid passes through tiny tubes where much of the glucose is reabsorbed and sent back to the blood in the renal vein.Which of these statements is/are correct?",
            "optionA": "  Only 1 ",
            "optionB": "  Only 2 ",
            "optionC": "  Both 1 and 2 ",
            "optionD": "  Neither 1 nor 2 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFrom Bowman's capsule, the filtered liquid passes through tiny tubes where much of the glucose is reabsorbed and sent back to the blood in the renal vein is the correct statement. ",
            "keyString": "131714s35m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following function is performed by the kidneys in the human body?",
            "optionA": "  Excretion ",
            "optionB": "  Respiration ",
            "optionC": "  Digestion ",
            "optionD": "  Transportation ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMost people know that a major function of the kidneys is to remove waste products and excess fluid from the body. These waste products and excess fluid are removed through the urine. The production of urine involves highly complex steps of excretion and re-absorption. ",
            "keyString": "131729s35m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one is located at the rear of the abdominal cavity?",
            "optionA": "  Liver  ",
            "optionB": "  Kidneys  ",
            "optionC": "  Heart  ",
            "optionD": "  Pancreas  ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe abdominal cavity is lined with a protective membrane termed the peritoneum. The inside wall is covered by the parietal peritoneum. The kidneys are located behind the peritoneum, in the retroperitoneum, outside the abdominal cavity. ",
            "keyString": "131740s35m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Urea is transported through",
            "optionA": "  RBCs  ",
            "optionB": "  WBCs  ",
            "optionC": "  Blood Plasma  ",
            "optionD": "  All of above  ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tUrea is the product of excess amino acids. It is transported into blood plasma by the liver and removed by the kidney. This process is called excretion. ",
            "keyString": "131750s35m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Mycology is the branch of botany in which we study about",
            "optionA": "  Algae ",
            "optionB": "  Fungi ",
            "optionC": "  Bacteria ",
            "optionD": "  Virus ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMycology is the branch of biology concerned with the study of fungi, including their genetic and biochemical properties, their taxonomy and their use to humans as a source for tinder, traditional medicine, food, and entheogens, as well as their dangers, such as toxicity or infection. ",
            "keyString": "168389s35m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Mycology is the branch of botany in which we study about",
            "optionA": "  Algae ",
            "optionB": "  Fungi ",
            "optionC": "  Bacteria ",
            "optionD": "  Virus ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": "\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tNo explanation is given for this questionLet's Discuss on Board ",
            "keyString": "168418s35m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Phycology is the branch of botany in which we study about",
            "optionA": "  Algae ",
            "optionB": "  Fungi ",
            "optionC": "  Ecology ",
            "optionD": "  Virus ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPhycology is the branch of botany in which we study about algae. ",
            "keyString": "168431s35m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The DNA bacterium consists of ring-like pieces known as the",
            "optionA": "  Plasmids ",
            "optionB": "  Genes ",
            "optionC": "  Chromosomes ",
            "optionD": "  Mesosomes ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe DNA bacterium consists of ring-like pieces known as the plasmids. ",
            "keyString": "168443s35m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "It is commonly found in the bottom tidal pools?",
            "optionA": "  Spirogyra ",
            "optionB": "  Ulva ",
            "optionC": "  Stiogeoclonium ",
            "optionD": "  Chlamydomonas ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tUlva is commonly found in the bottom tidal pools. ",
            "keyString": "168454s35m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Volvox colonies are found in",
            "optionA": "  Freshwater ponds  ",
            "optionB": "  Salt lakes  ",
            "optionC": "  Seawater  ",
            "optionD": "  Spring  ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tVolvox can be found in ponds, puddles, and bodies of still fresh water throughout the world. As autotrophs, they contribute to the production of oxygen and serve as food for a number of aquatic organisms, especially the microscopic invertebrates called rotifers.",
            "keyString": "204756s35m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following is not reserve food of fungi?",
            "optionA": "  Glycogen  ",
            "optionB": "  Fat  ",
            "optionC": "  Starch  ",
            "optionD": "  Both A and B  ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tReserve food material in all the fungi is glycogen and oil but not starch.",
            "keyString": "204784s35m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The nitrogen fixing bacteria present in the root nodules of leguminous plant is",
            "optionA": "  Salmonella  ",
            "optionB": "  Clostridium  ",
            "optionC": "  Rhizobium  ",
            "optionD": "  Pseudomonas  ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRhizobium is a genus of bacteria associated with the formation of root nodules on plants. These bacteria live in symbiosis with legumes. They take in nitrogen from the atmosphere and pass it on to the plant, allowing it to grow in soil low in nitrogen. ",
            "keyString": "204798s35m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "All of the following are true of neurons except that",
            "optionA": "  They conduct a nervous impulse ",
            "optionB": "  They are a very specialized form of connective tissue ",
            "optionC": "  Thay are separated from one another by synapses ",
            "optionD": "  When mature, they lose ability to divide ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAll of the following are true of neurons except that they are a very specialized form of connective tissue. ",
            "keyString": "204809s35m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Synapse gap is present between which of the following?",
            "optionA": "  Two neurons ",
            "optionB": "  Brain and Spinal Cord ",
            "optionC": "  Two Kidneys ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAn electrical synapse is a mechanical and electrically conductive link between two neighboring neurons that is formed at a narrow gap between the pre- and postsynaptic neurons known as a gap junction. ",
            "keyString": "204820s35m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Purification of blood takes place in",
            "optionA": "  Lungs ",
            "optionB": "  Heart ",
            "optionC": "  Kidney ",
            "optionD": "  Liver ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPurification of blood takes place in kidney. ",
            "keyString": "240554s35m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Fully mature human RBCs has",
            "optionA": "  A nucleus ",
            "optionB": "  No nucleus ",
            "optionC": "  Nucleus may or may not be present ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFully mature human RBCs has no nucleus. ",
            "keyString": "240583s35m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following blood group is universal donor?",
            "optionA": "  B ",
            "optionB": "  O ",
            "optionC": "  A ",
            "optionD": "  AB ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFor emergency transfusions, blood group type O negative blood is the variety of blood that has the lowest risk of causing serious reactions for most people who receive it. Because of this, it's sometimes called the universal blood donor type. ",
            "keyString": "240596s35m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Human heart is made up of",
            "optionA": "  Nervous tissue ",
            "optionB": "  Cardiac muscle ",
            "optionC": "  Nonstriated muscle ",
            "optionD": "  Connective tissue ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAn organ is a group of tissues that work together to perform a specific function. In the case of heart, this function is pumping blood throughout your body. Additionally, the heart is largely made up of a type of muscle tissue called cardiac muscle. ",
            "keyString": "240608s35m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Antigens 'A' and 'B' are absent in persons belong to blood group",
            "optionA": "  'O' ",
            "optionB": "  'A' ",
            "optionC": "  'B' ",
            "optionD": "  'AB' ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBlood group O has no antigens, but both anti-A and anti-B antibodies in the plasma, as well as some special \u201canti-A,B' antibodies. Blood group AB has both A and B antigens, but no antibodies. ",
            "keyString": "240619s35m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "A living part of the organisms environment is known as",
            "optionA": "  Abiotic Factor ",
            "optionB": "  Habitat ",
            "optionC": "  Biotic Factor ",
            "optionD": "  Non\u00adliving factor ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA living part of the organisms environment is known as biotic factor. ",
            "keyString": "277627s35m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Secondary consumers are eaten by larger",
            "optionA": "  Fast animal ",
            "optionB": "  Animal in the third trophic level ",
            "optionC": "  Herbivorous animal ",
            "optionD": "  Predator ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSecondary consumers can be sorted into two groups: carnivores and omnivores. Carnivores only eat meat, or other animals. Some secondary consumers are large predators, but even the smaller ones often eat herbivores bigger than they are in order to get enough energy. ",
            "keyString": "277659s35m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Some of the conifers in our northern areas include ",
            "optionA": "  Pines ",
            "optionB": "  Abies ",
            "optionC": "  Cedrus ",
            "optionD": "  All of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSome of the conifers in our northern areas include Pines, Abies and Cedrus. ",
            "keyString": "277674s35m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of these plants grow in an environment that is neither very wet nor very dry?",
            "optionA": "  Mesophytes ",
            "optionB": "  Sporophyte ",
            "optionC": "  Saprophytes ",
            "optionD": "  Tracheophytes ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMesophytes are terrestrial plants which are adapted to neither a particularly dry nor particularly wet environment. An example of a mesophytic habitat would be a rural temperate meadow, which might contain goldenrod, clover, daisy, and Rosa multiflora. ",
            "keyString": "277686s35m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which statement describes decomposers?",
            "optionA": "  Decomposers are insignificant organisms in the ecosystem and can be absent in some ecosystems ",
            "optionB": "  Decomposers can produce their own source of energy and can sometimes act as primary producers ",
            "optionC": "  Decomposers are those organisms that recycle matter in the ecosystem ",
            "optionD": "  All the above ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDecomposers are organisms that break down dead or decaying organisms, and in doing so, they carry out the natural process of decomposition. ",
            "keyString": "277697s35m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following blood cells carry oxygen?",
            "optionA": "  W.",
            "optionB": "Cs ",
            "optionC": "  Platelets ",
            "optionD": "  R.",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe main job of red blood cells, or erythrocytes, is to carry oxygen from the lungs to the body tissues and carbon dioxide as a waste product, away from the tissues and back to the lungs. Hemoglobin (Hgb) is an important protein in the red blood cells that carries oxygen from the lungs to all parts of our body. ",
            "keyString": "315862s35m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In human body lymphocytes are formed in",
            "optionA": "  Liver ",
            "optionB": "  Bone marrow ",
            "optionC": "  Pancreas ",
            "optionD": "  Spleen ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tLymphocytes develop in the thymus and bone marrow (yellow), which are therefore called central (or primary) lymphoid organs.",
            "keyString": "315895s35m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which statement about capillaries is correct?",
            "optionA": "  Their walls are covered with cilia ",
            "optionB": "  They warm and humidify inhaled air ",
            "optionC": "  Their walls are only one cell thick ",
            "optionD": "  They move mucus through the lungs ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCapillaries are tiny blood vessels connecting arteries to veins. These blood vessels carry oxygen and nutrients to individual cells. Capillaries are the smallest blood vessels in the body, and have walls only one or two cells thick. ",
            "keyString": "315908s35m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The grouping of blood is based on substances called",
            "optionA": "  Antibodies ",
            "optionB": "  Antigens ",
            "optionC": "  Antitoxin ",
            "optionD": "  Enzymes ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe red blood corpusclesor erythrocytes usually carry antigens and there are two types of antigens. The A group persons have antigen A in their red corpuscles and the B group have antigen B in their red corpuscles. The AB group person have both antigen A and antigen B in their erythrocytes. The 'O' group persons have no antigens in their red corpuscles. ",
            "keyString": "315920s35m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which blood group is universal acceptor?",
            "optionA": "  O+ ",
            "optionB": "  O- ",
            "optionC": "  AB- ",
            "optionD": "  AB+ ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAB+ is universal acceptor. ",
            "keyString": "315931s35m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Total number of bones found in child",
            "optionA": "  200 ",
            "optionB": "  206 ",
            "optionC": "  300 ",
            "optionD": "  306 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAn adult has 206 bones, but a newborn baby has nearly 300 bones in her body. ",
            "keyString": "351803s35m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "A typical human ribcage consists of how many ribs ?",
            "optionA": "  12 ",
            "optionB": "  14 ",
            "optionC": "  16 ",
            "optionD": "  24 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA typical human ribcage consists of 12 ribs. ",
            "keyString": "351831s35m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The total number of bones found in newly born human body ?",
            "optionA": "  212 ",
            "optionB": "  206 ",
            "optionC": "  202 ",
            "optionD": "  300 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA baby's body has about 300 bones at birth.",
            "keyString": "351845s35m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following bone is not found in human leg?",
            "optionA": "  Tibia ",
            "optionB": "  Humerus ",
            "optionC": "  Femur ",
            "optionD": "  Fibula ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe humerus is the long bone in the upper arm. It is located between the elbow joint and the shoulder. So, the correct option is C. ",
            "keyString": "351856s35m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which cell can contract and relax?",
            "optionA": "  Muscle cells ",
            "optionB": "  Excretory cells ",
            "optionC": "  Nervous cells ",
            "optionD": "  Respiratory cells ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMuscle Tissue: A collection of muscle fibers that can contract and relax to move body parts. Examples include cardiac (heart) muscle, skeletal muscle (in limbs, trunk, jaw and face) and smooth muscle (in digestive tract, eyes, blood vessels and ducts). ",
            "keyString": "351866s35m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following functions is not carried out by smooth endoplasmic reticulum?",
            "optionA": "  Transport of materials ",
            "optionB": "  Synthesis of lipid ",
            "optionC": "  Synthesis of protein ",
            "optionD": "  Synthesis of steroid hormone ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSmooth Endoplasmic Reticulumdoes not contain ribosomes on its surface for which it is regarded as smooth. So, proteins cannotbe synthesised by SER provided protein synthesis is the primary task of ribosomes. ",
            "keyString": "388186s35m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which is called the factory of ribosomes?",
            "optionA": "  Nucleus ",
            "optionB": "  Nucleous ",
            "optionC": "  Vacuole ",
            "optionD": "  Endoplasmic Reticulum ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNucleous is called the factory of ribosomes. ",
            "keyString": "388215s35m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In what organelle does cellular respiration take place?",
            "optionA": "  Cytoplasm ",
            "optionB": "  Ribosomes ",
            "optionC": "  Mitochondria ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe enzymatic reactions of cellular respiration begin in the cytoplasm, but most of the reactions occur in the mitochondria. Cellular respiration occurs in the double-membrane organelle called the mitochondrion. The folds in the inner membrane are called cristae. ",
            "keyString": "388229s35m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Chromosomes are present ",
            "optionA": "  Inside the nucleus ",
            "optionB": "  Inside the cytoplasm ",
            "optionC": "  Inside the ribosomes ",
            "optionD": "  Inside the endoplasmic reticulum ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tChromosomes are thread-like structures located inside the nucleus of animal and plant cells. Each chromosome is made of protein and a single molecule of deoxyribonucleic acid (DNA). Passed from parents to offspring, DNA contains the specific instructions that make each type of living creature unique. ",
            "keyString": "388240s35m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which organelle does cellular respiration occur?",
            "optionA": "  Chloroplast ",
            "optionB": "  ATP and NADPH ",
            "optionC": "  Cytoplasm ",
            "optionD": "  Mitochondria ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe enzymatic reactions of cellular respiration begin in the cytoplasm, but most of the reactions occur in the mitochondria. Cellular respiration occurs in the double-membrane organelle called the mitochondrion. The folds in the inner membrane are called cristae. ",
            "keyString": "388251s35m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In ________ cells the genetic material is without any nuclear membrane covering and is directly submerged in the cytoplasm.",
            "optionA": "  Virus ",
            "optionB": "  Algae ",
            "optionC": "  Bacteria ",
            "optionD": "  Moss ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn bacteria cells the genetic material is without any nuclear membrane covering and is directly submerged in the cytoplasm. ",
            "keyString": "423892s35m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Cyanobacteria are also known as",
            "optionA": "  Autotrophic bacteria ",
            "optionB": "  Blue Green Algae ",
            "optionC": "  Red Brown Algae ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCyanobacteria, also known as blue-green bacteria, blue-green algae, and Cyanophyta, is a phylum of bacteria that obtain their energy through photosynthesis. ",
            "keyString": "423924s35m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Branch of biology which deals with the study processing and preservation of food is called",
            "optionA": "  Food technology ",
            "optionB": "  Food biotechnology ",
            "optionC": "  Food preservation ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBranch of biology which deals with the study processing and preservation of food is called Food technology. ",
            "keyString": "423938s35m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "A viral species is a group of viruses that has",
            "optionA": "  Same ecological niche ",
            "optionB": "  Same genetic information ",
            "optionC": "  Both A & B ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA viral species is a group of viruses that has same ecological niche and same genetic information. ",
            "keyString": "423951s35m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The litmus paper utilized in the chemical laboratories is made of :",
            "optionA": "  Fern ",
            "optionB": "  Algae ",
            "optionC": "  Lichen ",
            "optionD": "  Fungi ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tLitmus paper is an acid/base indicator that changes color to identify bases and acids. Litmus is a dye made from naturally occurring substances, including lichens (fungi)\u2013 the most commonly used of which is the species roccella tinctoria. ",
            "keyString": "423962s35m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Bacteria are classified in the kingdom",
            "optionA": "  Animalia  ",
            "optionB": "  Fungi  ",
            "optionC": "  Monera  ",
            "optionD": "  Protista  ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBacteria are classified in the kingdom Monera. ",
            "keyString": "460117s35m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following animals shows radial symmetry?",
            "optionA": "  Frog  ",
            "optionB": "  Pila  ",
            "optionC": "  Star Fish  ",
            "optionD": "  Fish  ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tStar Fish shows radial symmetry. ",
            "keyString": "460145s35m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who introduced the \"binomial nomenclature\" to name organisms?",
            "optionA": "  ",
            "optionB": " Darwin  ",
            "optionC": "  G. Mendel  ",
            "optionD": "  E. Mayer  ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTyrannosaurus rex is probably the most widely known binomial. The formal introduction of this system of naming species is credited to Carl Linnaeus, effectively beginning with his work Species Plantarum in 1753. ",
            "keyString": "460158s35m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Aestivation is seen in",
            "optionA": "  Amphibians  ",
            "optionB": "  Chimpanzee  ",
            "optionC": "  Salmon  ",
            "optionD": "  Squirrels  ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAestivation occurs in animals living in deserts and tropical regions. This is done to protect themselves from hot and dry climate, and due to the scarcity of food water. This can be seen in earthworms, molluscs, arthropods, reptiles and amphibians. A lungfish can aestivate and survive without water for three years. ",
            "keyString": "460170s35m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one is the largest animal phylum?",
            "optionA": "  Arthropod  ",
            "optionB": "  Mollusca  ",
            "optionC": "  Chordata  ",
            "optionD": "  Coelomates  ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArthropod, (phylum Arthropoda), any member of the phylum Arthropoda, the largest phylum in the animal kingdom, which includes such familiar forms as lobsters, crabs, spiders, mites, insects, centipedes, and millipedes. About 84 percent of all known species of animals are members of this phylum. ",
            "keyString": "460181s35m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In a cell process of respiration takes place in",
            "optionA": "  Mitochondria ",
            "optionB": "  Plastids ",
            "optionC": "  Ribosomes ",
            "optionD": "  Lysosomes ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCellular respiration occurs in the double-membrane organelle called the mitochondrion. ",
            "keyString": "497181s35m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "It is the basic structure found in all membranes such as those of mitochondria and chloroplasts.",
            "optionA": "  Nuclear membrane ",
            "optionB": "  Unit membrane ",
            "optionC": "  Plasma membrane ",
            "optionD": "  Cell wall ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tUnit membrane is the basic structure found in all membranes such as those of mitochondria and chloroplasts. ",
            "keyString": "497211s35m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one is found in a pair in each chromosome?",
            "optionA": "  Genes  ",
            "optionB": "  Nuclei  ",
            "optionC": "  Bases  ",
            "optionD": "  Chromatids  ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tChromatids is found in a pair in each chromosome. ",
            "keyString": "497225s35m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Ribosomes are produced in",
            "optionA": "  Nucleolus  ",
            "optionB": "  Plasmid  ",
            "optionC": "  Mitochondria  ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above  ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn bacterial cells, ribosomes are synthesized in the cytoplasm through the transcription of multiple ribosome gene operons. In eukaryotes, the process takes place both in the cell cytoplasm and in the nucleolus, which is a region within the cell nucleus. ",
            "keyString": "497236s35m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which cell feature is responsible for storing water ?",
            "optionA": "  Vacuole  ",
            "optionB": "  Lysosome  ",
            "optionC": "  Mitochondria  ",
            "optionD": "  Non of the above  ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tVacuole is responsible for storing water. ",
            "keyString": "497247s35m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The bone humerus is found in",
            "optionA": "  Thigh ",
            "optionB": "  Upper arm ",
            "optionC": "  Fore arm ",
            "optionD": "  Leg ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe humerus is a long bone of the upper limb, which extends from the shoulder to the elbow.",
            "keyString": "554174s35m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The bone tibia is found in",
            "optionA": "  Skull ",
            "optionB": "  Leg ",
            "optionC": "  Arm ",
            "optionD": "  Mouth ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe tibia (shin bone) is a long bone of the leg, found medial to the fibula. It is also the the weight bearing bone of the leg, which is why it is the second largest bone in the body after the femur. ",
            "keyString": "554202s35m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Longest bone found in which part of human body?",
            "optionA": "  Vertebral column ",
            "optionB": "  Thigh ",
            "optionC": "  Rib cage ",
            "optionD": "  Arm ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe femur is one of the most researched bones in the human anatomy and forensic medicine. As the longest bone in the human body, it is well preserved in skeletal remains. ",
            "keyString": "554216s35m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one is the longest bone in human body?",
            "optionA": "  Tibia  ",
            "optionB": "  Fibula  ",
            "optionC": "  Radius  ",
            "optionD": "  Femur  ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe femur is one of the most researched bones in the human anatomy and forensic medicine. As the longest bone in the human body, it is well preserved in skeletal remains. ",
            "keyString": "554228s35m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Number of ribs found in a typical human ribcage is",
            "optionA": "  16  ",
            "optionB": "  21  ",
            "optionC": "  24  ",
            "optionD": "  28  ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe ribs are a set of twelve paired bones which form the protective 'cage' of the thorax. They articulate with the vertebral column posteriorly, and terminate anteriorly as cartilage (known as costal cartilage). Number of ribs found in a typical human ribcage is 24. ",
            "keyString": "554239s35m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In Pedology we study about",
            "optionA": "  Disease ",
            "optionB": "  Pollution ",
            "optionC": "  Soil ",
            "optionD": "  Rockes ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPedology is defined as the science that studies the genesis, nature, distribution and use potentiality of soil resources. ",
            "keyString": "590437s35m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Biological control is to check growth of ",
            "optionA": "  Plants ",
            "optionB": "  Animals ",
            "optionC": "  Weeds ",
            "optionD": "  One pest by another ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBiological control is to check growth of one pest by another. ",
            "keyString": "590467s35m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The biofertilizer used or the paddy crops is",
            "optionA": "  Blue-green algae ",
            "optionB": "  Rhizobium species ",
            "optionC": "  Fungal root fungal ",
            "optionD": "  Azetobactor species ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe bio-fertilizers used for rice crop are Azospirillum, Phosphobacteria, Blue green algae azolla and Mycorhiza. ",
            "keyString": "590480s35m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following plants have root nodules?",
            "optionA": "  Leguminous plants ",
            "optionB": "  Parasitic plants ",
            "optionC": "  Epiphytic Plants ",
            "optionD": "  Aquatic Plants ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tLeguminous plants have root nodules. ",
            "keyString": "590492s35m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Branch of agriculture concerned with the production of crops is",
            "optionA": "  Agrotology ",
            "optionB": "  Agronomy ",
            "optionC": "  Agrostology ",
            "optionD": "  Anthropology ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAgronomy is the branch of agriculture concerned with the production of crops. ",
            "keyString": "590503s35m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which lobe of human brain is associated with hearing?",
            "optionA": "  Frontal lobe ",
            "optionB": "  Parietal lobe ",
            "optionC": "  Temporal lobe ",
            "optionD": "  Occipital lobe ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe temporal lobe contains the primary auditory cortex, which receives auditory information from the ears and secondary areas, and processes the information so we understand what we're hearing (e.g. words, laughing, a baby crying). ",
            "keyString": "625337s35m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following organs do not have blood vessels?",
            "optionA": "  Spleen ",
            "optionB": "  Cornea ",
            "optionC": "  Liver ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCornea do not have blood vessels. ",
            "keyString": "625368s35m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Receptors for hearing are located in the",
            "optionA": "  Vestibule ",
            "optionB": "  Tympanic membrane ",
            "optionC": "  Semicircular canals ",
            "optionD": "  Cochlea ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe cochlea contains the spiral organ of Corti, which is the receptor organ for hearing. ",
            "keyString": "625384s35m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Image of object is formed on which part of eye?",
            "optionA": "  Cornea ",
            "optionB": "  Choroid ",
            "optionC": "  Retina ",
            "optionD": "  Iris ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAn image is formed on the retina with light rays converging most at the cornea and upon entering and exiting the lens. Rays from the top and bottom of the object are traced and produce an inverted real image on the retina. ",
            "keyString": "625396s35m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "A colour blind person has difficulty in distinguishing which of the two colours?",
            "optionA": "  Green & Red ",
            "optionB": "  White & Red ",
            "optionC": "  Blue & Red ",
            "optionD": "  Red & Black ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA colour blind person has difficulty in distinguishing green & red colours. ",
            "keyString": "625409s35m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Enzyme secreted by stomach digests the food but stomach is not digested by this digestive juice because",
            "optionA": "  Wall of stomach is lined with mucus ",
            "optionB": "  This is made up of hard cells ",
            "optionC": "  It is made up of steel ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe stomach does not digest itself because it is lined with epithial cells, which produce mucus. This forms a barrier between the lining of the stomach and the contents. Enzymes, which make up part of the digestive juices are also secreted by the stomach wall, from glands with no mucus barrier. ",
            "keyString": "663953s35m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Where does most digestion take place?",
            "optionA": "  Stomach ",
            "optionB": "  Large intestine ",
            "optionC": "  Small intestine ",
            "optionD": "  Mouth ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe majority of chemical digestion occurs in the small intestine. Digested chyme from the stomach passes through the pylorus and into the duodenum. ",
            "keyString": "663989s35m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Both food and air travel through the",
            "optionA": "  Pharynx ",
            "optionB": "  Trachea ",
            "optionC": "  Larynx ",
            "optionD": "  Alveolus ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAir, food and liquid all pass through this common passage, the oropharynx. The two passages separate again here, in the hypopharynx. Food and liquid pass backward into the esophagus on their way to the stomach. Air passes forward through the larynx and into the trachea, on its way to the lungs. ",
            "keyString": "664006s35m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The enzyme which take part in digestion of milk protein is",
            "optionA": "  Pepsin ",
            "optionB": "  Trypsin ",
            "optionC": "  Rennin ",
            "optionD": "  Eripsin ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe enzyme which take part in digestion of milk protein is rennin. ",
            "keyString": "664021s35m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following is an enzyme ?",
            "optionA": "  Gastrin ",
            "optionB": "  Keratin ",
            "optionC": "  Trypsin ",
            "optionD": "  Vasopressin ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTrypsin is an enzyme. ",
            "keyString": "664034s35m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Psidium guajava is the scientific name of ________ .",
            "optionA": "  Guava ",
            "optionB": "  Mango ",
            "optionC": "  Bamboo ",
            "optionD": "  Jack fruit ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPsidium guajava, the common guava, yellow guava, or lemon guava, is an evergreen shrub or small tree native to the Caribbean, Central America and South America. ",
            "keyString": "709198s35m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Grevillea Robusta is the scientific name of ________ .",
            "optionA": "  Peepal ",
            "optionB": "  Teak ",
            "optionC": "  Silver Oak ",
            "optionD": "  Jack fruit ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGrevillea robusta, commonly known as the southern silky oak, silk oak or silky oak, silver oak or Australian silver oak, is a flowering plant in the family Proteaceae. It is a tree, the largest species in its genus but is not closely related to the true oaks, Quercus. ",
            "keyString": "709246s35m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Artocarpus integra is the scientific name of ________ .",
            "optionA": "  Guava ",
            "optionB": "  Pineapple ",
            "optionC": "  Silver Oak ",
            "optionD": "  Jack fruit ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArtocarpus integra is the scientific name of jack fruit. ",
            "keyString": "709264s35m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is a fish?",
            "optionA": "  Jelly fish ",
            "optionB": "  Lobster ",
            "optionC": "  Salmon ",
            "optionD": "  Whale ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe characteristic features of fishes are aquatic, streamlined body with scales, 2-chambered heart and gills. Bombay duck, salmon and Hippocampus exhibit these features thus they belong to the class Pieces. Bombay duck or bummalo is a 'lizardfish'. It is native to the water between Mumbai and Kutch in the Arabian sea and a small numbers are also found in the Bay of Bengal. Salmon is the common name for several species of fishes. ",
            "keyString": "709277s35m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What is scientific name of \"Cotton\" ?",
            "optionA": "  Azadhirachta Indica ",
            "optionB": "  Phaseolies auicus ",
            "optionC": "  Gossypium Herbaceum ",
            "optionD": "  Ficus Benghalensis ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGossypium Herbaceum is scientific name of \"Cotton\". ",
            "keyString": "709290s35m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Increased RBC's in the blood leads to a condition called",
            "optionA": "  Anemia  ",
            "optionB": "  Haemophilia  ",
            "optionC": "  Polycthemia  ",
            "optionD": "  Leukaemia  ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPolycythemia is a condition that results in an increased level of circulating red blood cells in the bloodstream. ",
            "keyString": "751761s35m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Platelet is also known as",
            "optionA": "  Leucocytes  ",
            "optionB": "  Erythrocytes  ",
            "optionC": "  Thrombocytes  ",
            "optionD": "  Phagocytosis  ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPlatelets, also known as thrombocytes, are blood cells. They form in your bone marrow, a sponge-like tissue in your bones. Platelets play a major role in blood clotting. ",
            "keyString": "751861s35m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Antibodies are produced by",
            "optionA": "  Lymphocytes  ",
            "optionB": "  Plasma cells  ",
            "optionC": "  RBCs  ",
            "optionD": "  T-cells  ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAntibodies are produced by plasma cells. ",
            "keyString": "751934s35m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Oxygenated blood is carried from the lungs to the ________ by the pulmonary veins.",
            "optionA": "  Right ventricle  ",
            "optionB": "  Left ventricle  ",
            "optionC": "  Right auricle  ",
            "optionD": "  Left auricle  ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOxygenated blood is carried from the lungs to the left auricle by the pulmonary veins. ",
            "keyString": "751990s35m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one is the largest cells in white blood corpuscles?",
            "optionA": "  Lymphocytes  ",
            "optionB": "  Basophils  ",
            "optionC": "  Monocytes  ",
            "optionD": "  Neutrophils  ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMonocyte is the largest cells in white blood corpuscles. ",
            "keyString": "752045s35m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The food material prepared in the plants is transported to the various organs by which of the following?",
            "optionA": "  Xylem ",
            "optionB": "  Phloem ",
            "optionC": "  Cortex ",
            "optionD": "  Cambium ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe food which is prepared by the process of photosynthesis in the leaves of a plant has to be transported to other parts like stem, roots, branches etc. Phloem transports this food material. ",
            "keyString": "805039s35m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Cells with similar markers stick together and function as",
            "optionA": "  Organs ",
            "optionB": "  Tissues ",
            "optionC": "  Systems ",
            "optionD": "  Organisms ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA tissue is an ensemble of similar cells and their extracellular matrix from the same origin that together carry out a specific function. Hence, Cells with similar markers stick together and function as tissues. ",
            "keyString": "805099s35m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Xylem tissue is mainly concerned with the",
            "optionA": "  Photosynthesis of plants ",
            "optionB": "  Transport of water and mineral nutrients in plants ",
            "optionC": "  Storage of prepared foods in plants ",
            "optionD": "  Transport of enzymes in plants ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe basic function of xylem is to transport water from roots to stems and leaves, but it also transports nutrients. ",
            "keyString": "805117s35m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The major constituent of connective tissue is",
            "optionA": "  Lipid ",
            "optionB": "  Carbohydrate ",
            "optionC": "  Cholesterol ",
            "optionD": "  Collagen ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tUnlike the other tissue types (epithelium, muscle, and nerve), which consist mainly of cells, the major constituent of connective tissue is the extracellular matrix (ECM). Extracellular matrices consist of different combinations of protein fibers (collagen and elastic fibers) and ground substance. ",
            "keyString": "805154s35m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The connective tissue that connects a muscle to a bone is",
            "optionA": "  Cartilage ",
            "optionB": "  Ligament ",
            "optionC": "  Tendon ",
            "optionD": "  Interstitial fluid ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA tendon is a fibrous connective tissue which attaches muscle to bone. Tendons may also attach muscles to structures such as the eyeball. ",
            "keyString": "805189s35m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Lederberg and Tatum demonstrated conjugation in the bacteria in",
            "optionA": "  1944 ",
            "optionB": "  1945 ",
            "optionC": "  1946 ",
            "optionD": "  1947 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBacterial conjugation was first described by Lederberg and Tatum in 1946 as a phenomenon involving the exchange of markers between closely related strains of Escherichia coli. ",
            "keyString": "853765s35m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The individual chain of cells or filament in the colony of Nostoc is known as",
            "optionA": "  Trichome ",
            "optionB": "  Heterocyst ",
            "optionC": "  Hormogonia ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIf you look at Nostoc structure under a microscope, you will see thread-like filaments, called trichomes. Each trichome is really a chain of round or bead-like cells that lack a nucleus. ",
            "keyString": "853866s35m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Under the ideal environmental conditions bacterial cells divide at the rate of division per twenty ",
            "optionA": "  Second ",
            "optionB": "  Minutes ",
            "optionC": "  Hours ",
            "optionD": "  Days ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBacteria do not grow and multiply the same way as animals or humans. They take in nutrients and reproduce by dividing \u2013 one bacteria splits and becomes two bacteria, two become four, four become eight and so on. Under ideal conditions, many types of bacteria can double every 20 minutes. ",
            "keyString": "853918s35m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The virus is",
            "optionA": "  Protein and lipid ",
            "optionB": "  Nucleic acid and protein ",
            "optionC": "  Lipid and carbohydrate ",
            "optionD": "  Carbohydrate ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe virus is nucleic acid and protein. ",
            "keyString": "853976s35m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of these is a human disease caused by bacteria?",
            "optionA": "  TB ",
            "optionB": "  Ascariasis ",
            "optionC": "  Chickenpox ",
            "optionD": "  Common cold ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tInfectious diseases can be caused by: Bacteria. These one-cell organisms are responsible for illnesses such as strep throat, urinary tract infections and tuberculosis. ",
            "keyString": "854028s35m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Organic Substances which, in very small amounts, control growth and development called",
            "optionA": "  vitamins ",
            "optionB": "  hormones ",
            "optionC": "  enzymes ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOrganic Substances which, in very small amounts, control growth and development called hormones. ",
            "keyString": "913095s35m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Our major foods, fibres, spices, fruits and beverage crops are",
            "optionA": "  flowering plants ",
            "optionB": "  gymnosperms plants ",
            "optionC": "  pteridophytes ",
            "optionD": "  bryophytes ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOur major foods, fibres, spices, fruits and beverage crops are flowering plants. ",
            "keyString": "913167s35m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Movements due to light are shown by",
            "optionA": "  flowering plants ",
            "optionB": "  lower plants ",
            "optionC": "  all land plants ",
            "optionD": "  all the plants ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFlowering plants show the movement due to light. ",
            "keyString": "913218s35m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Outer covering of virus made up of protein is",
            "optionA": "  capsid ",
            "optionB": "  coat ",
            "optionC": "  virion ",
            "optionD": "  viriod ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA capsid is the protein shell of a virus, enclosing its genetic material. The proteins making up the capsid are called capsid proteins or viral coat proteins (VCP). ",
            "keyString": "913268s35m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Radish is a",
            "optionA": "  bulb ",
            "optionB": "  conn ",
            "optionC": "  modified root ",
            "optionD": "  tuber ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRadish is a modified root. ",
            "keyString": "913315s35m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "When more than 20% of the body weight is due to fat, the person is suffering from",
            "optionA": "  Marasmus ",
            "optionB": "  Kwashiorkor ",
            "optionC": "  Scurvy ",
            "optionD": "  Obesity ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tObesity - when body fat exceeds 30% of total weight. ",
            "keyString": "967668s35m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Bone deformities occur due to the excess intake of",
            "optionA": "  Phosphorus ",
            "optionB": "  Potassium ",
            "optionC": "  Fatty acid ",
            "optionD": "  Fluorine ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tWhen there is an excessive intake of fluorine in the diet, the person suffers from many dental and bone-related deformities.The long bones are affected which results in breaking and fractures in the bones.There is a reduction in bone density and elasticity which results in osteosclerosis.There are problems with dental fluorosis in cases of children during the growth of the teeth in case of a high intake of fluorine. Thus, the correct answer is option D.",
            "keyString": "967767s35m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Cellulose is a",
            "optionA": "  Mineral ",
            "optionB": "  Protein ",
            "optionC": "  Fat ",
            "optionD": "  Carbohydrate ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCellulose is a carbohydrate formed by a linear polymerisation of \u03b2-D-glucose units, which in contrast to starch, is oriented with \u2212 CH2OH groups, alternating above and below the plane of the cellulose molecule, thus producing long, unbranched chains.",
            "keyString": "967826s35m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Deficiency of 'Thiamine' causes",
            "optionA": "  Beri-Beri ",
            "optionB": "  Pellagra ",
            "optionC": "  Anaemia ",
            "optionD": "  Rickets ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThiamine deficiency, or beriberi, refers to the lack of thiamine. ",
            "keyString": "967875s35m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Kwashiorkor disease in children is caused by",
            "optionA": "  Sufficient carbohydrates but less fats in diet ",
            "optionB": "  Sufficient carbohydrates and fats but deficient proteins in diet ",
            "optionC": "  Sufficient vitamins but deficient fats in diet ",
            "optionD": "  Sufficient fats but deficient vitamins in diet ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tKwashiorkor is caused by a lack of protein in the diet. Every cell in your body contains protein. You need protein in your diet for your body to repair cells and make new cells. ",
            "keyString": "967924s35m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "A man whose blood group is not known meet with a serious accident and needs blood transfusion immediately. Which one of the blood group mentioned below and readily available in the hospital will be safe for transfusion?",
            "optionA": "  O, Rh- ",
            "optionB": "  O, Rh+ ",
            "optionC": "  AB, Rh- ",
            "optionD": "  AB, Rh+ ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDonors with blood group O, Rh- can donate to recipients with blood types A, B, AB and O (O is the universal donor), because it does not have any antigen, thereby no reaction would occur with the antibody, which may be present in donor's body. Hence, option A is correct. ",
            "keyString": "103972s36m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which letter indicates systolic pressure?",
            "optionA": "  I ",
            "optionB": "  B ",
            "optionC": "  C ",
            "optionD": "  A ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tLetter A indicates systolic pressure. ",
            "keyString": "104043s36m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The first heart transplantation was performed by",
            "optionA": "  Dr. W. Harbe ",
            "optionB": "  Sir F.G. Hafkin ",
            "optionC": "  Dr. Louis Pasteur ",
            "optionD": "  Dr. ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tChristiaan Barnard with his team, performed the world's first human-to-human heart transplant operation on 3 December 1967. ",
            "keyString": "104095s36m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is true about blood plasma?",
            "optionA": "  The main protein component is hemoglobin ",
            "optionB": "  It is a faint yellow fluid ",
            "optionC": "  It is the same as serum but without the clotting proteins ",
            "optionD": "  It is about 90% water ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe first option is incorrect because it is devoid of blood cell, also red blood cells so doesn\u2019t contains haemoglobin.The second option is incorrect because plasma is colorless.The third option is also incorrect because plasma contains the clotting factors. ",
            "keyString": "104143s36m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Most of the oxygen transported by the blood is",
            "optionA": "  Bound to haemoglobin ",
            "optionB": "  Dissolved in plasma ",
            "optionC": "  Dissolved in water ",
            "optionD": "  In ionic form as solute in plasma ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOxygen is carried in the blood in two forms: (1) dissolved in plasma and RBC water (about 2% of the total) and (2) reversibly bound to hemoglobin (about 98% of the total). ",
            "keyString": "104191s36m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Number of which type of WBC is greatest in blood of human?",
            "optionA": "  Eosinophils ",
            "optionB": "  Basiophils ",
            "optionC": "  Lymphocytes ",
            "optionD": "  Neutrophils ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNeutrophils are the most abundant white blood cell, constituting 60-70% of the circulating leukocytes, and including two functionally unequal subpopulations: neutrophil-killers and neutrophil-cagers. They defend against bacterial or fungal infection. ",
            "keyString": "155180s36m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Blood is",
            "optionA": "  Alkaline ",
            "optionB": "  Neutral ",
            "optionC": "  Like a buffer ",
            "optionD": "  Acidic ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBlood is alkaline. ",
            "keyString": "155253s36m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Blood pressure is measured with",
            "optionA": "  Thermometer ",
            "optionB": "  Barometer ",
            "optionC": "  Sphygmomanometer ",
            "optionD": "  Lactometer ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBlood pressure is measured with Sphygmomanometer. ",
            "keyString": "155305s36m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is true about veins?",
            "optionA": "  Veins carry blood away from the heart, while arteries carry blood to the heart ",
            "optionB": "  Veins are more muscular than arteries ",
            "optionC": "  Veins have valves; arteries do not ",
            "optionD": "  Veins have a smaller diameter lumen than arteries ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tVeins are blood vessels that carry blood toward the heart. Most veins carry deoxygenated blood from the tissues back to the heart; exceptions are the pulmonary and umbilical veins, both of which carry oxygenated blood to the heart. In contrast to veins, arteries carry blood away from the heart. Veins are less muscular than arteries and are often closer to the skin. There are valves in most veins to prevent backflow. ",
            "keyString": "155354s36m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following serve as antibodies?",
            "optionA": "  Proteins ",
            "optionB": "  Lipids ",
            "optionC": "  Carbohydrates ",
            "optionD": "  Nucleic acids ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tProteins serve as antibodies. ",
            "keyString": "155402s36m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "One day you wake with a sore throat and a runny nose. Your doctor takes a swab from your throat, sends it to a lab, and telephones you the next day to say that antibiotic will not help you get better. Which of the following is the most likely reason for the doctor's statement?",
            "optionA": "  Having waited a day, it is too late to take an antibiotic ",
            "optionB": "  You need an antiseptic, not an antibiotic ",
            "optionC": "  You need to be vaccinated instead of taking an antibiotic ",
            "optionD": "  You are infected by a virus ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe most likely reason for the doctor's statement is that the person is infected by a virus. ",
            "keyString": "204517s36m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Plants that grow under average temperature and moisture are called:",
            "optionA": "  halophytes ",
            "optionB": "  hydrophytes ",
            "optionC": "  mesophytes ",
            "optionD": "  xerophytes ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPlants that grow under average temperature and moisture are called mesophytes. ",
            "keyString": "204606s36m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Oxyreductases, transferases, hydrolases, lyases, isomerases and ligases are all classes of",
            "optionA": "  hormones ",
            "optionB": "  enzymes ",
            "optionC": "  proteins ",
            "optionD": "  vitamins ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOxyreductases, transferases, hydrolases, lyases, isomerases and ligases are all classes of enzymes. ",
            "keyString": "204669s36m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Mutation is",
            "optionA": "  a factor responsible for plant growth ",
            "optionB": "  a change which affects the offspring of F2 generation only ",
            "optionC": "  a change that is inherited ",
            "optionD": "  a change which affects the parents ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA mutation is a change in a DNA sequence. Mutations can result from DNA copying mistakes made during cell division, exposure to ionizing radiation, exposure to chemicals called mutagens, or infection by viruses. ",
            "keyString": "204725s36m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Pollination by wind is called",
            "optionA": "  anemophily ",
            "optionB": "  hydrophily ",
            "optionC": "  zoophily ",
            "optionD": "  entomophily ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAnemophily is the process when pollen is transported by air currents from one individual plant to another. About 12% of the world's flowering plants are wind-pollinated, including grasses and cereal crops, many trees, and the infamous allergenic ragweeds. ",
            "keyString": "204776s36m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Pressure, pain, and temperature receptors in the skin are",
            "optionA": "  Exteroceptors ",
            "optionB": "  Proprioceptors ",
            "optionC": "  Interoceptors ",
            "optionD": "  Mechanoreceptors ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPressure, pain, and temperature receptors in the skin are exteroceptors. ",
            "keyString": "261599s36m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Goosebumps are caused by contractions of the",
            "optionA": "  Muscles ",
            "optionB": "  Nerves ",
            "optionC": "  Bones ",
            "optionD": "  All of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGoosebumps are caused by the contraction of the tiny arrectores pilorum muscles attached to hair follicles, according to Dr. Allan L. Lorincz, a dermatologist at the University of Chicago. ",
            "keyString": "261639s36m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Lacrymal glands are situated in the",
            "optionA": "  Palms ",
            "optionB": "  Buccal cavity ",
            "optionC": "  Buccal cavity ",
            "optionD": "  Stomach ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tLacrymal glands are situated in the buccal cavity. ",
            "keyString": "261654s36m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following acts as an insulator against heat, cold and as a shock-absorber in the body?",
            "optionA": "  Dermis ",
            "optionB": "  Epidermis ",
            "optionC": "  Subcutaneous fat layer ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSubcutaneous fat layer acts as an insulator against heat, cold and as a shock-absorber in the body. ",
            "keyString": "261666s36m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "A/An ________ tissue is formed beneath the skin and between internal organs.",
            "optionA": "  Epithelial ",
            "optionB": "  Nervous ",
            "optionC": "  Muscular ",
            "optionD": "  Adipose ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA adipose tissue is formed beneath the skin and between internal organs. ",
            "keyString": "261677s36m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "During which phase or phase of cell division, the morphology of the chromosomes is best studied?",
            "optionA": "  Telophase, anaphase ",
            "optionB": "  Prohase, anaphase ",
            "optionC": "  Anaphase, metaphase ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tChromosomal morphology is best observed at metaphase. Metaphase is a stage of mitosis in the cell cycle in which chromosomes are at their most condensed and coiled stage. ",
            "keyString": "301663s36m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Metaphase is followed by the next phase of mitosis called",
            "optionA": "  Anaphase ",
            "optionB": "  Prophase ",
            "optionC": "  Interphase ",
            "optionD": "  Anaphase ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThese phases occur in strict sequential order, and cytokinesis - the process of dividing the cell contents to make two new cells - starts in anaphase or telophase. Stages of mitosis: prophase, metaphase, anaphase, telophase. Cytokinesis typically overlaps with anaphase and/or telophase. ",
            "keyString": "301740s36m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "It is a process which converts a single-celled zygote into a great number of cells, which then differentiate into tissues.",
            "optionA": "  Mitosis ",
            "optionB": "  Meiosis ",
            "optionC": "  Fractionation ",
            "optionD": "  Regenration ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMitosis is a process which converts a single-celled zygote into a great number of cells, which then differentiate into tissues. ",
            "keyString": "301798s36m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which division is responsible for the continuity of hereditary information?",
            "optionA": "  Mitosis ",
            "optionB": "  Meiosis ",
            "optionC": "  Regeneration ",
            "optionD": "  All of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe purpose of mitosis is to maintain continuity among cell progeny, meaning that if a tissue is made of thousands of cells that resulted from many mitosis events, each cell has the same number of genes as the original cell. ",
            "keyString": "301850s36m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The type of division which occurs in somatic cells is known as",
            "optionA": "  Mitosis ",
            "optionB": "  Meiosis ",
            "optionC": "  Binary Fission ",
            "optionD": "  Regeration ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMost of the time when people refer to \u201ccell division,\u201d they mean mitosis, the process of making new body cells and it occurs in all somatic cells. Meiosis is the type of cell division that creates egg and sperm cells i.e. Germ cells which are helpful in sexual reproduction. ",
            "keyString": "301900s36m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following hormones is essential for the uptake of glucose by cells in the human body?",
            "optionA": "  GH ",
            "optionB": "  TSH ",
            "optionC": "  Insulin ",
            "optionD": "  Cortisol ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tInsulin is an essential hormone produced by the pancreas. Its main role is to control glucose levels in our bodies. ",
            "keyString": "358362s36m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Goitre is caused by the deficiency of ________ ",
            "optionA": "  Zinc ",
            "optionB": "  Calcium ",
            "optionC": "  Iodine ",
            "optionD": "  Chlorine ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIodine deficiency is the main cause of goitre. Iodine is essential to helping your thyroid produce thyroid hormones. ",
            "keyString": "358391s36m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Endocrine glands are also known as",
            "optionA": "  Micro gland ",
            "optionB": "  Macro gland ",
            "optionC": "  Ductless gland ",
            "optionD": "  Acidic gland ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tEndocrine glands are also known as the ductless glands because of the fact that their secretions are released directly into the blood, not to any tubes or ducts. ",
            "keyString": "358404s36m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Enzymes are produced by",
            "optionA": "  Endocrine glands ",
            "optionB": "  Exocrine glands ",
            "optionC": "  Liver ",
            "optionD": "  Spleen ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tEnzymes are produced naturally in the body. For example, enzymes are required for proper digestive system function. Digestive enzymes are mostly produced in the pancreas, stomach, and small intestine. ",
            "keyString": "358416s36m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of following is a ductless gland?",
            "optionA": "  Liver ",
            "optionB": "  Sweat gland ",
            "optionC": "  Endocrine gland ",
            "optionD": "  Kidney ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tEndocrine glands are ductless glands of the endocrine system that secrete their products, hormones, directly into the blood.",
            "keyString": "358427s36m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Slow oxidative muscle fibers are best suited for",
            "optionA": "  Hitting football ",
            "optionB": "  Heavy workout in the gym ",
            "optionC": "  Running a marathon ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSlow oxidative muscle fibers are best suited for running a marathon. ",
            "keyString": "394868s36m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which body cavities are the lungs located",
            "optionA": "  Pelvic cavity ",
            "optionB": "  Thoracic cavity ",
            "optionC": "  Abdominal cavity ",
            "optionD": "  Body cavity ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe lungs are located in thoracic cavity. ",
            "keyString": "394898s36m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The molecule that is the main source of ATP synthesis",
            "optionA": "  Glucose  ",
            "optionB": "  Triglycerides  ",
            "optionC": "  Proteins  ",
            "optionD": "  Cholesterol  ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn general, the main energy source for cellular metabolism is glucose, which is catabolized in the three subsequent processes\u2014glycolysis, tricarboxylic acid cycle (TCA or Krebs cycle), and finally oxidative phosphorylation\u2014to produce ATP. ",
            "keyString": "394912s36m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Lungs are covered by",
            "optionA": "  Pericardium  ",
            "optionB": "  Pleura  ",
            "optionC": "  Peritoneum  ",
            "optionD": "  Meninges  ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe lungs are surrounded by two membranes, the pleurae. The outer pleura is attached to the chest wall and is known as the parietal pleura; the inner one is attached to the lung and other visceral tissues and is known as the visceral pleura. So, the correct answer is option C. ",
            "keyString": "394924s36m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Accumulation of which one of the following leads to cramp?",
            "optionA": "  Lactic acid ",
            "optionB": "  Ethanol ",
            "optionC": "  Pyruvic acid ",
            "optionD": "  Glucose ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe accumulation of lactic acid is the main reason for the formation of cramps in sprinters. ",
            "keyString": "394936s36m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Mode of nutrition in which particulate food is devoured is ",
            "optionA": "  Holozoic ",
            "optionB": "  Holophytic ",
            "optionC": "  Saprophytic ",
            "optionD": "  Parasitic ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe feeding mechanism is of several types. If it is entirely plant-like (photosynthesis),it is called holophytic. It is entirely (holo) animal-like (zoic), that is devouring already existing food, it is called holozoic. ",
            "keyString": "430464s36m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "They are organic compounds consisting of carbon, hydrogen and oxygen present in all living organisms.",
            "optionA": "  Proteins ",
            "optionB": "  Carbohydrates ",
            "optionC": "  Fats ",
            "optionD": "  Minerals ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCarbohydrates are organic molecules that consist of carbon, hydrogen, and oxygen. They are made up of repeating units called saccharides. They provide cells with energy, store energy, and form structural tissues. ",
            "keyString": "430494s36m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The energy released by 1 gram of glucose is",
            "optionA": "  6 kcal ",
            "optionB": "  4 kcal ",
            "optionC": "  5 kcal ",
            "optionD": "  3kcal ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe energy released by 1 gram of glucose is 4 kcal. ",
            "keyString": "430508s36m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Among the given nutrients, milk is a poor source of",
            "optionA": "  Calcium ",
            "optionB": "  Protein ",
            "optionC": "  Carbohydrate ",
            "optionD": "  Vitamin C ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAmong the given nutrients, milk is a poor source of Vitamin C. ",
            "keyString": "430520s36m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which nutrient forms most of our body weight?",
            "optionA": "  Water ",
            "optionB": "  Fats ",
            "optionC": "  Carbohydrates ",
            "optionD": "  Proteins ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tWater is a nutrient that makes up 60% of our body weight. ",
            "keyString": "430531s36m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Source of infection in diseases like Tuberculosis, Mumps and Whooping cough is",
            "optionA": "  Direct contact ",
            "optionB": "  Droplets of saliva ",
            "optionC": "  Carrier organism ",
            "optionD": "  A vector ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTuberculosis, mumps and whooping cough are the contagious types of diseases. The diseases can spread through the droplets or the aerosols which are formed during coughing or sneezing. These aerosols contain the bacterium. The bacterium may enter the other person's body who is healthy and cause infection.",
            "keyString": "507812s36m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Anopheles mosquito carries Plasmodium which causes malaria in ",
            "optionA": "  Humans ",
            "optionB": "  Animals ",
            "optionC": "  Sparrows ",
            "optionD": "  All of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAnopheles mosquito carries Plasmodium which causes malaria in humans. ",
            "keyString": "507841s36m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Anopheles mosquito carries Plasmodium which causes malaria in ",
            "optionA": "  Humans ",
            "optionB": "  Animals ",
            "optionC": "  Sparrows ",
            "optionD": "  All of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": "\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tNo explanation is given for this questionLet's Discuss on Board ",
            "keyString": "507854s36m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which is called as triple vaccine?",
            "optionA": "  BCG  ",
            "optionB": "  DTP  ",
            "optionC": "  TAB  ",
            "optionD": "  All of the above  ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDiphtheria is readily preventable by vaccine administration. This is included in the triple vaccine: diphtheria, tetanus and pertussis vaccine (DTP) or the quintuple diphtheria, tetanus, pertussis, polio and Hib vaccine. ",
            "keyString": "507866s36m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is an Abiotic factor?",
            "optionA": "  Plants ",
            "optionB": "  Water ",
            "optionC": "  Consumers ",
            "optionD": "  Animals ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAbiotic factors are the non-living parts of the environment that can often have a major influence on living organisms. Abiotic factors include water, sunlight, oxygen, soil and temperature. ",
            "keyString": "507877s36m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Every ecosystem must have",
            "optionA": "  Autotrophs ",
            "optionB": "  Heterotrophs ",
            "optionC": "  Both A & B ",
            "optionD": "  Photosynthesizers ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tEvery ecosystem must have Autotrophs. ",
            "keyString": "545166s36m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Silviculture is the branch of botany in which we study about",
            "optionA": "  Culture of algae ",
            "optionB": "  Development of forest ",
            "optionC": "  Culture of fungi ",
            "optionD": "  Silciphida plant ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSilviculture is the branch of botany in which we study about the development of forest. ",
            "keyString": "545201s36m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is an Autotroph?",
            "optionA": "  Fish ",
            "optionB": "  Algae ",
            "optionC": "  Butterfly ",
            "optionD": "  Mushroom ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAn autotroph is an organism that can produce its own food using light, water, carbon dioxide, or other chemicals. Algae is an autotroph. ",
            "keyString": "545218s36m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The energy in most ecosystems comes from",
            "optionA": "  Water ",
            "optionB": "  Carbon dioxide ",
            "optionC": "  Sun ",
            "optionD": "  Soil ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe vast majority of energy in food webs originates from the sun. Energy is not recycled in ecosystems and each ecosystem requires a continuous input of energy to sustain it. There is some energy transformed at each level of the food chain or food web in an ecosystem. ",
            "keyString": "545231s36m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Study of typical behaviour of organisms in their natural habitat is called",
            "optionA": "  Euthenics ",
            "optionB": "  Eugenics ",
            "optionC": "  Ethology ",
            "optionD": "  Ethnology ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tEthology is a field of basic biology, like ecology or genetics. It focuses on the behaviors of diverse organisms in their natural environment. Comparative psychology is an extension of work done in human psychology. ",
            "keyString": "545244s36m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Primary phloem develops from",
            "optionA": "  lateral meristem ",
            "optionB": "  protoderm ",
            "optionC": "  extrastelar cambium ",
            "optionD": "  provascular tissue ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPrimary phloem develops from provascular tissue. ",
            "keyString": "580360s36m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Other than spreading malaria, anopheles mosquitoes are also vectors of",
            "optionA": "  dengue fever ",
            "optionB": "  filariasis ",
            "optionC": "  encephalitis ",
            "optionD": "  yellow fever ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOther than spreading malaria, anopheles mosquitoes are also vectors of filariasis. ",
            "keyString": "580388s36m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Plants that grow in saline water are called",
            "optionA": "  halophytes ",
            "optionB": "  hydrophytes ",
            "optionC": "  mesophytes ",
            "optionD": "  thallophytes ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA halophyte is a salt-tolerant plant that grows in soil or waters of high salinity, coming into contact with saline water through its roots or by salt spray, such as in saline semi-deserts, mangrove swamps, marshes and sloughs and seashores. ",
            "keyString": "580402s36m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Pyorrhoea is a disease of the",
            "optionA": "  nose ",
            "optionB": "  gums ",
            "optionC": "  heart ",
            "optionD": "  lungs ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPyorrhoea, or periodontal disease, to give it a proper medical term, is a disease of the gums, it is one of the most widely prevalent diseases. It affects the membrane surrounding the roots of the teeth and leads to loosening of the teeth, pus formation, and shrinkage of the gum. This disease is the primary cause for tooth loss among adults. ",
            "keyString": "580413s36m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "O2 released in the process of photosynthesis comes from",
            "optionA": "  CO2 ",
            "optionB": "  water ",
            "optionC": "  sugar ",
            "optionD": "  pyruvic acid ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPhotosynthesis is the process by which plants use the energy of light to produce carbohydrates and molecular oxygen (O2) from carbon dioxide (CO2) and water. ",
            "keyString": "580424s36m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Night Blindness is caused by deficiency of which of the following Vitamin?",
            "optionA": "  Vitamin B ",
            "optionB": "  Vitamin C ",
            "optionC": "  Vitamin K ",
            "optionD": "  Vitamin A ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tVitamin A deficiency can result from inadequate intake, fat malabsorption, or liver disorders. Deficiency impairs immunity and hematopoiesis and causes rashes and typical ocular effects (eg, xerophthalmia, night blindness). ",
            "keyString": "615814s36m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Organisms that feed on the excreta of other organisms are called ",
            "optionA": "  Autotrophs ",
            "optionB": "  Heterotrophs ",
            "optionC": "  Coprophagous ",
            "optionD": "  Saprotrophs ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCoprophagia or coprophagy is the consumption of faeces. Coprophagy refers to all kinds of faeces eating including eating faeces of other species (heterospecific), of other individuals (allocoprophagy), or its own (autocoprophagy), those once deposited or taken directly from the anus. So, the correct answer is 'Coprophagus' ",
            "keyString": "615842s36m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following vitamin helps in clotting of blood?",
            "optionA": "  Vitamin K ",
            "optionB": "  Vitamin D ",
            "optionC": "  Vitamin B1 ",
            "optionD": "  Vitamin B2 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tVitamin K is a nutrient that the body needs to stay healthy. It's important for blood clotting and healthy bones and also has other functions in the body. ",
            "keyString": "615855s36m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Anaemia is due to deficiency of",
            "optionA": "  Ca ",
            "optionB": "  Fe ",
            "optionC": "  Mg ",
            "optionD": "  P ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIron deficiency anaemia is a common type of anaemia a condition in which blood lacks adequate healthy red blood cells.",
            "keyString": "615866s36m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In what chief capacity does vitamin k function?",
            "optionA": "  Raise plasma calcium ",
            "optionB": "  Blood clot ",
            "optionC": "  Produce rhodopsin ",
            "optionD": "  Bone density ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tHealth benefits and sources of vitamin K. Vitamin K refers to a group of fat-soluble vitamins that play a role in blood clotting, bone metabolism, and regulating blood calcium levels. The body needs vitamin K to produce prothrombin, a protein and clotting factor that is important in blood clotting and bone metabolism. ",
            "keyString": "615877s36m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following micro-organism causes diseases like polio and chicken pox?",
            "optionA": "  Bacteria ",
            "optionB": "  Protozoa ",
            "optionC": "  Algae ",
            "optionD": "  Virus ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSerious diseases like polio and chicken pox are caused by viruses. ",
            "keyString": "650624s36m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What kingdom does Amoeba belong to",
            "optionA": "  Plantae ",
            "optionB": "  Protista ",
            "optionC": "  Monera ",
            "optionD": "  Prokaryotae ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAmoeba belongs to kingdom protista. ",
            "keyString": "650663s36m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which bacteria cause the greatest harm in the food industry?",
            "optionA": "  Recycling ",
            "optionB": "  Digestive ",
            "optionC": "  Fermenting ",
            "optionD": "  Pathogenic ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPathogenic bacteria cause the greatest harm in the food industry. ",
            "keyString": "650680s36m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Bacteria divides by",
            "optionA": "  Binary Fission ",
            "optionB": "  Spirilla ",
            "optionC": "  RNA ",
            "optionD": "  Fusion ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBacteria reproduce by binary fission. In this process the bacterium, which is a single cell, divides into two identical daughter cells. Binary fission begins when the DNA of the bacterium divides into two (replicates). ",
            "keyString": "650695s36m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Important plant diseases like fire-blight and crown all are caused by",
            "optionA": "  Viruses ",
            "optionB": "  Bacteria ",
            "optionC": "  Fungi ",
            "optionD": "  Protozoans ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tImportant plant diseases like fire-blight and crown all are caused by bacteria. ",
            "keyString": "650708s36m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In human the thickest skin is present in",
            "optionA": "  Palm ",
            "optionB": "  Sole ",
            "optionC": "  Neck ",
            "optionD": "  Head ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tEpidermis varies in thickness throughout the body depending mainly on frictional forces and is thickest on the palms of the hands and soles of the feet, and thinnest in the face (eyelids) and genitalia. ",
            "keyString": "686620s36m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "They form the material which forms skins, muscles, hair and nails in animals.",
            "optionA": "  Protein ",
            "optionB": "  Carbohydrates ",
            "optionC": "  Fats ",
            "optionD": "  Vitamins ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tKeratinocytes make keratin, a type of protein that's a basic component of hair, skin, and nails. Keratin in the skin's outer layer helps create a protective barrier. ",
            "keyString": "686649s36m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is responsible for giving colour to human skin?",
            "optionA": "  Luciferin ",
            "optionB": "  Haemoglobin ",
            "optionC": "  Flavonoids ",
            "optionD": "  Melanin ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe actual skin color of different humans is affected by many substances, although the single most important substance is the pigment melanin. Melanin is produced within the skin in cells called melanocytes and it is the main determinant of the skin color of darker-skin humans. ",
            "keyString": "686663s36m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which is the largest organ in the human body?",
            "optionA": "  Heart ",
            "optionB": "  Brain ",
            "optionC": "  Skin ",
            "optionD": "  Liver ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBody organs aren't all internal like the brain or the heart. There's one we wear on the outside. Skin is our largest organ\u2014adults carry some 8 pounds (3.6 kilograms) and 22 square feet (2 square meters) of it. ",
            "keyString": "686674s36m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Branch of science which deals with the study of skin of man is called",
            "optionA": "  Physiology ",
            "optionB": "  Anatomy ",
            "optionC": "  Biochemistry ",
            "optionD": "  Dermatology ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDermatology is the branch of science which deals with the study of skin. ",
            "keyString": "686686s36m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Deficiency of which of the following causes non-clotting of blood?",
            "optionA": "  Vitamin C ",
            "optionB": "  Vitamin K ",
            "optionC": "  Vitamin E ",
            "optionD": "  Vitamin B12 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDeficiency of vitamin K causes non-clotting of blood. ",
            "keyString": "722031s36m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Organisms need nutrients in order to",
            "optionA": "  Breaking down food ",
            "optionB": "  Utilize chemical compounds ",
            "optionC": "  Recycling ",
            "optionD": "  None ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThey are necessary to the lives of people, plants, animals, and all other organisms. Nutrients help break down food to give organisms energy. They are used in every process of an organism's body. Some of the processes are growth (building cells), repair (healing a wound), and maintaining life (breathing). ",
            "keyString": "722058s36m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Sugar is a component of which of the following?",
            "optionA": "  Lipids ",
            "optionB": "  Nucleic acids ",
            "optionC": "  Carbohydrates ",
            "optionD": "  Both B & C ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSugar is a component of carbohydrates. ",
            "keyString": "722071s36m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The main protein found in milk is ________ ",
            "optionA": "  Albumin ",
            "optionB": "  Globulin ",
            "optionC": "  Globin ",
            "optionD": "  Casein ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCasein and whey protein are the major proteins of milk. ",
            "keyString": "722083s36m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following vitamins is known as the anti sterile factor?",
            "optionA": "  Ascorbic acid ",
            "optionB": "  Riboflavin ",
            "optionC": "  Niacin ",
            "optionD": "  Retinol ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRiboflavin is known as the anti sterile factor. ",
            "keyString": "722094s36m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Infection of salivary glands by a virus leads to ",
            "optionA": "  Tetanus ",
            "optionB": "  Mumps ",
            "optionC": "  Pyorrhoea ",
            "optionD": "  Ulcers ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn general, viral infections of the salivary gland may result in reduced saliva production and/or swelling. Mumps is the most common salivary gland infection caused by paramyxovirus. ",
            "keyString": "757166s36m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which virus causes Chicken Pox?",
            "optionA": "  Rubella Virus ",
            "optionB": "  Herpes Zoster Virus ",
            "optionC": "  Rabies ",
            "optionD": "  Variola Virus ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tVaricella-zoster is a herpes virus that causes chickenpox, a common childhood illness. It is highly contagious. If an adult develops chickenpox, the illness may be more severe. After a person has had chickenpox, the varicella-zoster virus can remain inactive in the body for many years. ",
            "keyString": "757195s36m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Besides Dog, which one is the other animal that can also cause rabies",
            "optionA": "  Donkey  ",
            "optionB": "  Bat  ",
            "optionC": "  Horse  ",
            "optionD": "  Crocodile  ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAny mammal can get rabies. The most common wild reservoirs of rabies are raccoons, skunks, bats, and foxes. Domestic mammals can also get rabies. Cats, cattle, and dogs are the most frequently reported rabid domestic animals in the United States. ",
            "keyString": "757209s36m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Theilreia parva causes infection in",
            "optionA": "  Dog  ",
            "optionB": "  Buffalo  ",
            "optionC": "  Cat  ",
            "optionD": "  Horse  ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTheilreia parva causes infection in buffalo. ",
            "keyString": "757222s36m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The interferons are",
            "optionA": "  Antiviral proteins  ",
            "optionB": "  Antibiotic proteins  ",
            "optionC": "  Antigen proteins  ",
            "optionD": "  All of these  ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tInterferons (IFNs) are proteins made and released by host cells in response to the presence of pathogens such as viruses, bacteria, parasites, or tumor cells.",
            "keyString": "757234s36m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In man there are how many pairs of homologous chromosomes?",
            "optionA": "  46 ",
            "optionB": "  23 ",
            "optionC": "  16 ",
            "optionD": "  11 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn humans, each cell normally contains 23 pairs of chromosomes, for a total of 46. ",
            "keyString": "792599s36m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "It is composed of two polynucleotide chains which are coiled around each other in the form of a double helix.",
            "optionA": "  DNA ",
            "optionB": "  RNA ",
            "optionC": "  Fats ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDNA) is a molecule composed of two polynucleotide chains that coil around each other to form a double helix carrying genetic instructions for the development, functioning, growth and reproduction of all known organisms and many viruses. DNA and ribonucleic acid (RNA) are nucleic acids. ",
            "keyString": "792627s36m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "How many chromosomes are in a human gamete?",
            "optionA": "  23 ",
            "optionB": "  46 ",
            "optionC": "  92 ",
            "optionD": "  102 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn humans, each cell normally contains 23 pairs of chromosomes, for a total of 46.",
            "keyString": "792640s36m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What is the unit of heredity?",
            "optionA": "  Cell ",
            "optionB": "  Blood ",
            "optionC": "  Gene ",
            "optionD": "  All of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA gene is the basic physical and functional unit of heredity. Genes are made up of DNA.",
            "keyString": "792652s36m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who discovered genetic material?",
            "optionA": "  Crick and Watson ",
            "optionB": "  Avery Mclood ",
            "optionC": "  Friedrich Griffith ",
            "optionD": "  Federik Meischer ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn the 1920s, Frederick Griffith made an important discovery. He was studying two different strains of a bacterium, called R (rough) strain and S (smooth) strain. ",
            "keyString": "792662s36m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which Vitamin is obtained from Sun rays?",
            "optionA": "  Vitamin A ",
            "optionB": "  Vitamin C ",
            "optionC": "  Vitamin K ",
            "optionD": "  Vitamin D ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tVitamin D is the sunshine vitamin that has been produced on this earth for more than 500 million years. During exposure to sunlight 7-dehydrocholesterol in the skin absorbs UV B radiation and is converted to previtamin D3 which in turn isomerizes into vitamin D3. ",
            "keyString": "827402s36m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Vitamin required for the synthesis of nucleic acid is",
            "optionA": "  Tocoferorl ",
            "optionB": "  Folic acid ",
            "optionC": "  Cyanocobalamine ",
            "optionD": "  Riboflavin ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAccording to Stokes, folic acid may function in an enzyme system responsible for the synthesis of thymine, which in turn is used for forming nucleic acids. ",
            "keyString": "827430s36m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following statements is not true about metabolism?",
            "optionA": "  Younger people generally have a slower metabolism than adults ",
            "optionB": "  Basal metabolism is the amount of energy needed for sustaining life ",
            "optionC": "  Basal metabolism is measured by the amount of calories burned when your body is inactive ",
            "optionD": "  Metabolism is influenced by numerous factors, such as heredity and age ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMetabolism is the set of life-sustaining chemical transformations within the cells of organisms. The three main purposes of metabolism are the conversion of food/fuel to energy to run cellular processes, the conversion of food/fuel to building blocks for proteins, lipids, nucleic acids, and some carbohydrates, and the elimination of nitrogenous wastes. Younger people have faster metabolism than adults. Hence, the given statement 'Younger people generally have a slower metabolism than adults' is false. ",
            "keyString": "827443s36m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "An important function of fat in the body is to",
            "optionA": "  Protect vital organs ",
            "optionB": "  Stores energy ",
            "optionC": "  Insulate us ",
            "optionD": "  All of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe body uses fat as a fuel source, and fat is the major storage form of energy in the body. Fat also has many other important functions in the body, and a moderate amount is needed in the diet for good health. ",
            "keyString": "827456s36m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Vitamin K is required for",
            "optionA": "  Blood clotting ",
            "optionB": "  Respiration ",
            "optionC": "  Carbohydrate metabolism ",
            "optionD": "  Calcium phosphorus ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tVitamin K is required for blood clotting. ",
            "keyString": "827467s36m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is an example of parasitism?",
            "optionA": "  Leeches consume blood of their host ",
            "optionB": "  Ticks that live on dogs ",
            "optionC": "  Aphid insects eat the sap of the host plant ",
            "optionD": "  All of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAll of the above are examples of parasitism. ",
            "keyString": "882574s36m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "________ is the interaction in which one species benefits and the other is neither harmed nor benefited.",
            "optionA": "  Predation ",
            "optionB": "  Commensalism ",
            "optionC": "  Competition ",
            "optionD": "  Parasitism ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCommensalism is an interaction in which one individual benefits while the other is neither helped nor harmed. ",
            "keyString": "882603s36m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Consider the following statements1. Different plant species grow together2. Light cannot penetrate into the lower strata full of undergrowth Which of the following type of vegetation is characterized by the above?",
            "optionA": "  Equatorial moist evergreen ",
            "optionB": "  Tropical deciduous ",
            "optionC": "  Mediterranean ",
            "optionD": "  Warm temperate broad leaved deciduous ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tEquatorial moist evergreen vegetation is characterized by the above statement. ",
            "keyString": "882616s36m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "It is the branch of biology which deals with the study of relationship between organisms and their environment.",
            "optionA": "  Ecology ",
            "optionB": "  Taxonomy ",
            "optionC": "  Evolution ",
            "optionD": "  Genetics ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tEcology is the branch of biology, that deals with the inter-relationships amongst organism and interactions between organisms and their environment. ",
            "keyString": "882629s36m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is responsible for Vermicomposting?",
            "optionA": "  Fungus ",
            "optionB": "  Worms ",
            "optionC": "  Bacteria ",
            "optionD": "  Birds ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tWorms are responsible for Vermicomposting. ",
            "keyString": "882639s36m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The bacterium which reduces the fertility of soil is ",
            "optionA": "  Nitrosomonas sp ",
            "optionB": "  Azotobacter sp ",
            "optionC": "  Nitrobacter sp ",
            "optionD": "  Bacillus dentificans ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBacillus dentificans is the bacterium which reduces the fertility of soil. ",
            "keyString": "917920s36m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "They are used in the retting of flax and hemp.",
            "optionA": "  Viruses ",
            "optionB": "  Bacteria ",
            "optionC": "  Fungi ",
            "optionD": "  Mosses ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBacteria are used in the retting of flax and hemp. ",
            "keyString": "917948s36m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following bacteria is responsible for the formation of curd?",
            "optionA": "  Lycopodium ",
            "optionB": "  Yeast ",
            "optionC": "  Lacto-bacillus ",
            "optionD": "  Fungus ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe preparation of curd requires a lactobacillus bacteria, while yogurt is made using two specific strains of bacteria called Lactobacillus delbrueckii subsp. bulgaricus and Streptococcus thermophilus bacteria. Other strains of lactic acid bacteria may also be added. ",
            "keyString": "917962s36m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Yeast used in making bread is a",
            "optionA": "  Fungus ",
            "optionB": "  Bacteria ",
            "optionC": "  Seed ",
            "optionD": "  Plant ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBaker's yeast is the common name for the strains of yeast commonly used in baking bread and bakery products, serving as a leavening agent which causes the bread to rise (expand and become lighter and softer) by converting the fermentable sugars present in the dough into carbon dioxide and ethanol. It is a fungus. ",
            "keyString": "917974s36m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Nitrogen fixation process in the soil is done by",
            "optionA": "  Virus  ",
            "optionB": "  Bacteria  ",
            "optionC": "  Fungi  ",
            "optionD": "  Protoza  ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMost nitrogen fixation occurs naturally, in the soil, by bacteria. ",
            "keyString": "917984s36m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In 1610, who made microscope and used it to observe very small animals?",
            "optionA": "  Robert Hooke ",
            "optionB": "  Galileo ",
            "optionC": "  Aristotle ",
            "optionD": "  Laveran ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGalileo made microscope and used it to observe very small animals. ",
            "keyString": "954096s36m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What three statements make up the cell theory?",
            "optionA": "  All living things are made up of cells ",
            "optionB": "  New cells come frome exisiting cells ",
            "optionC": "  Cells are the basic unit of structure/function in living things ",
            "optionD": "  All of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe unified cell theory states that: all living things are composed of one or more cells; the cell is the basic unit of life; and new cells arise from existing cells. ",
            "keyString": "954128s36m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The outermost layer in a plant cell is",
            "optionA": "  Cell wall ",
            "optionB": "  Cell membrane ",
            "optionC": "  Plasma membrane ",
            "optionD": "  Nuclear membrane ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe outermost layer in a plant cell is cell wall. ",
            "keyString": "954143s36m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The longest cells of human body is",
            "optionA": "  White blood corpuuscles ",
            "optionB": "  Red blood cells ",
            "optionC": "  Neuron cell ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNeurons or nerve cells can be up to 3 feet long. A typical neuron has a cell morphology called soma, hair-like structures called dendrites and an axon. Neurons are specialized in conveying knowledge throughout the body. The sensory neurons, motor neurons, and interneurons are three types of neurons. ",
            "keyString": "954156s36m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "They contain those enzymes which can digest the phagocytosed food particles.",
            "optionA": "  Ribosomes ",
            "optionB": "  Mitochondria ",
            "optionC": "  Lysosomes ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tLysosomes are membrane-enclosed organelles that contain an array of enzymes capable of breaking down all types of biological polymers proteins, nucleic acids, carbohydrates, and lipids. ",
            "keyString": "954169s36m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In plants cells,which structure provides a definite shape to the cell and makes it right?",
            "optionA": "  Cell membrane ",
            "optionB": "  Chitin ",
            "optionC": "  Epidermis ",
            "optionD": "  Cell wall ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPlant cells have a cell wall, as well as a cell membrane. In plants, the cell wall surrounds the cell membrane. This gives the plant cell its unique rectangular shape. ",
            "keyString": "989377s36m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Produces a usable form of energy for the cell",
            "optionA": "  Lysosomes ",
            "optionB": "  Vacuoles ",
            "optionC": "  Mitochondria ",
            "optionD": "  Ribosomes ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMitochondria produces a usable form of energy for the cell. ",
            "keyString": "989405s36m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which among the following is also called as 'power house of the cell'?",
            "optionA": "  Plastids ",
            "optionB": "  Mitochondria ",
            "optionC": "  Golgi bodies ",
            "optionD": "  Cell wall ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMitochondria is also called as 'power house of the cell'. ",
            "keyString": "989419s36m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Volume of blood found in a healthy person is ",
            "optionA": "  3-4 litre ",
            "optionB": "  4-5 litre ",
            "optionC": "  5-6 litre ",
            "optionD": "  6-7 litre ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tVolume of blood found in a healthy person is 5-6 litre. ",
            "keyString": "989432s36m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which blood group is universal donor?",
            "optionA": "  O+ ",
            "optionB": "  O- ",
            "optionC": "  AB- ",
            "optionD": "  AB+ ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFor emergency transfusions, blood group type O negative blood is the variety of blood that has the lowest risk of causing serious reactions for most people who receive it. Because of this, it's sometimes called the universal blood donor type. ",
            "keyString": "989444s36m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Filtration of blood takes place in",
            "optionA": "  Heart ",
            "optionB": "  Kidney ",
            "optionC": "  Liver ",
            "optionD": "  Spleen ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFiltration of blood takes place in kidney. ",
            "keyString": "26084s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In Mammal urinary bladder open into",
            "optionA": "  Uterus ",
            "optionB": "  Urethra ",
            "optionC": "  Vestibule ",
            "optionD": "  Ureter ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe bladder has three openings. The two ureters enter the bladder at ureteric orifices, and the urethra enters at the trigone of the bladder. ",
            "keyString": "26115s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Nephrology is the study of",
            "optionA": "  Lung ",
            "optionB": "  Kidney ",
            "optionC": "  Heart ",
            "optionD": "  Brain ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNephrology is a specialty of medicine and pediatric medicine that concerns with study of the kidneys. ",
            "keyString": "26129s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The organs of the urinary system are",
            "optionA": "  Kidney ",
            "optionB": "  Urinary bladder ",
            "optionC": "  Ureter ",
            "optionD": "  All of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe organs of the urinary system include the kidneys, renal pelvis, ureters, bladder and urethra.",
            "keyString": "26142s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The basic functional unit of kidney is",
            "optionA": "  Henle's loop ",
            "optionB": "  Nephron ",
            "optionC": "  Nephridium ",
            "optionD": "  Pyramid ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe nephron, the functional unit of the kidney, is responsible for removing waste from the body. ",
            "keyString": "26154s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Organisms which synthesise their own food are called",
            "optionA": "  Autotrophs ",
            "optionB": "  Heterotrophs ",
            "optionC": "  Auxotrophs ",
            "optionD": "  Saprotrophs ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAn autotroph is an organism that can produce its own food using light, water, carbon dioxide, or other chemicals. Because autotrophs produce their own food, they are sometimes called producers. ",
            "keyString": "61495s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Anaemia is caused because of deficiency of which of the following?",
            "optionA": "  Cobalt ",
            "optionB": "  Iron ",
            "optionC": "  Sodium ",
            "optionD": "  Calcium ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAs the name implies, iron deficiency anaemia is due to insufficient iron. Without enough iron, your body can't produce enough of a substance in red blood cells that enables them to carry oxygen (hemoglobin). As a result, iron deficiency anaemia may leave you tired and short of breath. ",
            "keyString": "61524s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is a good source of protein?",
            "optionA": "  Pea ",
            "optionB": "  Pigeon Pea ",
            "optionC": "  Black Gram ",
            "optionD": "  Soyabean ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSoyabean is a good source of protein. ",
            "keyString": "61539s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Goitre is due to the deficiency of",
            "optionA": "  Calcium ",
            "optionB": "  Zinc ",
            "optionC": "  Selenium ",
            "optionD": "  Iodine ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe most common cause of goiters worldwide is a lack of iodine in the diet. In the United States, where the use of iodized salt is common, a goiter is more often due to the over- or underproduction of thyroid hormones or to nodules in the gland itself. ",
            "keyString": "61551s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Biological complete proteins are found in",
            "optionA": "  Potato, Onion, Carrot ",
            "optionB": "  Apple, Egg, Wheat ",
            "optionC": "  Rice, Meat, Butter ",
            "optionD": "  Meat, Milk, Egg ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tComplete proteins contain the eight essential amino acids that are needed and can be found in foods such as fish, dairy products, and eggs. ",
            "keyString": "61562s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "When the diaphragm and external intercostal muscles contract,",
            "optionA": "  The volume of the thorax decreases ",
            "optionB": "  The volume of the lungs decreases ",
            "optionC": "  The volume of the thorax increases ",
            "optionD": "  The lungs shrink ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tWhen the diaphragm and external intercostal muscles contract, the volume of the thorax increases. ",
            "keyString": "97698s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Blood leaving lungs, is rich in",
            "optionA": "  Oxygen ",
            "optionB": "  Carbondioxide ",
            "optionC": "  Haemoglobin ",
            "optionD": "  Number of RBC ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBlood leaving lungs, is rich in oxygen. ",
            "keyString": "97727s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The organs protected by the thoracic cage include the",
            "optionA": "  Lungs ",
            "optionB": "  Heart ",
            "optionC": "  Both a & b ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe thoracic cage encloses and protects the organs of the thoracic cavity, including the heart and lungs. ",
            "keyString": "97740s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "By complete oxidation of glucose number of ATP molecule formed is",
            "optionA": "  2 ",
            "optionB": "  28 ",
            "optionC": "  38 ",
            "optionD": "  48 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBy complete oxidation of glucose number of ATP molecule formed is 38. ",
            "keyString": "97752s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "If CO2 concentration in the blood increases, the breathing will",
            "optionA": "  Increase ",
            "optionB": "  Decrease ",
            "optionC": "  Stop ",
            "optionD": "  No effect ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tWhen CO2 concentration in blood increases, breathing becomes faster and deeper.",
            "keyString": "97762s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "When the concentration of water and solutes on either side of the cell membrane is same, the solution is said to be",
            "optionA": "  Hypertonic ",
            "optionB": "  Isotonic ",
            "optionC": "  Hypotonic ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tWhen the concentration of water and solutes on either side of the cell membrane is same, the solution is said to be isotonic. ",
            "keyString": "133996s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Water molecules enter plant epidermal cells by",
            "optionA": "  Active Transport  ",
            "optionB": "  Translocation  ",
            "optionC": "  Osmosis  ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above  ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tWater enters the root hair cells by osmosis. This happens because soil water has a higher water potential than the cytoplasm of the root hair cell. Minerals enter by active transport. ",
            "keyString": "134029s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Root pressure is developed in",
            "optionA": "  Cortex  ",
            "optionB": "  Phloem  ",
            "optionC": "  Xylem  ",
            "optionD": "  Pith  ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRoot pressure, in plants, force that helps to drive fluids upward into the water-conducting vessels (xylem). It is primarily generated by osmotic pressure in the cells of the roots and can be demonstrated by exudation of fluid when the stem is cut off just aboveground. ",
            "keyString": "134046s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What process accounts for species diversity?",
            "optionA": "  Predation ",
            "optionB": "  Mitosis ",
            "optionC": "  Symbiosis ",
            "optionD": "  Meiosis ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMeiosis is the process which accounts for species diversity. Meiosis is termed as a specialized cell division which reduces chromosomes number by half and then creates for haploid cells. ",
            "keyString": "134058s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "When are chromatids found in a cell?",
            "optionA": "  Anaphase ",
            "optionB": "  Metaphase ",
            "optionC": "  Prophase ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tChromatids are found during metaphase. ",
            "keyString": "134072s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Sickle-cell anaemia is due to",
            "optionA": "  Viruses  ",
            "optionB": "  Genes  ",
            "optionC": "  Hormones  ",
            "optionD": "  Bacteria  ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSickle-cell anaemia is due to genes. ",
            "keyString": "206340s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who gave the term \"Antibiotics\"?",
            "optionA": "  Darwin  ",
            "optionB": "  Woodruff  ",
            "optionC": "  Flemming  ",
            "optionD": "  Selman Waksman  ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe word 'antibiotics' was first used over 30 years later by the Ukrainian-American inventor and microbiologist Selman Waksman, who in his lifetime discovered over 20 antibiotics. ",
            "keyString": "206371s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Antibody is produced by",
            "optionA": "  B-lymphocytes  ",
            "optionB": "  Erythrocytes  ",
            "optionC": "  Skin cells  ",
            "optionD": "  Osteoblast  ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAntibody is produced by B-lymphocytes. ",
            "keyString": "206385s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In man which organisms cause abscesses on the skin of arms or legs?",
            "optionA": "  Ascaris ",
            "optionB": "  Bacteria ",
            "optionC": "  Suinea worm ",
            "optionD": "  Ring worm ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn man Suinea worm cause abscesses on the skin of arms or legs ",
            "keyString": "206398s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which disease killed more peoples than any other death causing factors including all other diseases, natural calamities and wars?",
            "optionA": "  Small Pox ",
            "optionB": "  Measles ",
            "optionC": "  Malaria ",
            "optionD": "  Tetanus ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMalaria killed more peoples than any other death causing factors including all other diseases, natural calamities and wars. ",
            "keyString": "206410s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Most common disease of poultry in India is",
            "optionA": "  fowl pox ",
            "optionB": "  tick fever ",
            "optionC": "  ranikhet ",
            "optionD": "  coryza ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMost common disease of poultry in India is ranikhet. ",
            "keyString": "242271s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Most abundant tissues of our body are",
            "optionA": "  muscular ",
            "optionB": "  connective ",
            "optionC": "  epithelial ",
            "optionD": "  nervous ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAmong these Connective Tissue are most abundant in our body. Connective tissue is found in between other tissues everywhere in the body, including the nervous system. ",
            "keyString": "242300s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Mumps is a disease caused by",
            "optionA": "  fungus ",
            "optionB": "  bacterium ",
            "optionC": "  virus ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMumps is a contagious disease that is caused by a virus. It typically starts with a few days of fever, headache, muscle aches, tiredness, and loss of appetite. Then most people will have swelling of their salivary glands. ",
            "keyString": "242313s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Rain water helps to increase the ____ to some extent.",
            "optionA": "  phosphorous contents ",
            "optionB": "  nitrogen contents ",
            "optionC": "  calcium contents ",
            "optionD": "  potash contents ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRain water helps to increase the calcium contents to some extent. ",
            "keyString": "242324s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Number of chromosomes in down's syndrome is",
            "optionA": "  46 ",
            "optionB": "  47 ",
            "optionC": "  48 ",
            "optionD": "  49 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNumber of chromosomes in down's syndrome is 47. ",
            "keyString": "242334s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The trypsinogen is an enzyme secreted by the",
            "optionA": "  Liver  ",
            "optionB": "  Illeum  ",
            "optionC": "  Duodenum  ",
            "optionD": "  Pancreas ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTrypsinogen is the precursor form (or zymogen) of trypsin, a digestive enzyme. It is produced by the pancreas and found in pancreatic juice, along with amylase, lipase, and chymotrypsinogen. ",
            "keyString": "277559s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which body part will be affected with the disease leprosy?",
            "optionA": "  Blood ",
            "optionB": "  Legs ",
            "optionC": "  Skin ",
            "optionD": "  Brain ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tLeprosy is a chronic bacterial infection. It affects the skin and various nervous systems of the body, particularly the peripheral nerves. Leprosy is more common in tropical and subtropical areas. The disease is curable through multi-drug therapy. ",
            "keyString": "277590s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "AIDS is caused by the Human Immunodeficiency Virus (HIV). The transmission of HIV infection generally occurs through",
            "optionA": "  Eating contaminated food and water ",
            "optionB": "  Transfusion of contaminated blood and blood products ",
            "optionC": "  Inhaling polluted air ",
            "optionD": "  Shaking hand with infected person ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe transmission of HIV requires contact with a body fluid that contains the virus or cells infected with the virus. HIV can appear in nearly any body fluid, but transmission occurs mainly through blood, semen, vaginal fluids, and breast milk. ",
            "keyString": "277605s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following diseases is caused by bacteria and spread through faecal matter by houseflies ?",
            "optionA": "  Pertussis ",
            "optionB": "  Typhoid ",
            "optionC": "  Diphtheria ",
            "optionD": "  Chickenpox ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTyphoid is caused by bacteria and spread through faecal matter by houseflies. ",
            "keyString": "277618s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which cells are destroyed in AIDS?",
            "optionA": "  Monocytes ",
            "optionB": "  Neutrophils ",
            "optionC": "  Lymphocytes ",
            "optionD": "  R.",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tLymphocytes are destroyed in AIDS. ",
            "keyString": "277630s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who formulated Cell theory?",
            "optionA": "  Schwan ",
            "optionB": "  M.J.Schleiden ",
            "optionC": "  Henri Dutrochet ",
            "optionD": "  Both Schawn and M.J.Scheilden ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCell theory was formulated by two scientists: Theodor Schwann and Matthias Jakob Schleiden. ",
            "keyString": "313805s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following are known as the suicide bags of cells?",
            "optionA": "  Lysosomes ",
            "optionB": "  Golgi bodies ",
            "optionC": "  Nucleoli ",
            "optionD": "  Ribosomes ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tLysosomes are found in animal cell, they are also known as suicidal bags of the cell. A human cell contains around 300 lysosomes. They not only digest large molecules but also responsible for breaking down and getting rid of waste products of the cell. They have enzymes which allow them to carry out these processes. ",
            "keyString": "313835s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which feature do prokaryotic and eukaryotic cells share?",
            "optionA": "  Nucleus ",
            "optionB": "  DNA ",
            "optionC": "  Nuclear membrane ",
            "optionD": "  Membrane bound Organelles ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe common features of prokaryotic and eukaryotic cells are: DNA, the genetic material contained in one or more chromosomes and located in a non membrane bound nucleoid region in prokaryotes and a membrane-bound nucleus in eukaryotes. ",
            "keyString": "313850s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following contain enzymes for cellular respiration ?",
            "optionA": "  Dictyosomes ",
            "optionB": "  Endoplasmic reticula ",
            "optionC": "  Lysosomes ",
            "optionD": "  Mitochondria ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMitochondria contain enzymes for cellular respiration. Mitochondria are known as the powerhouse of the cell. ",
            "keyString": "313862s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The smallest unit that is capable of carrying out life functions is known as",
            "optionA": "  Tissue  ",
            "optionB": "  Cell  ",
            "optionC": "  Blood  ",
            "optionD": "  DNA  ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe cell is the smallest structural and functional unit of living organisms, which can exist on its own. Therefore, it is sometimes called the building block of life.",
            "keyString": "313874s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The main function of the Golgi body is",
            "optionA": "  Respiration ",
            "optionB": "  To begin cell division ",
            "optionC": "  To produce gastric juice ",
            "optionD": "  Secretion ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA Golgi body, also known as a Golgi apparatus, is a cell organelle that helps process and package proteins and lipid molecules, especially proteins destined to be exported from the cell. ",
            "keyString": "350397s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which organelle is the control center of a cell?",
            "optionA": "  Nucleus ",
            "optionB": "  Cytoplasm ",
            "optionC": "  Cell membrane ",
            "optionD": "  Endoplasmic reticulum ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe nucleus is the largest organelle in a eukaryotic cell and is considered to be the cell's control center. It contains most of the cell's DNA, which makes up chromosomes and is encoded with the genetic instructions for making proteins. ",
            "keyString": "350427s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following organelles of a cell is involved in photosynthesis?",
            "optionA": "  Chloroplast ",
            "optionB": "  Mitochondria ",
            "optionC": "  Golgi bodies ",
            "optionD": "  Endoplasmic reticulum ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn plants, photosynthesis takes place in chloroplasts, which contain the chlorophyll. Chloroplasts are surrounded by a double membrane and contain a third inner membrane, called the thylakoid membrane, that forms long folds within the organelle. ",
            "keyString": "350443s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The theory which states that all animals and plants are composed of cells and cell products is known as",
            "optionA": "  Cell Theory ",
            "optionB": "  Atomic Theory ",
            "optionC": "  Bohr's Theory ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBy the late 1830s, botanist Matthias Schleiden and zoologist Theodor Schwann were studying tissues and proposed the unified cell theory. The unified cell theory states that: all living things are composed of one or more cells; the cell is the basic unit of life; and new cells arise from existing cells. ",
            "keyString": "350458s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Biologists mainly deal with matters relating to",
            "optionA": "  Living part of nature ",
            "optionB": "  Non living things influencing living things ",
            "optionC": "  How life works ",
            "optionD": "  All three a b and c ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBiologists mainly deal with matters relating to living part of nature, non living things influencing living things and how life works. ",
            "keyString": "350470s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Vitamin present in guava fruit is",
            "optionA": "  Vitamin - A ",
            "optionB": "  Vitamin - B ",
            "optionC": "  Vitamin - C ",
            "optionD": "  Vitamin - D ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGuava has a rich source of vitamin C, A and E. Guava is called the super fruit because it is said to contain four times more vitamin C than orange and three times more proteins and four times more fibre than pineapple. It is also said to have more potassium than a banana. ",
            "keyString": "385814s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Vitamins are",
            "optionA": "  Macro Nutrients ",
            "optionB": "  Micro nutrients ",
            "optionC": "  Essential Amino acids ",
            "optionD": "  Non essential Amino acids ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tVitamins are micro nutrients. ",
            "keyString": "385843s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following vitamins acts like hormone?",
            "optionA": "  Vitamin A ",
            "optionB": "  Vitamin B ",
            "optionC": "  Vitamin C ",
            "optionD": "  Vitamin D ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tVitamin D is a hormone the kidneys produce that controls blood calcium concentration and impacts the immune system. It is also known as calcitriol, ergocalciferol, calcidiol and cholecalciferol. Of those, calcidiol is the form doctors most commonly focus on when measuring vitamin D levels in the blood. ",
            "keyString": "385857s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following vitamins are water soluble?",
            "optionA": "  Vitamin A & Vitamin B ",
            "optionB": "   Vitamin B & Vitamin C ",
            "optionC": "  Vitamin C & Vitamin D ",
            "optionD": "  Vitamin A & Vitamin K ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe water-soluble vitamins include ascorbic acid (vitamin C), thiamin, riboflavin, niacin, vitamin B6 (pyridoxine, pyridoxal, and pyridoxamine), folacin, vitamin B12, biotin, and pantothenic acid. ",
            "keyString": "385869s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Lathyrism is caused by excess consumption of ________ ",
            "optionA": "  Khesari Dal ",
            "optionB": "  Mustard oil ",
            "optionC": "  Mushrooms ",
            "optionD": "  Polished rice ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tLathyrism is a disease caused by eating seeds of species of Lathyrus (the grass pea), mainly L. sativus (the chickpea or khesari). ",
            "keyString": "385880s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The term biology was first coined by",
            "optionA": "  Aristotle ",
            "optionB": "  Darwin ",
            "optionC": "  Lamark ",
            "optionD": "  Lamark and Treviranus ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tLamark and Treviranus coined the term biology for the first time. ",
            "keyString": "421216s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The largest invertebrate is",
            "optionA": "  Octopus ",
            "optionB": "  Squid ",
            "optionC": "  Coral ",
            "optionD": "  Jelly fish ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe giant squid remains largely a mystery to scientists despite being the biggest invertebrate on Earth. The largest of these elusive giants ever found measured 59 feet in length and weighed nearly a ton. ",
            "keyString": "421244s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The tallest moss in the world is",
            "optionA": "  Funaira ",
            "optionB": "  Dawsonia ",
            "optionC": "  Marchantia ",
            "optionD": "  Sporophyte ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe tallest moss in the world is Dawsonia. ",
            "keyString": "421256s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The unique feature of bryophytes compared to other green plants groups is that",
            "optionA": "  They lack roots ",
            "optionB": "  They lack vascular tissue ",
            "optionC": "  They produce spores ",
            "optionD": "  Their sporophytes is attached to gametophyte ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe unique feature of bryophytes compared to other green plant group is that it contains no xylem for conducting water through the plant, instead it conducts water and nutrients through the leaves. Therefore, these are termed as non vascular terrestrial plants. ",
            "keyString": "421268s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Animals/organisms floating on the surface of water are",
            "optionA": "  Plankton ",
            "optionB": "  Pelagic ",
            "optionC": "  Benthon ",
            "optionD": "  Neritic ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAnimals or organism floating on the surface of water is plankton. ",
            "keyString": "421278s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following plants produce only seeds but no fruit?",
            "optionA": "  Sugarcane ",
            "optionB": "  Peanut ",
            "optionC": "  Cycas ",
            "optionD": "  Almond ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCycas and Pinus are Gymnosperms, those have seeds but not fruits or flowers. ",
            "keyString": "456727s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Consider the following plant1. Guava2. Mint3. Sweet potatoThe roots of which of these plants bear adventitious buds that developed into new individuals under favourable conditions.",
            "optionA": "  1 and 2 ",
            "optionB": "  2 only ",
            "optionC": "  3 only ",
            "optionD": "  1, 2 and 3 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe roots of sweet potato bear adventitious buds that developed into new individuals under favourable conditions. ",
            "keyString": "456759s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Potato is a",
            "optionA": "  Root  ",
            "optionB": "  Stem  ",
            "optionC": "  Bud  ",
            "optionD": "  Fruit  ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPotatoes are stem tubers. Enlarged stolons thicken to develop into storage organs. The tuber has all the parts of a normal stem, including nodes and internodes. ",
            "keyString": "456777s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The \"eyes\" of potato tubers are",
            "optionA": "  Shoot buds  ",
            "optionB": "  Flower buds  ",
            "optionC": "  Root buds  ",
            "optionD": "  Axillary buds  ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe axillary buds of the potato tuber are called \u201ceyes\u201d in common language. They are found at the nodes of the stem tuber. ",
            "keyString": "456789s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is responsible for transport of food and other substances in plants?",
            "optionA": "  Xylem ",
            "optionB": "  Phloem ",
            "optionC": "  Chloroplast ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe food which is prepared by the process of photosynthesis in the leaves of a plant has to be transported to other parts like stem, roots, branches etc. Therefore this food is transported to other parts of the plant through a kind of tubes called phloem. ",
            "keyString": "456801s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Plant bends towards the source of light on account of the movement of curvature known as",
            "optionA": "  geotropism ",
            "optionB": "  thigmotropism ",
            "optionC": "  chemotropism ",
            "optionD": "  phototropism ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPhototropism is one of the many plant tropisms or movements which respond to external stimuli. Growth towards a light source is called positive phototropism, while growth away from light is called negative phototropism (skototropism). ",
            "keyString": "492601s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Plant have ____ while animals lack it.",
            "optionA": "  starch ",
            "optionB": "  cellulose ",
            "optionC": "  protein ",
            "optionD": "  fat ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPlant have cellulose while animals lack it. ",
            "keyString": "492633s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Osmosis is the flow of solution from higher concentration to a solution of lower concentration through a semi permeable membrane. What is incorrect in this statement?",
            "optionA": "  Exact concentration of solution is not given ",
            "optionB": "  Character of semi permeable membrane is not given ",
            "optionC": "  The flow of solution is not possible through semi permeable membrane ",
            "optionD": "  All are incorrect ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOsmosis is defined as the flow of solvent molecules from a region of their higher concentration to a region of their lower concentration across a semipermeable membrane. Osmosis does not explains movement of solute particles or solution. ",
            "keyString": "492647s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Photosynthesis is a process",
            "optionA": "  reductive and exergonic ",
            "optionB": "  reductive and catabolic ",
            "optionC": "  reductive, endergonic and catabolic ",
            "optionD": "  reductive, endergonic and anabolic ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPhotosynthesis is a process which is reductive, endergonic and anabolic. ",
            "keyString": "492659s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "On which of the following plants did Gregor Mendal perform his classical experiment?",
            "optionA": "  Gram ",
            "optionB": "  Maize ",
            "optionC": "  Pea ",
            "optionD": "  Wheat ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGregor Mendal performed his classical experiment on pea. ",
            "keyString": "492670s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The female sex organs in a flower is the ________ .",
            "optionA": "  Zoospores ",
            "optionB": "  Stamen ",
            "optionC": "  Pistil ",
            "optionD": "  Chlorophyceae ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAs a plant's reproductive part, a flower contains a stamen (male flower part) or pistil (female flower part), or both, plus accessory parts such as sepals, petals, and nectar glands. The stamen is the male reproductive organ. ",
            "keyString": "528158s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The male sex organs in a flower is the ________ .",
            "optionA": "  Zoospores ",
            "optionB": "  Stamen ",
            "optionC": "  Pistil ",
            "optionD": "  Chlorophyceae ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAs a plant's reproductive part, a flower contains a stamen (male flower part) or pistil (female flower part), or both, plus accessory parts such as sepals, petals, and nectar glands. The stamen is the male reproductive organ. It consists of a pollen sac (anther) and a long supporting filament. ",
            "keyString": "528188s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which part of flower produces pollen grains that are generally yellowish in colour?",
            "optionA": "  Sepals ",
            "optionB": "  Petals ",
            "optionC": "  Stamens ",
            "optionD": "  Carpels ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tStamens are the part of the flower that produces pollen. Pollen is fine yellowish dust made by stamens inside a flower that contains the male sperm cells. ",
            "keyString": "528203s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following is the longest flower in the world?",
            "optionA": "  Lotus ",
            "optionB": "  Sunflower ",
            "optionC": "  Rafflesia ",
            "optionD": "  Glory Lily ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe flower with the world's largest bloom is the Rafflesia arnoldii. This rare flower is found in the rainforests of Indonesia. It can grow to be 3 feet across and weigh up to 15 pounds. It is a parasitic plant, with no visible leaves, roots, or stem. ",
            "keyString": "528215s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Usually the conspicuous, coloured, attractive part of flower is termed as",
            "optionA": "  Sepals ",
            "optionB": "  Carpels ",
            "optionC": "  Petals ",
            "optionD": "  Stamens ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe parts of a flower that are often conspicuously coloured are called petals. ",
            "keyString": "528227s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who discovered the insecticidal properties of DDT?",
            "optionA": "  Othmanzedicer  ",
            "optionB": "  R.H. Painter  ",
            "optionC": "  Paul Muller  ",
            "optionD": "  Rachel Carson  ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn 1939 the Swiss chemist Paul M\u00fcller discovered the insecticidal properties of DDT.",
            "keyString": "563576s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "There is no bacteria activity in which of the following process?",
            "optionA": "  Sewage disposal ",
            "optionB": "  Tanning of leather ",
            "optionC": "  Ripening of cheese ",
            "optionD": "  Preparation of sillage ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThere is no bacteria activity in the ripening of cheese. ",
            "keyString": "563607s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "________ reproduces by binary fission.",
            "optionA": "  Amoeba ",
            "optionB": "  Liverfiuke ",
            "optionC": "  Plasmodium ",
            "optionD": "  Planaria ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAmoeba reproduces by binary fission. ",
            "keyString": "563621s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The DNA of the bacterium is found present in a distinct nuclear region called",
            "optionA": "  Nucleolus ",
            "optionB": "  Centrosome ",
            "optionC": "  Nucleoid ",
            "optionD": "  Nucleus ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe nucleoid (meaning nucleus-like) is an irregularly-shaped region within the cell of a prokaryote that contains all or most of the genetic material. In contrast to the nucleus of a eukaryotic cell, it is not surrounded by a nuclear membrane. ",
            "keyString": "563632s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In autotrophic bacteria, where is chlorophyll located?",
            "optionA": "  In the nucleoid ",
            "optionB": "  In the infolded plasma membrane ",
            "optionC": "  In the ribosomes ",
            "optionD": "  In chloroplast membranes ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn autotrophic bacteria, chlorophyll is located in the infolded plasma membrane. ",
            "keyString": "563643s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Plants are killed in winter by frost",
            "optionA": "  because of desiccation and mechanical damage to the tissues ",
            "optionB": "  because no photosynthesis takes place at such low temperature ",
            "optionC": "  because respiration ceases at such low temperature ",
            "optionD": "  because there is no transpiration ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPlants are killed in winter by frost as there is desiccation and mechanical damage to the tissues. Desiccation is the state of extreme dryness, or the process of extreme drying. ",
            "keyString": "598701s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "One of the following is most suitable for study of mutations",
            "optionA": "  Haploids ",
            "optionB": "  Diploids ",
            "optionC": "  Tetraploids ",
            "optionD": "  Polyploid ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tHaploids are more suitable for mutation studies than the diploids. ",
            "keyString": "598729s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Pulses are a good source of",
            "optionA": "  carbohydrates ",
            "optionB": "  fats ",
            "optionC": "  proteins ",
            "optionD": "  vitamins ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPulses are a great source of protein. They can be particularly important for people who do not get protein by eating meat, fish or dairy products. Pulses include beans, lentils and peas.",
            "keyString": "598742s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Oxygen in our blood is transported by a protein named",
            "optionA": "  haemoglobin ",
            "optionB": "  keratin ",
            "optionC": "  collagen ",
            "optionD": "  myoglobin ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOxygen in our blood is transported by a protein named Haemoglobin. ",
            "keyString": "598754s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Nymph is the name of young one of",
            "optionA": "  butterfly ",
            "optionB": "  beetle ",
            "optionC": "  housefly ",
            "optionD": "  cockroach ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNymph is the name of young one of cockroach. ",
            "keyString": "598765s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The genotype of a plant showing a dominant phenotype can be determined by",
            "optionA": "  Backcross  ",
            "optionB": "  Dihybrid cross  ",
            "optionC": "  Testcross  ",
            "optionD": "  Pedigree analysis  ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe zygosity of F1 generation can be checked by test cross method. In a test cross : The organism with the dominant trait is always crossed with an organism with the recessive trait. If any offspring show the recessive trait, the unknown genotype is heterozygous. If all the offspring have the dominant trait, the unknown genotype is homozygous dominant. Large numbers of offspring are needed for reliable results. ",
            "keyString": "633533s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is not true about colour blindness?",
            "optionA": "  Colour blind people learn to rely on shapes, patterns, and positions of signs and signals ",
            "optionB": "  Red-green colour blindness is the most common type of colour blindness ",
            "optionC": "  A colour blind person cannot see any colours ",
            "optionD": "  For some people, it might be difficult to recognize colours of traffic lights and signs ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA colour blind person cannot see any colors is not true of colour blindness. ",
            "keyString": "633566s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Stem Cell Therapy (SCT) is not useful for the treatment of which one of the following ailments?",
            "optionA": "  Kidney failure ",
            "optionB": "  Cancer ",
            "optionC": "  Brain injury ",
            "optionD": "  Vision impairment ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tStem Cell Therapy (SCT) is not useful for the treatment of Vision impairment. ",
            "keyString": "633581s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which part of human eye controls the amount of light entering the eye?",
            "optionA": "  Pupil  ",
            "optionB": "  Iris  ",
            "optionC": "  Cornea  ",
            "optionD": "  Retina  ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t When there is bright light, the iris closes the pupil to let in less light. And when there is low light, the iris opens up the pupil to let in more light. Focuses light rays onto the retina. ",
            "keyString": "633593s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What is the distance of distinct vision (DDV) of a normal human eye?",
            "optionA": "  15 cm  ",
            "optionB": "  25 cm  ",
            "optionC": "  30 cm  ",
            "optionD": "  40 cm  ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe minimum distance from the eye at which an object appears to be distinct i.e., a very clear image of the object is formed is called the distance of distinct vision. This distance is about 25 cm from the eye. ",
            "keyString": "633603s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following completes the given statement correctly ?Cretinism is a human disorder which is due to the under secretion of",
            "optionA": "  Adrenalin hormone ",
            "optionB": "  Cortisone hormone ",
            "optionC": "  Glucagon hormone ",
            "optionD": "  Thyroxin hormone ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCretinism is a human disorder which is due to the under secretion of Thyroxin hormone. ",
            "keyString": "669312s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The thyroid hormone that regulates carbohydrate metabolism is",
            "optionA": "  Parathyroid ",
            "optionB": "  Thyroxin ",
            "optionC": "  Parathormone ",
            "optionD": "  Estrogen ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe thyroid hormone that regulates carbohydrate metabolism is thyroxin. ",
            "keyString": "669342s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following hormones contains Iodine?",
            "optionA": "  Thyroxine ",
            "optionB": "  Testosterone ",
            "optionC": "  Insulin ",
            "optionD": "  Adrenaline ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThyroxine hormone contains iodine. The thyroid gland produces two primary hormones - thyroxine and tri-iodothyronine. ",
            "keyString": "669355s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is not an Endocrine Gland?",
            "optionA": "  Spleen ",
            "optionB": "  Pituitary ",
            "optionC": "  Thyroid ",
            "optionD": "  Adrenal ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSpleen is not an Endocrine Gland. ",
            "keyString": "669366s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Pineal gland is situated in",
            "optionA": "  Liver ",
            "optionB": "  Brain ",
            "optionC": "  Kidney ",
            "optionD": "  Uterus ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe pineal gland is located deep in the brain in an area called the epithalamus, where the two halves of the brain join. ",
            "keyString": "669376s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following hormone is called the emergency hormone ?",
            "optionA": "  Insulin ",
            "optionB": "  Adrenaline ",
            "optionC": "  Estrogen ",
            "optionD": "  Oxytocin ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAdrenaline, also known as epinephrine, is a hormone and medication. Adrenaline is normally produced by both the adrenal glands and a small number of neurons in the medulla oblongata, where it acts as a neurotransmitter involved in regulating visceral functions. ",
            "keyString": "704614s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which cells secrete hormones?",
            "optionA": "  Tissue cells ",
            "optionB": "  Museles cells ",
            "optionC": "  Respiratory ",
            "optionD": "  Glands ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGlands secrete hormones. ",
            "keyString": "704643s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Insulin is secreted from which gland or organ of human body?",
            "optionA": "  Kidney  ",
            "optionB": "  Liver  ",
            "optionC": "  Small Intestine  ",
            "optionD": "  Pancreas  ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe most important hormone that the pancreas produces is insulin. Insulin is released by the 'beta cells' in the islets of Langerhans in response to food. ",
            "keyString": "704656s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following crops would be preferred for sowing in order to enrich soil with nitrogen?",
            "optionA": "  Wheat ",
            "optionB": "  Mustard ",
            "optionC": "  Sunflower ",
            "optionD": "  Gram ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe \"gram crops\" would be preferred for sowing in order to enrich the \"soil with nitrogen\". ",
            "keyString": "704667s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Censor mechanism of dispersal of seeds is found in",
            "optionA": "  Pea ",
            "optionB": "  Poppy ",
            "optionC": "  Cotton ",
            "optionD": "  Maize ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCensor mechanism of seed dispersal is a type of dispersal by wind, which generally occur in poppy. Its seeds bear hairy fibers outside and are very light in weight, which aid in easy dispersal by wind. ",
            "keyString": "704677s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What does the central nervous system consists of?",
            "optionA": "  Brain ",
            "optionB": "  Spinal cord ",
            "optionC": "  Nerves ",
            "optionD": "  All the above ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe central nervous system is made up of the brain and spinal cord. The peripheral nervous system is made up of nerves that branch off from the spinal cord and extend to all parts of the body. ",
            "keyString": "759795s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "How many pair of nerves arises from vertebral column?",
            "optionA": "  12 pair ",
            "optionB": "  13 pair ",
            "optionC": "  31 pair ",
            "optionD": "  33 pair ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t31 pair of nerves arises from vertebral column. ",
            "keyString": "759827s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one is the biggest part of the brain?",
            "optionA": "  Thalamus  ",
            "optionB": "  Medulla  ",
            "optionC": "  Cerebellum  ",
            "optionD": "  Cerebrum  ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe largest part of the brain, the cerebrum has two hemispheres (or halves). The cerebrum controls voluntary movement, speech, intelligence, memory, emotion, and sensory processing. ",
            "keyString": "759842s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The brain is a part of which organ system?",
            "optionA": "  Respiratory System  ",
            "optionB": "  Circulatory System  ",
            "optionC": "  Nervous System  ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above  ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe nervous system is made up of the central nervous system and the peripheral nervous system: The brain and the spinal cord are the central nervous system. The nerves that go through the whole body make up the peripheral nervous system. ",
            "keyString": "759854s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Asexual reproduction differs from sexual reproduction in that in asexual reproduction, ________ ",
            "optionA": "  The new organisms are genetically identical to the parent ",
            "optionB": "  The gametes are produced in reproduction ",
            "optionC": "  The nuclei of gametes fuse ",
            "optionD": "  The offspring shows variations ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSexual reproduction just means combining genetic material from two parents. Asexual reproduction produces offspring genetically identical to the one parent. ",
            "keyString": "759865s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "A seed is ripened ________",
            "optionA": "  Ovary ",
            "optionB": "  Flower ",
            "optionC": "  Gynoecium ",
            "optionD": "  Ovule ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA seed is a small embryonic plant enclosed in a covering called the seed coat, usually with some stored food. It is the product of the ripened ovule of gymnosperm and angiosperm plants which occurs after fertilization and some growth with in the mother plant. ",
            "keyString": "794714s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which among the following is not a true fruit?",
            "optionA": "  Apple ",
            "optionB": "  Date ",
            "optionC": "  Grape ",
            "optionD": "  Plum ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTechnically, apple is not a true fruit. A fruit is a ripened ovary. Inside the apple fruit , the structure holding the seeds is actually the fruit while the edible fleshy part is actually the swollen wall material of ovary. ",
            "keyString": "794744s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of these is unique to flowering plants?",
            "optionA": "  Double fertilization ",
            "optionB": "  An embryo surrounded by nutritive tissue ",
            "optionC": "  Haploid gametophytes ",
            "optionD": "  Pollen production ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn flowering plants one sperm nucleus fertilizes the egg and the other sperm nucleus fuses with two other nuclei found within the ovule, thus forming triploid endosperm. Hence, double fertilization is unique to flowering plants. ",
            "keyString": "794758s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The pollination by snails is called",
            "optionA": "  Zoophily ",
            "optionB": "  Entomophily ",
            "optionC": "  Chiropteriphily ",
            "optionD": "  Malacophily ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPollination is a crucial ecological process that aids sexual reproduction in flowering plants. Although a variety of animals are known to bring about pollen transfer, pollination by snails (malacophily) has remained a rare and obscure phenomenon.",
            "keyString": "794770s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following completes the given statement correctly?A seed is a ripened _______",
            "optionA": "  Ovary ",
            "optionB": "  Flower ",
            "optionC": "  Gynoecium ",
            "optionD": "  Ovule ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA seed is a ripened ovule. ",
            "keyString": "794782s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which group of organisms serves as the best indicator of pollution in a water body?",
            "optionA": "  Plankton  ",
            "optionB": "  Benthos  ",
            "optionC": "  Nekton  ",
            "optionD": "  Neuston  ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPlankton serves as the best indicator of pollution in a water body. ",
            "keyString": "885522s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In female a small portion oviduct is removed and cut end is ligated by surgical operation is called",
            "optionA": "  Vasectomy ",
            "optionB": "  Tubectomy ",
            "optionC": "  Neurotomy ",
            "optionD": "  Psycotomy ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSurgical methods, also called as sterilisation, are generally advised for the male/female partner as a terminal method to prevent any more pregnancies.Surgical intervention blocks gamete transport and thereby prevent conception. Sterilisation procedure in the male is called as vasectomy and that in the female, tubectomy.",
            "keyString": "885551s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following would cause gene flow?",
            "optionA": "  Individuals moving into population ",
            "optionB": "  Genetic drift ",
            "optionC": "  Mutation ",
            "optionD": "  Artificial selection ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGene flow means migration of genes from one to another. This gene flow is caused by individuals moving into population. ",
            "keyString": "885564s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Oral pills of birth control prevent",
            "optionA": "  Ovulation ",
            "optionB": "  Fertilization ",
            "optionC": "  Pregnency ",
            "optionD": "  Entery of sperm in uterus ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOral contraceptives (birth-control pills) are used to prevent pregnancy. Estrogen and progestin are two female sex hormones. Combinations of estrogen and progestin work by preventing ovulation (the release of eggs from the ovaries). ",
            "keyString": "885575s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Study of population is",
            "optionA": "  Palentology ",
            "optionB": "  Geofraphy ",
            "optionC": "  Demography ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe field of science interested in collecting and analyzing numbers related to population is known as demography.",
            "keyString": "885586s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The audible sounds of heart are made by the closing of the",
            "optionA": "  Arteries  ",
            "optionB": "  Veins  ",
            "optionC": "  Valve  ",
            "optionD": "  Ventricle  ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tClosure of the heart valves is associated with an audible sound, called the heartbeat.",
            "keyString": "920761s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one is the largest artery in the human body",
            "optionA": "  Radial Artery  ",
            "optionB": "  Ulnar Artery  ",
            "optionC": "  Aorta  ",
            "optionD": "  Arterioles  ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMost arteries carry oxygenated blood. The largest artery is the aorta, which is connected to the heart and extends into the abdomen. ",
            "keyString": "920790s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which veins do not carry deoxygenated blood?",
            "optionA": "  Portal Veins  ",
            "optionB": "  Hepatic Veins  ",
            "optionC": "  Subclavian Veins  ",
            "optionD": "  Pulmonary Veins  ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tVeins are blood vessels that carry blood towards the heart. Most veins carry deoxygenated blood from the tissues back to the heart; exceptions are the pulmonary and umbilical veins, both of which carry oxygenated blood to the heart. ",
            "keyString": "920803s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Muscular wall of the heart is externally covered by",
            "optionA": "  Epithelium  ",
            "optionB": "  Endothelium  ",
            "optionC": "  Epicardium  ",
            "optionD": "  Myocardium  ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe wall of the heart consists of three layers: the epicardium (external layer), the myocardium (middle layer) and the endocardium (inner layer). ",
            "keyString": "920814s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The deposition of cholesterol on the walls of blood vessels causes the arteries to lose their elasticity and get stiffened is called",
            "optionA": "  Hypotension  ",
            "optionB": "  Hypertension  ",
            "optionC": "  Systolic Pressure  ",
            "optionD": "  Arteriosclerosis  ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAtherosclerosis, sometimes called \"hardening of the arteries,\" occurs when fat, cholesterol, and other substances build up in the walls of arteries.",
            "keyString": "920825s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In test tube baby",
            "optionA": "  Fertilization of ova and development takes place in test tube ",
            "optionB": "  Fertilization of ova takes place in test tube which development of embryo occur in uterus ",
            "optionC": "  Fertilization takes place in uterus while development takes place in test tube ",
            "optionD": "  Development of ova take place in test tube without fertilization ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn test tube baby fertilization of ova takes place in test tube and development of embryo occur in uterus.",
            "keyString": "956011s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In uterus embryo get their nutrition through a structure called",
            "optionA": "  Fallopian tube ",
            "optionB": "  Placenta ",
            "optionC": "  Uterus ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe placenta is the structure which attaches the developing embryo with the mother. This is the structure which is attached to the umbilical cord of the embryo. The placenta helps to provide nutrition to the embryo. This structure also carries oxygen to the embryo and the wastes away from the embryo. ",
            "keyString": "956046s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Study of female reproductive system is",
            "optionA": "  Gerontology ",
            "optionB": "  Gastroenterology ",
            "optionC": "  Gyneocology ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tStudy of female reproductive system is gyneocology. ",
            "keyString": "956062s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which among the following is/are female hormones?(i) Estrogen(ii) Progesterone(iii) Testosterone",
            "optionA": "  (i) and (iii) ",
            "optionB": "  (i) and (ii) ",
            "optionC": "  (ii) and (iii) ",
            "optionD": "  Only (iii) ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tEstrogen and Progesterone are female hormones. ",
            "keyString": "956076s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Fertilization in human takes place inside",
            "optionA": "  Uterus ",
            "optionB": "  Oviduct ",
            "optionC": "  Ovigland ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFertilization in human takes place inside oviduct. ",
            "keyString": "956093s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Biological membranes are composed of",
            "optionA": "  Phospholipids ",
            "optionB": "  Proteins ",
            "optionC": "  Carbohydrate groups ",
            "optionD": "  All of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBiological membranes are composed of Phospholipids,proteins and carbohydrate groups. ",
            "keyString": "992977s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Biological membranes are composed of",
            "optionA": "  40% proteins and 60% lipids ",
            "optionB": "  50% proteins and 50% lipids ",
            "optionC": "  70% proteins and 30% lipids ",
            "optionD": "  60% proteins and 40% lipids ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBiological membranes are composed of 60% proteins and 40% lipids. ",
            "keyString": "993006s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "They are double membrane structures that are commonly oval or disc shaped.",
            "optionA": "  Ribosomes ",
            "optionB": "  Lysosomes ",
            "optionC": "  Nucleus ",
            "optionD": "  Golgi bodies ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRibosomes are double membrane structures that are commonly oval or disc shaped. ",
            "keyString": "993020s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The cell wall of plants is generally made up of cellulose and is differently structured than that of a",
            "optionA": "  Moss ",
            "optionB": "  Bacterium ",
            "optionC": "  Fern ",
            "optionD": "  Algae ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe cell wall of plants is generally made up of cellulose and is differently structured than that of a bacterium. ",
            "keyString": "993032s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which cell feature is responsible for making proteins?",
            "optionA": "  Chromosomes ",
            "optionB": "  Nucleus ",
            "optionC": "  Ribosomes ",
            "optionD": "  Cytoplasm ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRibosomes is responsible for making proteins. ",
            "keyString": "993043s37m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Most of the digestion occur in which part of alimentary canal of man",
            "optionA": "  Pancreas ",
            "optionB": "  Small intestine ",
            "optionC": "  Large intestine ",
            "optionD": "  Stomach ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMost of the digestion of food takes place in the small intestine which is the longest part of the GI tract. A major digestive organ is the stomach. Within its mucosa are millions of embedded gastric glands. ",
            "keyString": "27458s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is not an enzyme?",
            "optionA": "  Oxytocin ",
            "optionB": "  Trypsin ",
            "optionC": "  Pepsin ",
            "optionD": "  Ptyalin ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOxytocin is not an enzyme. ",
            "keyString": "27484s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Man has ________ pairs of salivary glands.",
            "optionA": "  3 ",
            "optionB": "  4 ",
            "optionC": "  6 ",
            "optionD": "  8 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThere are three pairs of major salivary glands: the parotid glands, the submandibular glands, and the sublingual glands. ",
            "keyString": "27497s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "All enzymes are",
            "optionA": "  Alkaloids ",
            "optionB": "  Proteins ",
            "optionC": "  Carbohydrates ",
            "optionD": "  Lipids ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tEnzymes are proteins that act as biological catalysts (biocatalysts). Catalysts accelerate chemical reactions.",
            "keyString": "27509s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following is the correct sequence in the order of decreasing length of the structural parts given below of small intestine in the human body?",
            "optionA": "  Jejunum-Duodenum-Jejunum ",
            "optionB": "  Ileum-Duodenum-Jejunum ",
            "optionC": "  Jejunum-Ileum-Duodenum ",
            "optionD": "  Ileum-Jejunum-Duodenum ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIleum-Jejunum-Duodenum is the correct sequence. ",
            "keyString": "27519s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Photosynthesis takes place in the presence of chlorophyll and ________",
            "optionA": "  Water ",
            "optionB": "  Nutrients ",
            "optionC": "  Carbon-dioxide ",
            "optionD": "  Sunlight ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPhotosynthesis takes place in the presence of chlorophyll and sunlight. ",
            "keyString": "63557s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "One of the following cannot be performed by animals.",
            "optionA": "  Respiration ",
            "optionB": "  Photosynthesis ",
            "optionC": "  Reproduction ",
            "optionD": "  Digestion ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPhotosynthesis cannot be performed by animals. ",
            "keyString": "63587s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Green pigment is called",
            "optionA": "  Chlorophyll ",
            "optionB": "  Xanthophyll ",
            "optionC": "  Carotene ",
            "optionD": "  Phycobillin ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGreen pigment is called Chlorophyll. ",
            "keyString": "63601s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Plants utilise ________ from the atmosphere for photosynthesis.",
            "optionA": "  Oxygen ",
            "optionB": "  Nitrogen ",
            "optionC": "  Carbon dioxide ",
            "optionD": "  Hydrogen ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDuring photosynthesis, plants take in carbon dioxide (CO2) and water (H2O) from the air and soil. Within the plant cell, the water is oxidized, meaning it loses electrons, while the carbon dioxide is reduced, meaning it gains electrons. This transforms the water into oxygen and the carbon dioxide into glucose. ",
            "keyString": "63613s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In Photosynthesis",
            "optionA": "  Light energy is converted into chemical energy ",
            "optionB": "  Chemical energy is converted into light energy ",
            "optionC": "  Chemical energy is converted into electrical energy ",
            "optionD": "  Light energy is converted into mechanical eneargy ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn Photosynthesis light energy is converted into chemical energy. ",
            "keyString": "63624s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "All insects have how many parts of legs?",
            "optionA": "  2 ",
            "optionB": "  3 ",
            "optionC": "  4 ",
            "optionD": "  6 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAll insects have 3 parts of a leg. ",
            "keyString": "120641s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "All living things except bacteria and blue green algae are termed as",
            "optionA": "  Prokayotes ",
            "optionB": "  Lysosmes ",
            "optionC": "  Eukaryotes ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAll living things except bacteria and blue green algae are termed as eukaryotes. ",
            "keyString": "120670s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "There are how many species of fungi?",
            "optionA": "  80 species ",
            "optionB": "  800 species ",
            "optionC": "  8,000 species ",
            "optionD": "  80,000 species ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThere are 80,000 species of fungi. ",
            "keyString": "120684s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is true of annelids?",
            "optionA": "  They have an open circulatory system ",
            "optionB": "  They have a nerve net ",
            "optionC": "  They perform gas exchange across their skin ",
            "optionD": "  They have pseudocoeloms ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAnnelids perform gas exchange across their skin. ",
            "keyString": "120697s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following has the largest number of chromosomes?",
            "optionA": "  Human beings ",
            "optionB": "  Pteridophytes ",
            "optionC": "  Elephants ",
            "optionD": "  Bryophytes ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPteridophytes has the largest number of chromosomes. ",
            "keyString": "120709s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "During which phase centromeres divide and chromatids separate into chromosomes?",
            "optionA": "  Prophase ",
            "optionB": "  Metaphase ",
            "optionC": "  Telophase ",
            "optionD": "  Anaphase ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDuring anaphase, the \u201cupward phase,\u201d the cohesin proteins degrade, and the sister chromatids separate at the centromere. Each chromatid, now called a chromosome, is pulled rapidly toward the centrosome to which its microtubule is attached. ",
            "keyString": "158233s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The shape of chromosome is clearly visible at",
            "optionA": "  Prophase ",
            "optionB": "  Anaphase ",
            "optionC": "  Metaphase ",
            "optionD": "  Telophase ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe shape of chromosome is clearly visible at metaphase. ",
            "keyString": "158265s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "How many daughter cells are formed after the completion mitosis?",
            "optionA": "  2 ",
            "optionB": "  4 ",
            "optionC": "  6 ",
            "optionD": "  8 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAt the end of mitosis, two daughter cells will be formed which are exact copies of the original cell. Each daughter cell will have 30 chromosomes.",
            "keyString": "158279s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Pollen is produced by the process of",
            "optionA": "  Mitosis ",
            "optionB": "  Pollination ",
            "optionC": "  Meiosis ",
            "optionD": "  Fertilization ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPollen development is a postmeiotic process that produces immature pollen grains from microspores. The maturation process can be dissected into various stages. During microspore mitosis, the pollen first develops a large vacuole that mediates nuclear migration to produce polarized cells. ",
            "keyString": "158290s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "How many daughter cells reproduces after the completion of Meiosis II?",
            "optionA": "  2 daughter cells ",
            "optionB": "  4 daughter cells ",
            "optionC": "  6 daughter cells ",
            "optionD": "  8 daughter cells ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCompletion of meiosis II results in the production of four haploid daughter cells, each of which contains only one copy of each chromosome. ",
            "keyString": "158301s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What does stomach acid mostly consist of?",
            "optionA": "  Acetic Acid  ",
            "optionB": "  Ascorbic Acid  ",
            "optionC": "  Hydrochloric Acid  ",
            "optionD": "  Sulphuric Acid  ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tYour stomach has a nifty way of digesting proteins and it's called stomach acid, though you might know it as gastric juice or simply acid. It mainly consists of hydrochloric acid, a potent chemical produced by the cells lining the stomach (parietal cells) and your gastric glands. ",
            "keyString": "194476s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following is a digestive hormone?",
            "optionA": "  Gastrin  ",
            "optionB": "  Pepsin  ",
            "optionC": "  Amylase  ",
            "optionD": "  Lipase  ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGastrin is a digestive hormone. ",
            "keyString": "194525s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The teeth lacking in herbivorous animals is",
            "optionA": "  Molar  ",
            "optionB": "  Canine  ",
            "optionC": "  Incissor  ",
            "optionD": "  Premolar  ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPremolar teeth are lacking in herbivorous animal. ",
            "keyString": "194540s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Alimentary canal runs from mouth to",
            "optionA": "  Stomach  ",
            "optionB": "  Small Intestine  ",
            "optionC": "  Large Intestine  ",
            "optionD": "  Anus  ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe digestive system is made up of the alimentary canal (also called the digestive tract) and other organs, such as the liver and pancreas. Alimentary canal runs from mouth to anus. ",
            "keyString": "194552s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one is the longest part of the alimentary canal?",
            "optionA": "  Oseophagus  ",
            "optionB": "  Large Intestine  ",
            "optionC": "  Small Intestine  ",
            "optionD": "  Stomach  ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe longest part of the alimentary canal, the small intestine is about 3.05 meters (10 feet) long in a living person (but about twice as long in a cadaver due to the loss of muscle tone). ",
            "keyString": "194578s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Pepsin is a",
            "optionA": "  Hormone ",
            "optionB": "  Enzyme ",
            "optionC": "  Vitamin ",
            "optionD": "  Mineral ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPepsin is a stomach enzyme that serves to digest proteins found in ingested food. Gastric chief cells secrete pepsin as an inactive zymogen called pepsinogen. Parietal cells within the stomach lining secrete hydrochloric acid that lowers the pH of the stomach. ",
            "keyString": "235997s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The hormone which stimulates the stomach for the production of digestive juice is",
            "optionA": "  Gastrin ",
            "optionB": "  Trysin ",
            "optionC": "  Secretin ",
            "optionD": "  Pepsin ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGastrin is a hormone produced by the stomach, which stimulates the release of gastric acid. ",
            "keyString": "236149s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Most absorption of nutrients occurs in the",
            "optionA": "  Stomach ",
            "optionB": "  Liver ",
            "optionC": "  Large intestine ",
            "optionD": "  Small intestine ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMost absorption of nutrients occurs in the small intestine. ",
            "keyString": "236198s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is the largest digestive gland in humans?",
            "optionA": "  Spleen ",
            "optionB": "  Liver ",
            "optionC": "  Pancreas ",
            "optionD": "  Hepato-Pancreas ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tHepato-Pancreas is the largest digestive gland. ",
            "keyString": "236234s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one among the following is the hardest part of our body ?",
            "optionA": "  Skull bones of head ",
            "optionB": "  Thumb nails ",
            "optionC": "  Enamel of teeth ",
            "optionD": "  Spinal vertebra ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tEnamel of teeth is the hardest part of our body. ",
            "keyString": "236262s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Tracheids are conducting cells of which tissue?",
            "optionA": "  Xylem ",
            "optionB": "  Phloem ",
            "optionC": "  Cambium ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTracheids (top) and vessel elements (bottom) are the water conducting cells of xylem tissue.",
            "keyString": "274915s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The main function of the inner bark of a woody plant is to",
            "optionA": "  Transport minerals and water from the roots to the leaves ",
            "optionB": "  Act as a membrane impermeable to water and gas ",
            "optionC": "  Transport food from the leaves to the other parts of the plant ",
            "optionD": "  Protect the plant from herbivorous animals ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe inner bark is composed of living tissues, which help translocate the sugars created in the leaves to other parts of the plant. This happens in the secondary phloem. ",
            "keyString": "274943s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following tissues is responsible for increase of girth in the stem of a plant?",
            "optionA": "  Tracheid ",
            "optionB": "  Pericycle ",
            "optionC": "  Intercalary meristem ",
            "optionD": "  Lateral meristem ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCork cambium and vascular cambium are responsible for the increase in diameter of the stem and root of a plant. These are present in dicot plants. These are the lateral meristem and are responsible for the secondary growth of the plant. ",
            "keyString": "274956s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following transports water from the roots of the plant to its leaves?",
            "optionA": "  Xylem ",
            "optionB": "  Phloem ",
            "optionC": "  Both xylem and phloem ",
            "optionD": "  Cortex ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tXylem transports water from the roots of the plant to its leaves. ",
            "keyString": "274967s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The water and mineral salts are transported to the various organs by which of the following?",
            "optionA": "  Xylem ",
            "optionB": "  Phloem ",
            "optionC": "  Cortex ",
            "optionD": "  Cambium ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tXylem transports water and mineral salts from the roots up to other parts of the plant, while phloem transports sucrose and amino acids between the leaves and other parts of the plant. ",
            "keyString": "274978s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The process in which energy stored in carbohydrates is released",
            "optionA": "  Photosynthesis ",
            "optionB": "  Respiration ",
            "optionC": "  Reproduction ",
            "optionD": "  Excretion ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPhotosynthesis absorbs energy from sunlight to build carbohydrates in the chloroplasts, and aerobic cellular respiration releases that stored energy by using oxygen to break down carbohydrates. ",
            "keyString": "311726s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What is the purpose of the mucus in your nose?",
            "optionA": "  Protects lungs ",
            "optionB": "  Clear air passage ",
            "optionC": "  Protects nose ",
            "optionD": "  All of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMucus has a pretty important job \u2014 it keeps the lining of your nose moist and warms the air you breathe. Mucus also protects the lungs. When you breathe in air through your nose, it contains lots of tiny things, like dust, dirt, germs, and pollen. ",
            "keyString": "311761s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Precentage of CO2 found in exhaled air is",
            "optionA": "  0.04 ",
            "optionB": "  0.08 ",
            "optionC": "  0.12 ",
            "optionD": "  0.16 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPrecentage of CO2 found in exhaled air is 0.04. ",
            "keyString": "311776s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Muscles get tired when there is shortfall of ________ .",
            "optionA": "  Lactic acid ",
            "optionB": "  Na+ ions ",
            "optionC": "  ATP ",
            "optionD": "  Sulphates ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMuscles get tired when there is shortfall of ATP. ",
            "keyString": "311790s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Cellular respiration is best associated with the",
            "optionA": "  Microtubule ",
            "optionB": "  Ribosome ",
            "optionC": "  Golgi apparatus ",
            "optionD": "  Mitochondrion ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCellular respiration is best associated with the organelle mitochondrion. ",
            "keyString": "311803s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Late blight of potato is caused by",
            "optionA": "  Alternia solanii  ",
            "optionB": "  Phytophthora infestans  ",
            "optionC": "  Albugo candida  ",
            "optionD": "  Fusarium  ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tLate blight is caused by the oomycete Phytophthora infestans. Oomycetes are fungus-like organisms also called water molds, but they are not true fungi. ",
            "keyString": "347623s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Amoeba proteus was discovered by",
            "optionA": "  Gerald Durrell  ",
            "optionB": "  William Bullock  ",
            "optionC": "  Johann R\u00f6sel von Rosenhof  ",
            "optionD": "  Paul \u00c9mile de Puydt ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe earliest record of an amoeboid organism was produced in 1755 by August Johann R\u00f6sel von Rosenhof, who named his discovery \"Der Kleine Proteus\" (\"the Little Proteus\").",
            "keyString": "347652s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the fungi is commonly called as bread mould?",
            "optionA": "  Puccinia  ",
            "optionB": "  Rhizopus  ",
            "optionC": "  Ustilago  ",
            "optionD": "  All of these  ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRhizopus stolonifer is commonly known as black bread mold. It is a member of Zygomycota and considered the most important species in the genus Rhizopus. ",
            "keyString": "347666s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In N2 - fixation process, nitrite is converted to nitrate by",
            "optionA": "  Nitrobacter  ",
            "optionB": "  Azotobacter  ",
            "optionC": "  Nitosomonas  ",
            "optionD": "  Azospirillum  ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn N2 - fixation process, nitrite is converted to nitrate by nitrobacter. ",
            "keyString": "347679s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Green mould is common name for",
            "optionA": "  Neurospora  ",
            "optionB": "  Mucor  ",
            "optionC": "  Penicillium  ",
            "optionD": "  Saccharomyces  ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t Green mould is common name for Penicillium digitatum. ",
            "keyString": "347691s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Pellagra and Scurvy are caused by which pair of vitamin deficiency respectively ________ ",
            "optionA": "  Vitamin C and Vitamin D ",
            "optionB": "  Vitamin B-12 and Vitamin C ",
            "optionC": "  Vitamin C and Vitamin A ",
            "optionD": "  Vitamin A and Vitamin B-12 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPellagra and Scurvy are caused by Vitamin B-12 and Vitamin Cdeficiency respectively. ",
            "keyString": "402386s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The kilo calories of energy released from one gram of fats is",
            "optionA": "  5.49 ",
            "optionB": "  4.59 ",
            "optionC": "  9.45 ",
            "optionD": "  9.54 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCarbohydrates provide 4 calories per gram, protein provides 4 calories per gram, and fat provides 9 calories per gram. ",
            "keyString": "402416s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Deficiency of fluoride leads to which one of the following health problems?",
            "optionA": "  Tooth caries ",
            "optionB": "  Mottling of tooth ",
            "optionC": "  Bending of bones ",
            "optionD": "  Stiffening of joints ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFluoride deficiency is a disorder which may cause increased dental caries due to a lack of fluoride in the diet. Dental caries or tooth decay is the breakdown of dental tissues by the acidic products released by the \"bacterial fermentation of dietary carbohydrates\u201d. ",
            "keyString": "402430s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is not a function of proteins?",
            "optionA": "  Build tissues such as bone and muscle ",
            "optionB": "  Help to fight disease ",
            "optionC": "  Nail formation ",
            "optionD": "  Store and transmit heredity ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tStore and transmit heredity is not a function of proteins. ",
            "keyString": "402442s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Bleeding of gums, falling of teeth, fragile bones and delayed wound healing occur due to the deficiency of which one of the following vitamins?",
            "optionA": "  Vitamin C ",
            "optionB": "  Vitamin K ",
            "optionC": "  Vitamin D ",
            "optionD": "  Vitamin B ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDeficiency of Vitamin C causes Scurvy, Swelling of gums etc.Vitamin K causes Non-clotting of blood ,Vitamin D causes Rickets in children and Osteomalasia in adults, Vitamin B 1 causes Beriberi,B2 causes Cracking of skin,reddish eye,cracking of tongue,B3 causes Whitening of hair ,mentally retardness ,B5 causes Pallagra or 4D syndrome,B6 causes Anemia,skin disease ,B7 causes Paralysis,hair falling,B11 causes Dysentery and B12 causes Jaundice and Teroile Glutemi. ",
            "keyString": "402453s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Rate of transpiration can be measured by",
            "optionA": "  Ganong's potometer  ",
            "optionB": "  Auxanometer  ",
            "optionC": "  Respirometer  ",
            "optionD": "  Porometer  ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe uptake of water can be measured using a potometer. Under normal circumstances, the rate of water uptake gives a measure of the rate of transpiration . A simple potometer is a piece of capillary tubing to which a plant has been connected. Ganong's potometer is the right answer. ",
            "keyString": "424218s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Most highly intelligent mammals are",
            "optionA": "  whales ",
            "optionB": "  dolphins ",
            "optionC": "  elephants ",
            "optionD": "  kangaroos ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDolphins are the most highly intelligent mammals. ",
            "keyString": "459871s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Plant development is influenced by",
            "optionA": "  quality of light only ",
            "optionB": "  quality and quantity of light ",
            "optionC": "  quality and duration of light ",
            "optionD": "  quality, quantity and duration of light ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPlant development is influenced by quality, quantity and duration of light. Plants cannot get too much light, but they can get too much of the heat energy that comes with the light. ",
            "keyString": "459900s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Prokaryotic cells lack",
            "optionA": "  nucleolus ",
            "optionB": "  nuclear membrane ",
            "optionC": "  membrane bound by organelles ",
            "optionD": "  All of these ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tProkaryotic cells lack nucleolus, nuclear membrane and membrane bound by organelles. ",
            "keyString": "459914s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Photosynthesis takes place faster in",
            "optionA": "  yellow light ",
            "optionB": "  white light ",
            "optionC": "  red light ",
            "optionD": "  darkness ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAs far as the rate of photosynthesis is concerned, it is fastest in white light making the rate of photosynthesis maximum. After white, we have violet light where photosynthesis occur to a higher extent as it has the shortest wavelength hence has the max energy. ",
            "keyString": "459924s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Nucleus, the genetic material containing rounded body in each cell, was first discovered in 1831 by",
            "optionA": "  Robert Hooke ",
            "optionB": "  Robert Brown ",
            "optionC": "  Rudolf Virchow ",
            "optionD": "  Theodore Schwann ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNucleus, the genetic material containing rounded body in each cell, was first discovered in 1831 by Robert Brown. ",
            "keyString": "459935s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Study of process of ageing",
            "optionA": "  Genocology ",
            "optionB": "  Geronotology ",
            "optionC": "  Ontogeny ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGerontology, the study of the aging process, is devoted to the understanding and control of all factors contributing to the finitude of individual life. ",
            "keyString": "497710s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Sweating is important",
            "optionA": "  For improvement of normal health ",
            "optionB": "  To open the pore of skin ",
            "optionC": "  To control the temperature of body ",
            "optionD": "  To excret the smell of body ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe main function of sweating is to control body temperature. As the water in the sweat evaporates, the surface of the skin cools. An additional function of sweat is to help with gripping, by slightly moistening the palms. ",
            "keyString": "497740s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The outermost layer of skin is",
            "optionA": "  Epidermis ",
            "optionB": "  Dermis ",
            "optionC": "  Tissues ",
            "optionD": "  Hypodermis ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe stratum corneum is the outermost layer of the epidermis, and is made up of 10 to 30 thin layers of continually shedding, dead keratinocytes. ",
            "keyString": "497755s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Homeostasis is the condition in which the body maintains",
            "optionA": "  A relatively stable internal environment within limits ",
            "optionB": "  A changing state within an unlimited range ",
            "optionC": "  The lowest possible energy usage ",
            "optionD": "  A static state with no deviation from preset points ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tHomeostasis is the condition in which a system such as the human body is maintained in a more-or-less steady state. ",
            "keyString": "497768s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The normal temperature of human body on the Kelvin scale is",
            "optionA": "  280K ",
            "optionB": "  290K ",
            "optionC": "  300K ",
            "optionD": "  310K ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe normal temperature of human body on the Kelvin scale is 310K. ",
            "keyString": "497780s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The phenomenon of summer sleep by animals is called",
            "optionA": "  Hibernation ",
            "optionB": "  Aestivation ",
            "optionC": "  Laziness ",
            "optionD": "  Lethargy ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAestivation is a state of animal dormancy, similar to hibernation, although taking place in the summer rather than the winter. ",
            "keyString": "572134s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Animals who have constant body temperature are",
            "optionA": "  Homeothermic ",
            "optionB": "  Hemothermic ",
            "optionC": "  Hematology ",
            "optionD": "  Histology ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAnimals who have constant body temperature are homeothermic. ",
            "keyString": "572165s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which type of cell, skin is made up of:",
            "optionA": "  Epidermal cells ",
            "optionB": "  Connective tissue ",
            "optionC": "  Permanent tissues ",
            "optionD": "  Parenchyma ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSkin is made up of epidermal cells. ",
            "keyString": "572178s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Cold blooded animals are known as",
            "optionA": "  Homiotherms  ",
            "optionB": "  Eurytherms  ",
            "optionC": "  Endotherms  ",
            "optionD": "  Poikilotherms  ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCold blooded animals are known as Poikilotherms. ",
            "keyString": "572191s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Ginger is a stem and not a root because",
            "optionA": "  It stores food ",
            "optionB": "  It lacks chlorophyll ",
            "optionC": "  It has nodes and internodes ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGinger is a stem which can be differentiated from root because it (1) Grows parallel to ground. (2) Stores food. (3) Lacks chlorophyll. (4) Has nodes and internodes. ",
            "keyString": "572202s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Grassland with scattered tree is known as",
            "optionA": "  Savanna  ",
            "optionB": "  Deciduous Forests  ",
            "optionC": "  Evergreen Forests  ",
            "optionD": "  Tropical Rain Forests  ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSavanna is grassland with scattered individual trees. ",
            "keyString": "607279s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Dr. Birbal Sahni; a famous Indian botanist is concerned with ________ studies.",
            "optionA": "  Algal  ",
            "optionB": "  Fossil  ",
            "optionC": "  Bryophytic  ",
            "optionD": "  Fungal  ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBirbal Sahni (14 November 1891 \u2013 10 April 1949) was an Indian paleobotanist who studied the fossils of the Indian subcontinent. He also took an interest in geology and archaeology. He founded what is now the Birbal Sahni Institute of Palaeobotany at Lucknow in 1946. ",
            "keyString": "607310s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Plants which grow on saline soils are known as",
            "optionA": "  Xerophytes  ",
            "optionB": "  Hydrophytes  ",
            "optionC": "  Halophytes  ",
            "optionD": "  Succulents  ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA halophyte is a salt-tolerant plant that grows in soil or waters of high salinity, coming into contact with saline water through its roots or by salt spray, such as in saline semi-deserts, mangrove swamps, marshes and sloughs and seashores. ",
            "keyString": "607324s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following organisms fix nitrogen in aquatic ecosystems?",
            "optionA": "  Fungi  ",
            "optionB": "  Chemoautotrophs  ",
            "optionC": "  Cyanobacteria  ",
            "optionD": "  Phytoplankton  ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFungi fix nitrogen in aquatic ecosystems. ",
            "keyString": "607337s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which ecological pyramid can never be inverted",
            "optionA": "  Pyramid of number  ",
            "optionB": "  Pyramid of size  ",
            "optionC": "  Pyramid of energy  ",
            "optionD": "  Pyramid of biomass  ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe pyramid of energy can never be inverted. The pyramid represents the amount of energy at each trophic level of the food chain. ",
            "keyString": "607348s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Most of the red, blue and purple colours of plants are due to a pigment called",
            "optionA": "  anthocyanin ",
            "optionB": "  carotene ",
            "optionC": "  chlorophyll ",
            "optionD": "  xanthophylls ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAnthocyanin - A blue, violet, or red flavonoid pigment found in plants.",
            "keyString": "643671s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Plants developing in dry conditions are",
            "optionA": "  xerophytes ",
            "optionB": "  mesophytes ",
            "optionC": "  lithophytes ",
            "optionD": "  hydrophytes ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tXerophytes are adapted to survive in hot deserts where there is very little water. Xerophytes are common in coastal areas and thrive in saline water. ",
            "keyString": "643701s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Plants growing on sand are called as",
            "optionA": "  chasmophytes ",
            "optionB": "  oxylophytes ",
            "optionC": "  lithophytes ",
            "optionD": "  psammophytes ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPsammophytes are plants that preferentially grow in sand. ",
            "keyString": "643715s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Our skin, when exposed to excess sunlight, becomes dark. This is because of our skin pigments called",
            "optionA": "  flavoxanthin ",
            "optionB": "  melanin ",
            "optionC": "  carotene ",
            "optionD": "  Xanthophyll ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tWithin the skin's epidermal (outer) layer are cells that contain the pigment melanin. Suntanning occurs because exposure to sunlight causes the skin to produce more melanin and to darken. The tan fades as these cells move toward the surface and are sloughed off. ",
            "keyString": "643728s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Ramapithecus and Cro-Magnon man are considered",
            "optionA": "  ancestors of modern man ",
            "optionB": "  ancestors of monkey ",
            "optionC": "  ancestors of lion ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRamapithecus and Cro-Magnon man are considered ancestors of modern man. ",
            "keyString": "643740s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following is not a genetic disorder?",
            "optionA": "  Colour blindness ",
            "optionB": "  Down's syndrome ",
            "optionC": "  Haemophilia ",
            "optionD": "  Xerophthalmia ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tXerophthalmia is not a genetic disorder. ",
            "keyString": "679288s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who is known as Father of Modern Genetics?",
            "optionA": "  Charles Darwin  ",
            "optionB": "  Louis Pasteur  ",
            "optionC": "  Gregor Mendel  ",
            "optionD": "  Jean Baptiste Lamarck  ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGregor Mendel is known as Father of Modern Genetics. ",
            "keyString": "679316s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "How many pairs of chromosomes are found in a human cell?",
            "optionA": "  18  ",
            "optionB": "  23  ",
            "optionC": "  27  ",
            "optionD": "  32  ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA human cell has 23 pairs of chromosomes. ",
            "keyString": "679330s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The experimental material used by Gregor Mendel is ________",
            "optionA": "  Pea plant  ",
            "optionB": "  Drossophila  ",
            "optionC": "  Potato plant  ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above  ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMendel carried out his key experiments using the garden pea, Pisum sativum, as a model system. ",
            "keyString": "679341s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Mendel's second law is the law of",
            "optionA": "  Segregation  ",
            "optionB": "  Independent assortment  ",
            "optionC": "  Dominance  ",
            "optionD": "  Polygenic inheritance  ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe results of Mendel's second set of experiments led to his second law. This is the law of independent assortment. It states that factors controlling different characteristics are inherited independently of each other. ",
            "keyString": "679352s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What prevents food from entering the windpipe?",
            "optionA": "  Epiglottis ",
            "optionB": "  Pharynx ",
            "optionC": "  Trachea ",
            "optionD": "  Larynx ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn the second stage of swallowing, an important small flap of tissue called the epiglottis, folds over the voice box (larynx) at the entrance to the windpipe (trachea), preventing food from going down the wrong way. ",
            "keyString": "713791s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is true of enzymes?",
            "optionA": "  Enzymes lowers the activation energy for the chemical reaction ",
            "optionB": "  Enzymes speed up the rate of a chemical reaction ",
            "optionC": "  Both A & B ",
            "optionD": "  Neither A nor B ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tEnzymes lowers the activation energy for the chemical reaction and speed up the rate of a chemical reaction. ",
            "keyString": "713820s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The substances, which assist enzymes act, are called",
            "optionA": "  Diastase ",
            "optionB": "  Substrates ",
            "optionC": "  Co-enzymes ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCatalysts accelerate chemical reactions. The molecules upon which enzymes may act are called substrates, and the enzyme converts the substrates into different molecules known as products. ",
            "keyString": "713833s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Biological catalysis in living organisms are known as",
            "optionA": "  Hormones ",
            "optionB": "  Vitamins ",
            "optionC": "  Steroids ",
            "optionD": "  Enzymes ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tEnzymes are biological catalysts produced by all living organisms. They facilitate the biochemical reactions that enable microbes, plants and animals to function. ",
            "keyString": "713845s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is not a function of saliva?",
            "optionA": "  Contains fluoride to harden the tooth enamel ",
            "optionB": "  Moistens food and helps stick it together to make it easier to swallow ",
            "optionC": "  Begins the chemical breakdown of starches ",
            "optionD": "  Helps clean the mouth ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tContains fluoride to harden the tooth enamel is not a function of saliva. ",
            "keyString": "713856s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which structure is specific to eukaryotic cells?",
            "optionA": "  Nucleus ",
            "optionB": "  DNA ",
            "optionC": "  Cytoplasm ",
            "optionD": "  Cell membrane ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNucleus is specific to eukaryotic cell. ",
            "keyString": "749738s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of these statements is true of the kingdom protista?",
            "optionA": "  All are unicellular ",
            "optionB": "  All are hetertrophic ",
            "optionC": "  All are autotrophic ",
            "optionD": "  All are eukaryotic ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe statement that is true of the kingdom protists is that all are eukaryotic. ",
            "keyString": "749768s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Study of internal structure of organism is called",
            "optionA": "  Morphology ",
            "optionB": "  Anatomy ",
            "optionC": "  Histology ",
            "optionD": "  Cytology ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAnatomy is the branch of biology concerned with the study of the structure of organisms and their parts. ",
            "keyString": "749782s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Biology is the scientific study of ",
            "optionA": "  Plants ",
            "optionB": "  Animals ",
            "optionC": "  Bacteria ",
            "optionD": "  Living organisms ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBiology is a natural science concerned with the study of life and living organisms. ",
            "keyString": "749795s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following does not have blood but undergoes respiration?",
            "optionA": "  Cockroach ",
            "optionB": "  Snail ",
            "optionC": "  Hydra ",
            "optionD": "  Kangaroo ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCockroach has blood known as homocoel, snails and kangaroos also have blood in their bodies. But hydra does not contain any blood but still it respires. It does not have any respiratory organs but it respires and thus exchanges gases throughout its body. ",
            "keyString": "749807s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The outer white part of the eye which is supporting wall of the eyeball is known as",
            "optionA": "  Cornea  ",
            "optionB": "  Sclera  ",
            "optionC": "  Iris  ",
            "optionD": "  Retina  ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe eye has three main layers. These layers lie flat against each other and form the eyeball. The outer layer of the eyeball is a tough, white, opaque membrane called the sclera (the white of the eye). The slight bulge in the sclera at the front of the eye is a clear, thin, dome-shaped tissue called the cornea. ",
            "keyString": "784376s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Human eye can differentiate between colours due to",
            "optionA": "  Rods  ",
            "optionB": "  Cones  ",
            "optionC": "  Bipolar nerves  ",
            "optionD": "  Pigmented epithelium  ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNormal cones and pigment sensitivity enable an individual to distinguish all the different colours as well as subtle mixtures of hues. This type of normal colour vision is known as trichromacy and relies upon the mutual interaction from the overlapping sensitivity ranges of all three types of photoreceptor cone. ",
            "keyString": "784403s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The outer membrane that covers the brain is",
            "optionA": "  Myelin sheath ",
            "optionB": "  Dura mater ",
            "optionC": "  Arachnoid membrane ",
            "optionD": "  Pia mater ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThree layers of membranes known as meninges protect the brain and spinal cord. The delicate inner layer is the pia mater. The middle layer is the arachnoid, a web-like structure filled with fluid that cushions the brain. The tough outer layer is called the dura mater. ",
            "keyString": "784416s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The innermost membrane that covers the brain is",
            "optionA": "  Pleura ",
            "optionB": "  Duramater ",
            "optionC": "  Pia mater ",
            "optionD": "  Arachnoid membrane ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe pia mater is the innermost layer of meninges. This thin, delicate membrane is tightly bound to the surface of the brain and spinal cord and cannot be dissected away without damaging the surface. Meningiomas are tumors of the nerve tissue covering the brain and spinal cord. ",
            "keyString": "784427s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which systems comprise the nervous system?",
            "optionA": "  Central nervous system ",
            "optionB": "  Peripheral nervous system ",
            "optionC": "  Both A & B ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe nervous system has two main parts: The central nervous system is made up of the brain and spinal cord. The peripheral nervous system is made up of nerves that branch off from the spinal cord and extend to all parts of the body. ",
            "keyString": "784437s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which is the innermost layer of the heart?",
            "optionA": "  Epicardium  ",
            "optionB": "  Endocardium  ",
            "optionC": "  Myocardium  ",
            "optionD": "  Pericardium  ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe inner layer of the heart wall is the endocardium, composed of endothelial cells that provide a smooth, elastic, non-adherent surface for blood collection and pumping. ",
            "keyString": "819730s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "________ is a hormone that regulates the amount of glucose in the blood.",
            "optionA": "  Glucogen ",
            "optionB": "  Thyroxine ",
            "optionC": "  Oxytocin ",
            "optionD": "  Insulin ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tInsulin is a peptide hormone made in the beta cells of the pancreas that is central to regulating carbohydrate metabolism in the body. After a meal, insulin is secreted into the bloodstream. ",
            "keyString": "819758s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of following is known as pace maker of endocrine gland?",
            "optionA": "  Thyroxin ",
            "optionB": "  Calcitonin ",
            "optionC": "  Insulin ",
            "optionD": "  Adrenalin ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThyroxin is secreted by thyroid gland (the largest gland), situated in neck region. Thyroxine regulates the metabolic rate, thus, called as pacesetter of the body. If there's more of thyroxine present in the blood, processes take place at a faster rate, energy is utilized at a faster rate, and if the amount of thyroxine secreted is less than required, the processes of the body take place at a slower pace, lesser energy utilization. Thus, functioning of thyroid gland has major effect on all the organs of our body. ",
            "keyString": "819771s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The rate of heartbeat is accelerated by the hormone",
            "optionA": "  Adrenaline ",
            "optionB": "  Acetylcholine ",
            "optionC": "  Thyroxine ",
            "optionD": "  Pituitrin ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe rate of heartbeat is accelerated by the hormone. The hormone adrenaline also called epinephrine is known as a stress hormone. In emotional upsets( like fear, anger etc.) this hormone is poured into the blood and it accelerates heart beat. ",
            "keyString": "819782s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Cortisol is secreted by",
            "optionA": "  Thyroid gland ",
            "optionB": "  Pituitary gland ",
            "optionC": "  Adrenal gland ",
            "optionD": "  Parathyroid gland ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCortisol is released from the adrenal cortex and allows the body to continue to stay on high alert. ",
            "keyString": "819792s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Reflex actions are controlled by",
            "optionA": "  The Spinal Chord ",
            "optionB": "  The Nerves ",
            "optionC": "  The cells ",
            "optionD": "  The Brain ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA reflex arc is a neural pathway that controls a reflex. In vertebrates, most sensory neurons do not pass directly into the brain, but synapse in the spinal cord. This allows for faster reflex actions to occur by activating spinal motor neurons without the delay of routing signals through the brain. ",
            "keyString": "855513s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What part of the body controls balance?",
            "optionA": "  Cerebrum ",
            "optionB": "  Cerebellum ",
            "optionC": "  Medulla oblangata ",
            "optionD": "  Amygdala ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe cerebellum, in the back of the brain, controls balance, coordination and fine muscle control (e.g., walking). It also functions to maintain posture and equilibrium. ",
            "keyString": "855542s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which part of the brain is responsible for consciousness?",
            "optionA": "  Brain stem ",
            "optionB": "  Cerebrum ",
            "optionC": "  Cerebellum ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe cerebrum is the largest brain structure and part of the forebrain (or prosencephalon). Its prominent outer portion, the cerebral cortex, not only processes sensory and motor information but enables consciousness, our ability to consider ourselves and the outside world. ",
            "keyString": "855556s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which part of Nervous system controls involuntary actions?",
            "optionA": "  Medulla oblongata ",
            "optionB": "  Cerebellum ",
            "optionC": "  Hypothalamus ",
            "optionD": "  Spinal cord ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMedulla oblongata controls involuntary actions. ",
            "keyString": "855567s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The brain is covered by",
            "optionA": "  Meninges ",
            "optionB": "  Skin ",
            "optionC": "  Bone ",
            "optionD": "  All the above ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe brain is covered by meninges, skin and bone. ",
            "keyString": "855577s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following glands is both endocrine and exocrine?",
            "optionA": "  Pancreas  ",
            "optionB": "  Pituitary  ",
            "optionC": "  Adrenal  ",
            "optionD": "  Pineal  ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe liver and pancreas are both exocrine and endocrine glands; they are exocrine glands because they secrete products\u2014bile and pancreatic juice\u2014into the gastrointestinal tract through a series of ducts, and endocrine because they secrete other substances directly into the bloodstream. ",
            "keyString": "890310s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which hormone causes emotional disturbance?",
            "optionA": "  Thyroxine  ",
            "optionB": "  Oxytocin  ",
            "optionC": "  Vasopressin  ",
            "optionD": "  Adrenalin  ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOxytocin causes emotional disturbance. ",
            "keyString": "890337s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Haemophilia is a hereditary disease carried by",
            "optionA": "  Females and expressed by males ",
            "optionB": "  Males and expressed by males ",
            "optionC": "  Females and expressed by females ",
            "optionD": "  Males and expressed by females ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tHaemophilia is a hereditary disease carried by females and expressed by males. ",
            "keyString": "890350s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The sex of a newborn baby is determined by the chromosome inherited from",
            "optionA": "  The Father ",
            "optionB": "  The Mother ",
            "optionC": "  The Father's Father ",
            "optionD": "  Both A & B ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe sex of a baby is determined by two sex chromosomes inherited from both the genetic parents. A baby will normally inherit one sex chromosome from the mother and one from the father. A woman has two X chromosomes and thus gives either of her X chromosomes. The father has one X chromosome and one Y chromosome, can give either his X or Y chromosome. The egg (from the mother) already contains an X chromosome. Therefore the sex of a baby is determined by the X or Y chromosome of thesperm cell from the father.",
            "keyString": "890362s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The chromosome number 2n is known as",
            "optionA": "  Haploid number ",
            "optionB": "  Diploid number ",
            "optionC": "  Triploid number ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn sexually reproducing organisms, the number of chromosomes in the body (somatic) cells typically is diploid (2n; a pair of each chromosome), twice the haploid (1n) number found in the sex cells, or gametes. ",
            "keyString": "890372s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Reflex actions are controlled by : ",
            "optionA": "  The cells ",
            "optionB": "  The Spinal Chord ",
            "optionC": "  The Brain ",
            "optionD": "  The Nerves ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA reflex arc is a neural pathway that controls a reflex. In vertebrates, most sensory neurons do not pass directly into the brain, but synapse in the spinal cord. This allows for faster reflex actions to occur by activating spinal motor neurons without the delay of routing signals through the brain. ",
            "keyString": "925605s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following is not an insect: ",
            "optionA": "  Bed bug ",
            "optionB": "  House fly ",
            "optionC": "  Mosquitoes ",
            "optionD": "  Spider ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSpiders are arachnids. So are scorpions, mites, and ticks. Arachnids are classified primarily by having eight legs and two distinct body regions, the cephalothorax (which is a fusion of the head and thorax), and the abdomen. ",
            "keyString": "925633s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which cell organelles are involved in photosynthesis?",
            "optionA": "  Chloroplasts ",
            "optionB": "  Plastids ",
            "optionC": "  Lipids ",
            "optionD": "  Plasmids ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn plants, photosynthesis takes place in chloroplasts, which contain the chlorophyll. Chloroplasts are surrounded by a double membrane and contain a third inner membrane, called the thylakoid membrane, that forms long folds within the organelle. ",
            "keyString": "925646s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "It consists of an aqueous ground substance containing a variety of cell organelles and other inclusions such as wastes and storage products.",
            "optionA": "  Cytoplasm ",
            "optionB": "  Actoplasm ",
            "optionC": "  Endoplasm ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCytoplasm consists of an aqueous ground substance, the cytosol, containing a variety of cell organelles and other inclusions such as insoluble waste and storage products (starch, glycogen, lipid, etc.) ",
            "keyString": "925657s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The study of structures of organisms, their cells and their organelles at molecular level is known as ",
            "optionA": "  Molecular biology ",
            "optionB": "  Environmental biology ",
            "optionC": "  Microbiology ",
            "optionD": "  Cell biology ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tStudy of cell structure and function is called cell biology. Cell biology is a branch of biology that studies cells, their physiological properties, their structure, the organelles they contain, interactions with their environment, their life cycle, division, death and cell function. ",
            "keyString": "925667s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Virus range in size from",
            "optionA": "  2 nm to 70 nm ",
            "optionB": "  2 nm to 100 nm ",
            "optionC": "  2 nm to 200 nm ",
            "optionD": "  2 nm to 300 nm ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA virus is an infectious agent of small size and simple composition that can multiply only in living cells of animals, plants, or bacteria. They range in size from about 20 to 300 nanometres in diameter. ",
            "keyString": "962147s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Virus was discovered by",
            "optionA": "  V.M.Stanely ",
            "optionB": "  Stanely Miller ",
            "optionC": "  ",
            "optionD": " Iwanowski ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTwo scientists contributed to the discovery of the first virus, Tobacco mosaic virus. Ivanoski reported in 1892 that extracts from infected leaves were still infectious after filtration through a Chamberland filter-candle.",
            "keyString": "962176s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The study of microorganisms is termed as ",
            "optionA": "  Evolution ",
            "optionB": "  Microbiology ",
            "optionC": "  Zoology ",
            "optionD": "  Palaeontology ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTechnically a microorganism or microbe is an organism that is microscopic. The study of microorganisms is called microbiology. ",
            "keyString": "962190s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Entamoeba Histolytica is a",
            "optionA": "  Virus  ",
            "optionB": "  Protozoan  ",
            "optionC": "  Fungus  ",
            "optionD": "  Bacteria  ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tEntamoeba histolytica is a protozoan parasite that accounts for an estimated 100,000 annual deaths globally. ",
            "keyString": "962203s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Amoeba belongs to which group",
            "optionA": "  Protozoa  ",
            "optionB": "  Bacteria  ",
            "optionC": "  Fungi  ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above  ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAmoeba belongs to which group protozoa. ",
            "keyString": "962216s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Photosynthesis occurs in",
            "optionA": "  Nucleus  ",
            "optionB": "  Mitochondria  ",
            "optionC": "  Chloroplast  ",
            "optionD": "  Peroxisome  ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn plants, photosynthesis takes place in chloroplasts, which contain the chlorophyll. Chloroplasts are surrounded by a double membrane and contain a third inner membrane, called the thylakoid membrane, that forms long folds within the organelle. ",
            "keyString": "999906s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Sulphur Dioxide pollution is indicated by an excessive growth of which of the following?",
            "optionA": "  Algal Blooms ",
            "optionB": "  Lichens ",
            "optionC": "  Bryophytes ",
            "optionD": "  Protozoa ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIf air is polluted with sulphur dioxide, then lichens will die in that particular environment. Since the era of industrialization, many species of lichens have gone extinct. Due to this property, lichens are considered to be the indicators of the air pollution. ",
            "keyString": "999943s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Food wrapped in news paper is likely to get contaminated by ",
            "optionA": "  Magnesium ",
            "optionB": "  Alluminium ",
            "optionC": "  Lead ",
            "optionD": "  Copper ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFood wrapped in newspaper is likely to get contaminated with lead. ",
            "keyString": "999961s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What is full form of BOD?",
            "optionA": "  Biological Oxygen Deficit ",
            "optionB": "  Biological Oxygen Difference ",
            "optionC": "  Biological Oxygen Demand ",
            "optionD": "  Biological Oxygen Distribution ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBiological Oxygen Demand is full form of BOD. ",
            "keyString": "999975s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The non-biotic pollutant of underground water is",
            "optionA": "  Bacteria  ",
            "optionB": "  Algae  ",
            "optionC": "  Arsenic  ",
            "optionD": "  Viruses  ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe non-biotic pollutant of underground water is arsenic. ",
            "keyString": "999988s38m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following organelles contain enzymes that have digestive action?",
            "optionA": "  Plastids  ",
            "optionB": "  Lysosomes  ",
            "optionC": "  Ribosomes  ",
            "optionD": "  Polysomes  ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tLysosomes are membrane-enclosed organelles that contain an array of enzymes capable of breaking down all types of biological polymers\u2014proteins, nucleic acids, carbohydrates, and lipids. ",
            "keyString": "40832s39m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "They are also concerned with the formation and storage of certain compounds secreted by the cell.",
            "optionA": "  Lysosomes ",
            "optionB": "  Golgi Bodies ",
            "optionC": "  Centriole ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGolgi Bodies are also concerned with the formation and storage of certain compounds secreted by the cell. ",
            "keyString": "40902s39m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Carbon monoxide has ________ greater affinity for haemoglobin as compared to oxygen.",
            "optionA": "  1000 times ",
            "optionB": "  210 times ",
            "optionC": "  20 times ",
            "optionD": "  2 times ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCarbon monoxide has 210 times greater affinity for haemoglobin than oxygen. ",
            "keyString": "40954s39m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Sphygmomanometer measures the blood pressure in the",
            "optionA": "  Veins ",
            "optionB": "  Arteries ",
            "optionC": "  Eyes ",
            "optionD": "  Synovial ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA sphygmomanometer has three parts: a cuff that can be inflated with air, a pressure meter (manometer) for measuring air pressure in the cuff, and. a stethoscope for listening to the sound the blood makes as it flows through the brachial artery (the major artery found in your upper arm). ",
            "keyString": "41003s39m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which statement best describes arteries?",
            "optionA": "  They have thin walls and transport blood away from the heart ",
            "optionB": "  They have thick walls and transport blood toward the heart ",
            "optionC": "  They have thin walls and transport blood toward the heart ",
            "optionD": "  They have thick walls and transport blood away from the heart ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThey have thick walls and transport blood away from the heart. ",
            "keyString": "41053s39m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In plants, chloroplasts are necessary for ",
            "optionA": "  Photosynthesis ",
            "optionB": "  Storage ",
            "optionC": "  Cell movement ",
            "optionD": "  Respiration ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn plants and algae, which developed much later, photosynthesis occurs in a specialized intracellular organelle - the chloroplast.",
            "keyString": "77377s39m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which of the following organelles does photosynthesis take place?",
            "optionA": "  Miochondria ",
            "optionB": "  Chloroplast ",
            "optionC": "  Central Vacuole ",
            "optionD": "  Ribosome ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPhotosynthesis take place in chloroplast. ",
            "keyString": "77406s39m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "It is a heredity material and contains the genetic information which is passed on from one generation to another.",
            "optionA": "  RNA ",
            "optionB": "  DNA ",
            "optionC": "  Chromosomes ",
            "optionD": "  Carbohydrates ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDNA is a heredity material and contains the genetic information which is passed on from one generation to another. ",
            "keyString": "77419s39m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Where is the genetic information of the cell stored?",
            "optionA": "  DNA ",
            "optionB": "  Cell membrane ",
            "optionC": "  Nucleus ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe genetic information of an organism is stored in DNA molecules. ",
            "keyString": "77430s39m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Where does protein synthesis take place in a cell?",
            "optionA": "  Ribosomes ",
            "optionB": "  Mitochondria ",
            "optionC": "  Cytoplasm ",
            "optionD": "  Nucleus ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tProtein synthesis takes place in ribosomes of a cell. ",
            "keyString": "77441s39m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Name the part of neuron where information is acquired.",
            "optionA": "  Axon ",
            "optionB": "  Nucleus ",
            "optionC": "  Dendrite ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe part of neuron where the information is acquired is ends of dendrites. ",
            "keyString": "131855s39m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The basic unit of the nervous system is the",
            "optionA": "  Lymphs ",
            "optionB": "  Nephrons ",
            "optionC": "  Nerves ",
            "optionD": "  Neurons ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe basic unit of the nervous system is a nerve cell, or neuron. The human brain contains about 100 billion neurons. ",
            "keyString": "131883s39m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The weight of the brain in the total weight of the body is about",
            "optionA": "  2% ",
            "optionB": "  3% ",
            "optionC": "  4% ",
            "optionD": "  5% ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe adult human brain weighs about 3 pounds (1,300-1,400 g). The adult human brain is about 2 % of the total body weight. The average human brain is 140 mm wide. So, the correct answer is 2%. ",
            "keyString": "131895s39m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Cerebrum is located in which part of brain?",
            "optionA": "  Lower side ",
            "optionB": "  Extension of brain ",
            "optionC": "  Fore front ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCerebrum is located in fore front of brain. ",
            "keyString": "131907s39m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The smallest structural and functional unit of nervous system is",
            "optionA": "  Centron ",
            "optionB": "  Dendron ",
            "optionC": "  Axon ",
            "optionD": "  Neuron ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe smallest functional unit of the nervous system is the neuron. Neurons are specialized cells that send out neurotransmitters to other neurons. ",
            "keyString": "131917s39m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "A typical chromosome has two parts a centrifuge and ________",
            "optionA": "  Blastomeres ",
            "optionB": "  Chromosomes ",
            "optionC": "  Centrosomes ",
            "optionD": "  Ribosomes ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA typical chromosome has two parts a centrifuge and Centrosome. ",
            "keyString": "168868s39m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "How does a Unicellular Organism reproduce?",
            "optionA": "  Cell division ",
            "optionB": "  Cell reproduction ",
            "optionC": "  Cell synthesis ",
            "optionD": "  Fragmentation ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn unicellular eukaryotes, reproduction can occur by mitosis and cytokinesis\u2014the other form of cell division. ",
            "keyString": "168896s39m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Healing of wounds is dependent upon the ________ division of underlying cells.",
            "optionA": "  Meiosis ",
            "optionB": "  Mitotic ",
            "optionC": "  Budding ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tHealing of wounds is dependent upon the mitotic division of underlying cells. ",
            "keyString": "168909s39m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "It is formed by a repeating nucleosome units, which are closely attached to each other to a continuous fibre.",
            "optionA": "  Chromatin ",
            "optionB": "  Centromere ",
            "optionC": "  Chromosome ",
            "optionD": "  DNA ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tChromatin is formed by a repeating nucleosome units, which are closely attached to each other to a continuous fibre. ",
            "keyString": "168920s39m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "It is the site of chromosome attachment to the fibres of spindle.",
            "optionA": "  Chromomere ",
            "optionB": "  Centromere ",
            "optionC": "  Centrosme ",
            "optionD": "  Blastomere ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe centromere is the part of a chromosome where the sister chromatids are linked together during the cell division. In mitosis, spindle fibres attach to the centromere via the kinetochore. Centromeres were first defined as genetic loci that direct the behaviour of chromosomes. ",
            "keyString": "168931s39m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which statement regarding the mammalian heart is correct?",
            "optionA": "  Blood is pumped from the heart via the atria ",
            "optionB": "  Oxygen-loaded blood moves only through the right side of the heart ",
            "optionC": "  When the right atrium contracts, it forces blood into the left atrium ",
            "optionD": "  In the adult heart, blood in the right chambers of the heart cannot enter the left chambers without passing through the lungs ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn the adult heart, blood in the right chambers of the heart cannot enter the left chambers without passing through the lungs. ",
            "keyString": "206095s39m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "An individual whose blood type is B may in an emergency, donate blood to a person whose blood type is",
            "optionA": "  B or A ",
            "optionB": "  AB or A ",
            "optionC": "  A or O ",
            "optionD": "  AB or B ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAn individual whose blood type is B may in an emergency, donate blood to a person whose blood type is AB or B. ",
            "keyString": "206124s39m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following carries oxygen to various parts of human body?",
            "optionA": "  Red blood cells ",
            "optionB": "  White blood cells ",
            "optionC": "  Plasma ",
            "optionD": "  Nerves ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tHemoglobin is the protein inside red blood cells that carries oxygen to various parts of human body. ",
            "keyString": "206137s39m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Instrument used to measure blood pressure is",
            "optionA": "  E.",
            "optionB": "G ",
            "optionC": "  Stetheoscope ",
            "optionD": "  sphygmomanometer ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tYou can measure your blood pressure on your own using a digital blood pressure monitor for automated readings or an instrument called a sphygmomanometer for manual readings. ",
            "keyString": "206148s39m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Lymph carries digested and absorbed fat from ________ .",
            "optionA": "  Lungs ",
            "optionB": "  Intestine ",
            "optionC": "  Stomach ",
            "optionD": "  Kidney ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tLymph carries digested and absorbed fat from intestine and drains excess fluid from extra cellular space back into the blood. ",
            "keyString": "206158s39m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "They are probably the simplest and the smallest living organisms possessing cellular organisation.",
            "optionA": "  Viruses ",
            "optionB": "  Fungi ",
            "optionC": "  Mosses ",
            "optionD": "  Bacteria ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBacteria are probably the simplest and the smallest living organisms possessing cellular organisation. ",
            "keyString": "280996s39m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Sexual reproduction in Algae that takes place through fusion of two dissimilar size gametes is called",
            "optionA": "  Zoospores ",
            "optionB": "  Anisogamous ",
            "optionC": "  Isogamous ",
            "optionD": "  Oogamous ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAnisogamy (also called heterogamy) is the form of sexual reproduction that involves the union or fusion of two gametes, which differ in size and/or form. ",
            "keyString": "281026s39m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Floridian starch is characteristic energy storage material of which algae?",
            "optionA": "  Blue green algae ",
            "optionB": "  Brown algae ",
            "optionC": "  Red algae ",
            "optionD": "  Green algae ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe floridian starch is reserve food materials in the red algae or the members of class Rhodophytae. It is a characteristic feature of this group. ",
            "keyString": "281040s39m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following does not have any enzymes in its cells?",
            "optionA": "  Algae ",
            "optionB": "  Virus ",
            "optionC": "  Lichen ",
            "optionD": "  Bacteria ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tVirus is not a cell; it remains just in the form of a genetic material or encapsulated on outside with a protein capsid. It generally injects its genetic material into host cells wherein the viral proteins get synthesised. ",
            "keyString": "281051s39m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Statement which is true about bacteria ?",
            "optionA": "  All bacteria are autotrophs ",
            "optionB": "  Most of them are heterotrophs but some are autotrophs ",
            "optionC": "  All bacteria heterophs ",
            "optionD": "  All bacteria are photosynthetic ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMost of the bacteria are heterotrophs but some are autotrophs. ",
            "keyString": "281061s39m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Where the mature sperm are produced?",
            "optionA": "  Scrotum ",
            "optionB": "  Vas deferens ",
            "optionC": "  Prostate gland ",
            "optionD": "  Testes ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe structure on top of the seminiferous tubules in the testes is the epididymis. The sperm migrate from of the seminiferous tubules to the epididymis. Within the epididymis, the sperm mature while they are stored in this structure. ",
            "keyString": "316422s39m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "During rainy season wooden doors are difficult to open or closure because of ?",
            "optionA": "  Imbibition ",
            "optionB": "  Plasmolysis ",
            "optionC": "  Diffusion ",
            "optionD": "  Osmosis ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tImbibition is a process in which the biological colloidal substances absorb water and show swelling and increase in volume. This happens when the wood of doors and window absorb water and swell during rainy season and cause problems as these do not fit in the frame and do not get closed. ",
            "keyString": "316452s39m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which statement concerning the diagnosis of ADHD is true?",
            "optionA": "  Boys are more likely to be diagnosed with ADHD than girls ",
            "optionB": "  Most children \"outgrow\" symptoms of ADHD ",
            "optionC": "  About 20 percent of school-age children are diagnosed with ADHD ",
            "optionD": "  Racial minority status is a good predictor of being diagnosed with ADHD ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBoys are more likely to be diagnosed with ADHD than girls. Racial minority status is a good predictor of being diagnosed with ADHD. ",
            "keyString": "316465s39m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "According to Erikson, the goal of adolescence is to",
            "optionA": "  Independent identity ",
            "optionB": "  Explore who they are ",
            "optionC": "  Both a & b ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIdentity versus confusion is the fifth stage of ego according to psychologist Erik Erikson's theory of psychosocial development. This stage occurs during adolescence between the ages of approximately 12 and 18. During this stage, adolescents explore their independence and develop a sense of self. ",
            "keyString": "316476s39m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following weeds is effective in controlling water pollution caused by industrial effluents?",
            "optionA": "  Parthenium ",
            "optionB": "  Elephant grass ",
            "optionC": "  Water hycinth ",
            "optionD": "  Mogar grass ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tParthenium is effective in controlling water pollution caused by industrial effluents. ",
            "keyString": "316486s39m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Movement of cell against concentration gradient is called",
            "optionA": "  osmosis ",
            "optionB": "  active transport ",
            "optionC": "  diffusion ",
            "optionD": "  passive transport ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tActive transport, this is the only transport method that can move species against their concentration gradient (from low to high concentration). Facilitated diffusion only moves species down their concentration gradient from high to low concentration.",
            "keyString": "351838s39m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Photosynthesis generally takes place in which parts of the plant?",
            "optionA": "  Leaf and other chloroplast bearing parts ",
            "optionB": "  steam and leaf ",
            "optionC": "  Roots and chloroplast bearing parts ",
            "optionD": "  Bark and leaf ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn plants, the process of photosynthesis takes place in the mesophyll of the leaves, inside the chloroplasts. Chloroplasts contain disc-shaped structures called thylakoids, which contain the pigment chlorophyll. ",
            "keyString": "351871s39m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Most fish do not sink in water because of the presence of:\nI. swim bladder\nII. air bladder\nIII. air sacs\nIV. air in spongy bones",
            "optionA": "  I and II are correct ",
            "optionB": "  II and III are correct ",
            "optionC": "  III and IV are correct ",
            "optionD": "  I, II, III and IV are correct ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFishes have a swim bladder or air bladder which helps them to remain buoyant without sinking in water. They are present in the body cavity. ",
            "keyString": "351887s39m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Plants synthesis protein from",
            "optionA": "  starch ",
            "optionB": "  sugar ",
            "optionC": "  amino acids ",
            "optionD": "  fatty acids ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tWe know that, proteins are polymers of amino acids. So, plants are also used to synthesise protein from amino acids. Hence, plants synthesis protein from amino acids in the presence of ATP by specific synthetases. ",
            "keyString": "351906s39m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Plants absorb dissolved nitrates from soil and convert them into",
            "optionA": "  free nitrogen ",
            "optionB": "  urea ",
            "optionC": "  ammonia ",
            "optionD": "  proteins ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe plant cells absorb nitrates from the soil and convert them into ammonia which ultimately reduced to ammonium ions (NH4+). These ammonium ions are then combined with organic compounds to form amino acids such as glutamine i.e., free nitrogen. This process of conversion is known as nitrogen fixation. ",
            "keyString": "351919s39m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The plant body not differentiated into root, shoot and stem is termed as",
            "optionA": "  Rihazome ",
            "optionB": "  Thallus ",
            "optionC": "  Lysosome ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe plant body not differentiated into root, shoot and stem is termed as thallus. ",
            "keyString": "389517s39m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Capitulum is also given another name",
            "optionA": "  Branch ",
            "optionB": "  Head ",
            "optionC": "  Tail ",
            "optionD": "  Caktin ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCapitulum is also given another name called head. ",
            "keyString": "389551s39m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In all arthropods,the body is covered with a chittinous cuticle which is secreted by the ",
            "optionA": "  Endodermis ",
            "optionB": "  Mesophyll ",
            "optionC": "  Chitin ",
            "optionD": "  Epidermis ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn all arthropods,the body is covered with a chittinous cuticle which is secreted by the epidermis. ",
            "keyString": "389567s39m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Scientist who is known as father of botany.",
            "optionA": "  Aristotle ",
            "optionB": "  Darwin ",
            "optionC": "  Theophrastus ",
            "optionD": "  Linneus ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tWhen Aristotle fled Athens, Theophrastus took over as head of the Lyceum. Theophrastus presided over the Peripatetic school for thirty-six years, during which time the school flourished greatly. He is often considered the father of botany for his works on plants. ",
            "keyString": "389580s39m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which of the following chlorophyll does not exist?",
            "optionA": "  Algae ",
            "optionB": "  Fungi ",
            "optionC": "  Bryophytes ",
            "optionD": "  Pteridophytes ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAlgae, Bryophytes and Pteridophytes are true plants and contain chlorophyll . While fungi have characteristics that put this kingdom more close to animals, one of the features is that all fungi are heterotrophs and contain no chlorophyll. ",
            "keyString": "389594s39m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is a fresh water sponge?",
            "optionA": "  Sycon ",
            "optionB": "  Euspongia ",
            "optionC": "  Spongilla ",
            "optionD": "  Pleurobrachia ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSpongilla is a genus of fresh water sponges, found in lakes and slow streams. Sponges of the genus Spongilla attach themselves to rocks and logs and filter the water for various small aquatic organisms. It has monaxons spicules, which are like single pointed shaft. These spicules are present in large numbers. ",
            "keyString": "428842s39m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The kingdom Protista is primarily made up of organisms that are",
            "optionA": "  Eukaryotic and multicellular ",
            "optionB": "  Prokaryotic and multicellular ",
            "optionC": "  Prokaryotic and single-celled ",
            "optionD": "  Eukaryotic and single-celled ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAll single-celled eukaryotes are placed under Protista. This kingdom forms a link with others dealing with plants, animals and fungi. ",
            "keyString": "428919s39m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Marsupial Kangaroo is",
            "optionA": "  Viviparous ",
            "optionB": "  Oviparous ",
            "optionC": "  Ovoviviparous ",
            "optionD": "  A distinct category ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe kangaroo is a marsupial from the family Macropodidae. In common use the term is used to describe the largest species from this family, the red kangaroo, as well as the antilopine kangaroo, eastern grey kangaroo, and western grey kangaroo. ",
            "keyString": "428965s39m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following has a bilateral symmetry in its body organization?",
            "optionA": "  Asterias ",
            "optionB": "  Sea anemone ",
            "optionC": "  Nereis ",
            "optionD": "  Euchinus ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAsterias has bilateral symmetry only at larval stagebut fivefold symmetry (pentamerism, a special type of radial symmetry) as adults.Nereis do not possess any symmetry elements in their body organisation. ",
            "keyString": "428993s39m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Branch of biology which deals with the study of identification, nomenclature and classification of organisms is",
            "optionA": "  Exobiology ",
            "optionB": "  Ecology ",
            "optionC": "  Taxonomy ",
            "optionD": "  Toxicology ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTaxonomy is that branch of biology dealing with the identification and naming of organisms. ",
            "keyString": "429016s39m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Gametes are produced by the process of",
            "optionA": "  Mitosis ",
            "optionB": "  Meiosis ",
            "optionC": "  Both A & B ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMeiosis is a type of cell division that reduces the number of chromosomes in the parent cell by half and produces four gamete cells. This process is required to produce egg and sperm cells for sexual reproduction. ",
            "keyString": "476373s39m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In each pollen sacs a large number of pollens or microspores are produced by",
            "optionA": "  Mitosis ",
            "optionB": "  Meiosis ",
            "optionC": "  Regeneration ",
            "optionD": "  Fragmentation ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn a process called microsporogenesis, four haploid microspores are produced from each diploid sporogenous cell (microsporocyte, pollen mother cell or meiocyte), after meiotic division. After the formation of the four microspores, which are contained by callose walls, the development of the pollen grain walls begins. ",
            "keyString": "476415s39m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Synapsis occurs during",
            "optionA": "  Mitosis ",
            "optionB": "  Meiosis ",
            "optionC": "  Both A & B ",
            "optionD": "  None ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSynapsis (also called syndesis) is the pairing of two homologous chromosomes that occurs during meiosis. ",
            "keyString": "476435s39m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which cell division of phase of cell division maintains the chromosomes number constant from generation to generation?",
            "optionA": "  Mitosis ",
            "optionB": "  Meiosis ",
            "optionC": "  Prophase I ",
            "optionD": "  Zygotene ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn summary, meiosis is a form of cell division that results in half the normal number of chromosomes in sex cells, or gametes, thus maintaining the chromosome number of a species from generation to generation. ",
            "keyString": "476451s39m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Mitosis cannot take place bacteria because they lack ________",
            "optionA": "  Chromosomes ",
            "optionB": "  Nucleus ",
            "optionC": "  Centrosome ",
            "optionD": "  Mesosomes ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThere are many differences between prokaryotic and eukaryotic cell division. Bacteria have a single, circular DNA chromosome and no nucleus. Therefore, mitosis is not necessary in bacterial cell division. ",
            "keyString": "476467s39m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Salts and sugars works to preserve foods by creating a",
            "optionA": "  Hypertonic environment ",
            "optionB": "  Lower pH ",
            "optionC": "  Depletion of nutrients ",
            "optionD": "  Lower osmotic pressure ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSalts and sugars work to preserve foods by creating a hypertonic environment. ",
            "keyString": "529489s39m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Movement of cell against concentration gradient is called",
            "optionA": "  Active transport ",
            "optionB": "  Diffusion ",
            "optionC": "  Osmosis ",
            "optionD": "  Passive transport ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDuring active transport, substances move against the concentration gradient, from an area of low concentration to an area of high concentration. This process is \u201cactive\u201d because it requires the use of energy (usually in the form of ATP). It is the opposite of passive transport. ",
            "keyString": "529531s39m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one among the following Indian scientist proposed a theory for long distance transport of water in plants?",
            "optionA": "  J.",
            "optionB": " Bose ",
            "optionC": "  Birbal Sahni ",
            "optionD": "  P. Maheshwari ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tN.S. Parihar proposed a theory for long distance transport of water in plants. ",
            "keyString": "529552s39m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The movement of materials across the cell membrane with the help of biological energy provided by ATP is called",
            "optionA": "  Active Transport ",
            "optionB": "  Passive Transport ",
            "optionC": "  Endocytosis ",
            "optionD": "  Fractionation ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPrimary active transport moves ions across a membrane and creates a difference in charge across that membrane. The primary active transport system uses ATP to move a substance, such as an ion, into the cell, and often at the same time, a second substance is moved out of the cell. ",
            "keyString": "529570s39m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which process requires no energy from the cell?",
            "optionA": "  Osmosis ",
            "optionB": "  Diffusion ",
            "optionC": "  Both A & B ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPassive transport requires no energy from the cell. Examples include the diffusion of oxygen and carbon dioxide, osmosis of water, and facilitated diffusion. ",
            "keyString": "529586s39m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Pair of ribs found in man",
            "optionA": "  12 ",
            "optionB": "  10 ",
            "optionC": "  14 ",
            "optionD": "  11 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPair of ribs found in man is 12. ",
            "keyString": "573765s39m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Strongest bone of body is found in",
            "optionA": "  Thigh ",
            "optionB": "  Jaw ",
            "optionC": "  Shoulder ",
            "optionD": "  Neck ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe femur bone is the longest and strongest bone in the body. Located in the thigh, it spans the hip and knee joints and helps maintain upright posture by supporting the skeleton ",
            "keyString": "573805s39m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Smallest bone of human body is",
            "optionA": "  Nails ",
            "optionB": "  Fibula ",
            "optionC": "  Bone of nose ",
            "optionD": "  Stapes ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe 3 smallest bones in the human body--malleus, incus, and stapes--are located in the middle ear. At 3 x 5 mm in size, the stapes is the smallest bone in the human body. ",
            "keyString": "573821s39m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Study of bone is called",
            "optionA": "  Orology ",
            "optionB": "  Oesterology ",
            "optionC": "  Seromology ",
            "optionD": "  Geology ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA subdiscipline of anatomy, anthropology, and paleontology, osteology is a detailed study of the structure of bones, skeletal elements, teeth, microbone morphology, function, disease, pathology, the process of ossification (from cartilaginous molds), and the resistance and hardness of bones (biophysics). ",
            "keyString": "573833s39m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Tissue that connects muscle to bone",
            "optionA": "  Tendons ",
            "optionB": "  Joint capsule ",
            "optionC": "  Body fiber ",
            "optionD": "  Ligament ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA tendon is a fibrous connective tissue which attaches muscle to bone. Tendons may also attach muscles to structures such as the eyeball. ",
            "keyString": "573850s39m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Red snow causing alga is",
            "optionA": "  Chamydomonas nivalis ",
            "optionB": "  Chlamydomonas reinhardtii ",
            "optionC": "  Chlamydomonas debaryanum ",
            "optionD": "  Chalmydomonas media ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIt is the algae that give the snow its red tinge. This alga species, Chlamydomonas nivalis, exists in snow in the polar and glacial regions, and carries a red pigment to keep itself warm . ",
            "keyString": "645519s39m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Cork-screw shaped bacteria are known as",
            "optionA": "  Cocci ",
            "optionB": "  Bacilli ",
            "optionC": "  Spirilla ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t The bacteria which are twisted, helical or spiral in shape and called spirilla.",
            "keyString": "645555s39m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Ringworm is a disease caused by",
            "optionA": "  Fungi ",
            "optionB": "  Bacteria ",
            "optionC": "  Virus ",
            "optionD": "  Flies ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRingworm is a common infection of the skin and nails that is caused by fungus. The infection is called \u201cringworm\u201d because it can cause an itchy, red, circular rash.",
            "keyString": "645573s39m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Rod shaped bacteria are known as",
            "optionA": "  Cocci ",
            "optionB": "  Bacilli ",
            "optionC": "  Spirilla ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBacilli are rod-shaped bacteria. Bacilli all divide in one plane producing a bacillus, streptobacillus, or coccobacillus arrangement. ",
            "keyString": "645588s39m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Virus is not regarded as a cell, because",
            "optionA": "  It is anactive unless it finds a host to multiply ",
            "optionB": "  Most of the cellular activity is absent ",
            "optionC": "  The genetic material does not replicate on its own ",
            "optionD": "  All of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tViruses are not made out of cells, they can't keep themselves in a stable state, they don't grow, and they can't make their own energy. Even though they definitely replicate and adapt to their environment, viruses are more like androids than real living organisms. ",
            "keyString": "645603s39m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Study of parasitic organism is called",
            "optionA": "  Parazology ",
            "optionB": "  Parasitology ",
            "optionC": "  Both a and b ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMedical parasitology traditionally has included the study of three major groups of animals: parasitic protozoa, parasitic helminths (worms), and those arthropods that directly cause disease or act as vectors of various pathogens. ",
            "keyString": "713116s39m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The study of relation of animals and plants to their surroundings is called ________ ",
            "optionA": "  Ecology ",
            "optionB": "  Ethrology ",
            "optionC": "  Genealogy ",
            "optionD": "  Iconology ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tEcology term was coined by Ernst Heckel. It studies the interaction of living beings with their environment. ",
            "keyString": "713145s39m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Amarbel is an example of",
            "optionA": "  Parasite ",
            "optionB": "  Host ",
            "optionC": "  Autotroph ",
            "optionD": "  Saprotroph ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAmarbel is an example of the parasite. Cuscuta reflexa is the botanical name for the amarbel. It is also known as giant dodder. It grows in a creative manner over host plants and this species has the capability of producing numerous branches within a short period of time.",
            "keyString": "713159s39m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "When we consume the goat or sheep beef then we are",
            "optionA": "  Primary consumer ",
            "optionB": "  Secondary consumer ",
            "optionC": "  Tertiary consumer ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGoats, sheep and other herbivores are the primary consumers or heterotrophs. Any animal that eats primary consumers are the secondary consumers or heterotrophs. ",
            "keyString": "713171s39m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Branch of biology in which we study about relationship between living and their environment.",
            "optionA": "  Physiology ",
            "optionB": "  Genetics ",
            "optionC": "  Ecology ",
            "optionD": "  Geology ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tEcology is the branch of biology that explains the relationship between organisms and their environments.",
            "keyString": "713182s39m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Kelps are obtained from",
            "optionA": "  Algae ",
            "optionB": "  Marine algae ",
            "optionC": "  Fresh water algae ",
            "optionD": "  Lichens ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tKelps is obtained from marine brown algae. ",
            "keyString": "775798s39m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Blue green algae possess chlorophlyll along with a pigment known as",
            "optionA": "  Chlorophy ",
            "optionB": "  Phycobilin ",
            "optionC": "  Haemoglobin ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBlue-green Algae, now known as Cyanobacteria, are named for the blue-green pigment phycocyanin which along with chlorophyll a gives them a blue-green appearance. In the marine environment some Cyanobacteria trap and bind together sediment while they simultaneously precipitate carbonate. ",
            "keyString": "775832s39m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "A cell wall material present only in blue green algae and bacteria is ",
            "optionA": "  Cellulose ",
            "optionB": "  Glycogen ",
            "optionC": "  Muramic acid ",
            "optionD": "  Pectin ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThere are many similarities between cyanobacterium and bacterium. They both posses saparophytic mode of life. They both lack true cell organelles. They both posses nucleoid instead of true nucleus. In both bacteria and blue green algae, the cell wall is made up of muramic acid and diaminopimelic acid. Thus, the correct answer is 'Muramic acid.' ",
            "keyString": "775846s39m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Liver fluke is parasite in the liver of",
            "optionA": "  Sheep ",
            "optionB": "  Goat ",
            "optionC": "  Cattle ",
            "optionD": "  All of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA liver fluke is a parasitic worm. Infections in humans usually occur after eating contaminated raw or undercooked freshwater fish or watercress. After liver flukes have been ingested, they travel from your intestines to your bile ducts in your liver where they then live and grow. Hence D is the correct answer. ",
            "keyString": "775859s39m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Most bacteria reproduce by",
            "optionA": "  Budding ",
            "optionB": "  Binary fission ",
            "optionC": "  Fragmentation ",
            "optionD": "  Mitosis ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMost bacteria reproduce by binary fission. ",
            "keyString": "775870s39m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "When a foreign body inter into blood circulatory system the reaction is started by",
            "optionA": "  RBC ",
            "optionB": "  WBC ",
            "optionC": "  Platletes ",
            "optionD": "  Cytoplasm ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tWhen a foreign body inter into blood circulatory system the reaction is started by white blood cells. ",
            "keyString": "827293s39m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "How many chambers does a human heart have?",
            "optionA": "  2  ",
            "optionB": "  4  ",
            "optionC": "  6  ",
            "optionD": "  7  ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tHuman heart has 4 chambers. ",
            "keyString": "827325s39m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The muscle which separate the right side and left side of heart is known as",
            "optionA": "  Keratin  ",
            "optionB": "  Maxilla  ",
            "optionC": "  Septum  ",
            "optionD": "  Tubercules  ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA wall of muscle called the septum separates the left and right atria and the left and right ventricles. ",
            "keyString": "827338s39m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What is the pH value range of human blood?",
            "optionA": "  7.1-7.15  ",
            "optionB": "  7.45-7.55  ",
            "optionC": "  7.22-7.28  ",
            "optionD": "  7.35-7.45  ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBlood is normally slightly basic, with a normal pH range of about 7.35 to 7.45. Usually the body maintains the pH of blood close to 7.40. ",
            "keyString": "827351s39m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The main function of hemoglobin is",
            "optionA": "  Carries Oxygen  ",
            "optionB": "  Control Blood Pressure  ",
            "optionC": "  Produce hormones  ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above  ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAbout 70 percent of your body's iron is found in the red blood cells of your blood called hemoglobin and in muscle cells called myoglobin. Hemoglobin is essential for transferring oxygen in your blood from the lungs to the tissues.",
            "keyString": "827362s39m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which vitamin is necessary for blood clotting?",
            "optionA": "  Vitamin A  ",
            "optionB": "  Vitamin C  ",
            "optionC": "  Vitamin K  ",
            "optionD": "  Vitamin D  ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tVitamin K is necessary for blood clotting. ",
            "keyString": "903657s39m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Most of the enzymes are",
            "optionA": "  Fats  ",
            "optionB": "  Carbohydrates  ",
            "optionC": "  Proteins  ",
            "optionD": "  Minerals  ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tStructurally, the vast majority of enzymes are proteins. Also RNA molecules have catalytic activity (ribozymes). Coenzymes are small nonprotein molecules that are associated to some enzymes. ",
            "keyString": "903688s39m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The disease Rickets is caused by the deficiency of",
            "optionA": "  Vitamin A  ",
            "optionB": "  Vitamin B  ",
            "optionC": "  Vitamin C  ",
            "optionD": "  Vitamin D  ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe most common cause of rickets is a lack of vitamin D or calcium in a child's diet. ",
            "keyString": "903703s39m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which vitamin also act as coenzymes?",
            "optionA": "  K  ",
            "optionB": "  E  ",
            "optionC": "  B12  ",
            "optionD": "  None of the Above  ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tVitamin B12 act as coenzymes. ",
            "keyString": "903715s39m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Amoeba is ________ in nutrition",
            "optionA": "  Holozoic  ",
            "optionB": "  Holophytic  ",
            "optionC": "  Saprozoic  ",
            "optionD": "  Myxotrophic  ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAmoeba takes its nutrition through a process called phagocytosis where the entire organism swallows the food it plans on eating up. The mode through which an amoeba engulfs nutrition is known as holozoic nutrition.",
            "keyString": "903727s39m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The total number of pairs of Peripheral nerves in man are",
            "optionA": "  41 ",
            "optionB": "  42 ",
            "optionC": "  43 ",
            "optionD": "  44 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe total number of pairs of Peripheral nerves in man are 43. ",
            "keyString": "941039s39m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Medulla oblongata is a part of which of the following?",
            "optionA": "  Heart ",
            "optionB": "  Brain ",
            "optionC": "  Lungs ",
            "optionD": "  Stomach ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMedulla oblongata is a part of brain. ",
            "keyString": "941068s39m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Acetylcholine is",
            "optionA": "  Toxin ",
            "optionB": "  Vitamin ",
            "optionC": "  Enzyme ",
            "optionD": "  Chemical transmitter ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAcetylcholine is an organic chemical that functions in the brain and body of many types of animals as a neurotransmitter\u2014a chemical message released by nerve cells to send signals to other cells, such as neurons, muscle cells and gland cells.",
            "keyString": "941082s39m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The pair of spinal nerves in man are",
            "optionA": "  30 ",
            "optionB": "  31 ",
            "optionC": "  32 ",
            "optionD": "  33 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSpinal nerve, in vertebrates, any one of many paired peripheral nerves that arise from the spinal cord. In humans there are 31 pairs of spinal nerve. ",
            "keyString": "941094s39m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "How many bones are there in the human cranium?",
            "optionA": "  6 ",
            "optionB": "  8 ",
            "optionC": "  10 ",
            "optionD": "  12 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThere are 8 bones in the human cranium. ",
            "keyString": "941104s39m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "________ helps the eye to adjust the focal length of the lens.",
            "optionA": "  Lens ",
            "optionB": "  Ciliary body ",
            "optionC": "  Retina ",
            "optionD": "  Entire eye ball ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCiliary muscles help in changing the focal length of the eye lens. ",
            "keyString": "976540s39m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Eustachian Tube is located in which part of human body?",
            "optionA": "  Nose ",
            "optionB": "  Ear ",
            "optionC": "  Eyes ",
            "optionD": "  Throat ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe eustachian tube is a canal that connects the middle ear to the nasopharynx, which consists of the upper throat and the back of the nasal cavity. It controls the pressure within the middle ear, making it equal with the air pressure outside the body. ",
            "keyString": "976583s39m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Glomerulus and Bowman's capsule constitute",
            "optionA": "  Blood vessels ",
            "optionB": "  Malpighian body ",
            "optionC": "  Green gland ",
            "optionD": "  Malpighian tubule ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGlomerulus and Bowman's capsule constitute Malpighian tubule. ",
            "keyString": "976601s39m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The kidneys are stimulated to produce renin",
            "optionA": "  When the pH of the urine decreases ",
            "optionB": "  When the specific gravity of urine rises above 1.10 ",
            "optionC": "  When the peritubular capillaries are dilated ",
            "optionD": "  By a decrease in the blood pressure ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe secretion of renin is stimulated by the following three factors: When a fall in arterial blood pressure is detected by pressure sensitive receptors (baroreceptors) in the arterial vessels. When a decrease in sodium chloride (salt) is detected in the kidney by the macula densa in the juxtaglomerular apparatus. ",
            "keyString": "976616s39m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In mammals, an important role of excretion is played by ________ ",
            "optionA": "  Large intestine ",
            "optionB": "  Kidneys ",
            "optionC": "  Lungs ",
            "optionD": "  Liver ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe kidneys are bean-shaped organs that serve several excretory roles apart from the essential regulatory roles in mammals. They remove from the blood the nitrogenous wastes such as urea, as well as salts and excess water, and excrete them in the form of urine. In producing urine, the kidneys excrete nitrogenous wastes such as urea and ammonium. ",
            "keyString": "976630s39m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Antigen is present in",
            "optionA": "  RBC  ",
            "optionB": "  Plasma  ",
            "optionC": "  WBC  ",
            "optionD": "  Both A and B  ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAntigen is present in red blood cells. ",
            "keyString": "19704s40m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Agro forestry is",
            "optionA": "  Growing tree for forest ",
            "optionB": "  Growing tree after cutting crop ",
            "optionC": "  Growing of tree with cultivation of crop in the same field ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAgroforestry is the management and integration of trees, crops and/or livestock on the same plot of land and can be an integral component of productive agriculture. It may include existing native forests and forests established by landholders. ",
            "keyString": "19733s40m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Agrostology is the study of",
            "optionA": "  Seed of oil ",
            "optionB": "  Crop ",
            "optionC": "  Grass ",
            "optionD": "  Fruits ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAgrostology, the branch of botany concerned with the study of grasses, especially their classification. ",
            "keyString": "19747s40m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The primary goal of conservation biology is to",
            "optionA": "  Counter the loss of biodiversity ",
            "optionB": "  Estimate the total number of species that exist ",
            "optionC": "  Integrate human culture back into nature ",
            "optionD": "  Catalogue species ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAs a distinct scientific field, conservation biology is an integrated, multidisciplinary subject that developed in response to the challenge of preserving populations, species, ecosystems, and biological interactions. The main aim of conservation biology is to ensure the long-term preservation of biodiversity. ",
            "keyString": "19758s40m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Distribution of plant on the various part of earth",
            "optionA": "  Biogeography ",
            "optionB": "  Zoogeography ",
            "optionC": "  Phytogeography ",
            "optionD": "  Geopraphy ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPhytogeography or botanical geography is the branch of biogeography that is concerned with the geographic distribution of plant species and their influence on the earth's surface. ",
            "keyString": "19769s40m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Study of pulse and arterial blood pressure is called",
            "optionA": "  Sphygmology ",
            "optionB": "  Scerology ",
            "optionC": "  Sonography ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tStudy of pulse and arterial blood pressure is called Sphygmology. ",
            "keyString": "56034s40m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Longest artery found in the body of human is",
            "optionA": "  Venacava ",
            "optionB": "  Aorta ",
            "optionC": "  Capillaries ",
            "optionD": "  Ventricle ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tLongest artery found in the body of human is Aorta. ",
            "keyString": "56065s40m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Oxygen in our blood is transported by a protein named",
            "optionA": "  Keratin ",
            "optionB": "  Myoglobi ",
            "optionC": "  Collagen ",
            "optionD": "  Haemoglobin ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tHemoglobin, or Hb, is a protein molecule found in red blood cells (erythrocytes) made of four subunits: two alpha subunits and two beta subunits. ",
            "keyString": "56078s40m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who was the discoverer of human blood groups ?",
            "optionA": "  Landsteiner ",
            "optionB": "  Livine ",
            "optionC": "  Vinear ",
            "optionD": "  Leeuwenhoek ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tLandsteiner discovered human blood groups. ",
            "keyString": "56091s40m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Study of blood is called",
            "optionA": "  Hepatology ",
            "optionB": "  Hematalogy ",
            "optionC": "  Histology ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tHematology is the study of blood and blood disorders. ",
            "keyString": "56102s40m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The colour of Hemoglobin is",
            "optionA": "  Red  ",
            "optionB": "  Yellow  ",
            "optionC": "  White  ",
            "optionD": "  Colorless  ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe colour of Hemoglobin is red. ",
            "keyString": "94309s40m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The elastic vessels which transport blood to the heart is known as",
            "optionA": "  Arteries  ",
            "optionB": "  Veins  ",
            "optionC": "  Capillaries  ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above  ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe elastic vessels which transport blood to the heart is known as veins. ",
            "keyString": "94338s40m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The elastic vessels which transport blood from the heart is known as",
            "optionA": "  Arteries  ",
            "optionB": "  Sinusoids  ",
            "optionC": "  Capillaries  ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above  ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe elastic vessels which transport blood from the heart is known as arteries. ",
            "keyString": "94352s40m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "White blood cell act",
            "optionA": "  As a defence against infection  ",
            "optionB": "  As a source of energy  ",
            "optionC": "  For clotting blood  ",
            "optionD": "  As a medium for oxygen transport from lung to tissues  ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tWhite blood cell, also called leukocyte or white corpuscle, a cellular component of the blood that lacks hemoglobin, has a nucleus, is capable of motility, and defends the body against infection and disease by ingesting foreign materials and cellular debris, by destroying infectious agents and cancer cells. ",
            "keyString": "94364s40m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The top chambers of human heart are called",
            "optionA": "  Aorta  ",
            "optionB": "  Atrium  ",
            "optionC": "  Septum  ",
            "optionD": "  Ventricle  ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe top chambers of human heart are called atrium. ",
            "keyString": "94375s40m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The plants which live in soil, but depends on water for reproduction is known as",
            "optionA": "  Algae  ",
            "optionB": "  Pteridophytes  ",
            "optionC": "  Bryophytes  ",
            "optionD": "  Angiosperms  ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBryophytes include the various mosses and liverworts that are found commonly growing in moist shaded areas in the hills. Bryophytes are also called amphibians of the plant kingdom because these plants can live in soil but are dependent on water for sexual reproduction. ",
            "keyString": "222060s40m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The branch of botany which deals with identification, nomenclature and classification of an organism is known as",
            "optionA": "  Morphology  ",
            "optionB": "  Phytochemistry  ",
            "optionC": "  Taxonomy  ",
            "optionD": "  Paleobotany  ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe 'branch of botany' which deals with the classification 'nomenclature and identification' is taxonomy. ",
            "keyString": "222134s40m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who is known as the father of Taxonomy?",
            "optionA": "  Galen  ",
            "optionB": "  Darwin  ",
            "optionC": "  Lamarck  ",
            "optionD": "  Carolus Linnaeus  ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCarolus Linnaeus is known as the father of Taxonomy. ",
            "keyString": "222189s40m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Bat can fly in dark because they",
            "optionA": "  Have strong wings  ",
            "optionB": "  Have sharp eyes  ",
            "optionC": "  Produce ultrasonic wave  ",
            "optionD": "  Are nocturnal  ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBats can fly in dark because they produce ultrasonic waves. The bats possess very poor vision. It cannot see in dark. It produces ultrasonic waves which strike with the obstacles present on its way. The bat receives its echo and changes its path to protect itself from collision. ",
            "keyString": "222241s40m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The term \"taxon\" is first used by",
            "optionA": "  Francesco Cetti  ",
            "optionB": "  Adolf Meyer-Abich  ",
            "optionC": "  Nathan Cobb  ",
            "optionD": "  Gregor Mendel  ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe term taxon was first used in 1926 by Adolf Meyer-Abich for animal groups, as a backformation from the word Taxonomy. ",
            "keyString": "222291s40m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Sponges belong to the phylum",
            "optionA": "  Protozoa ",
            "optionB": "  Annelida ",
            "optionC": "  Porifera ",
            "optionD": "  Cnidaria ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe phylum of sponges (Porifera) contains sessile organisms, most of which live in marine habitats. The few species of freshwaters all belong to the class of demosponges (Demospongiae). ",
            "keyString": "302675s40m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Study of algae is called",
            "optionA": "  Phycology ",
            "optionB": "  Micro biology ",
            "optionC": "  Psychology ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPhycology, also called algology, the study of algae, a large heterogeneous group of chiefly aquatic plants ranging in size from microscopic forms to species as large as shrubs or trees. The discipline is of immediate interest to humans because of algae's importance in ecology. ",
            "keyString": "302706s40m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Study of butterfly is",
            "optionA": "  Ichthyology ",
            "optionB": "  Neonatology ",
            "optionC": "  Lapidopterology ",
            "optionD": "  Polynalogy ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tStudy of butterfly is Lapidopterology. ",
            "keyString": "302721s40m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following is the largest phylum in the animal kingdom?",
            "optionA": "  Annelida ",
            "optionB": "  Arthopoda ",
            "optionC": "  Chordata ",
            "optionD": "  Protozoa ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArthropod, (phylum Arthropoda), any member of the phylum Arthropoda, the largest phylum in the animal kingdom, which includes such familiar forms as lobsters, crabs, spiders, mites, insects, centipedes, and millipedes. ",
            "keyString": "302734s40m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "When a Cuttlefish is described as a Molluscs, it is at which level of classification?",
            "optionA": "  Class ",
            "optionB": "  Order ",
            "optionC": "  Family ",
            "optionD": "  Phylum ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCuttlefish is at mollusc level of classification. ",
            "keyString": "302746s40m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Metal present in Haemoglobin",
            "optionA": "  Copper ",
            "optionB": "  Iron ",
            "optionC": "  Mangnese ",
            "optionD": "  Zinc ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe heme group (a component of the hemoglobin protein) is a metal complex, with iron as the central metal atom, that can bind or release molecular oxygen. ",
            "keyString": "338460s40m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The right portion of human heart receives ________ blood.",
            "optionA": "  Pure ",
            "optionB": "  Impure ",
            "optionC": "  Mixed ",
            "optionD": "  None ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe right portion of human heart receives impure blood. ",
            "keyString": "338488s40m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Arteries supplying blood to the heart are called",
            "optionA": "  Carotid arteries ",
            "optionB": "  Hepatic arteries ",
            "optionC": "  Coronary arteries ",
            "optionD": "  Pulmonary arteries ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCoronary arteries supply blood to the heart muscle. Like all other tissues in the body, the heart muscle needs oxygen-rich blood to function. Also, oxygen-depleted blood must be carried away. The coronary arteries wrap around the outside of the heart. ",
            "keyString": "338501s40m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The plasma of the blood contains which among the following constituents?I. ProteinsII. SaltsIII. Hormones",
            "optionA": "  Only I and II ",
            "optionB": "  Only I and III ",
            "optionC": "  Only II and III ",
            "optionD": "  All I, II and III ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe plasma of the blood contains proteins, salts and hormones. ",
            "keyString": "338513s40m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Antibodies is produced in the plasma of blood by",
            "optionA": "  Monocytes ",
            "optionB": "  Lymphocytes ",
            "optionC": "  Eosinophils ",
            "optionD": "  Neutrophils ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAntibodies is produced in the plasma of blood by lymphocytes. ",
            "keyString": "338526s40m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who first studied the process of cell division in animals?",
            "optionA": "  Walther Fleming ",
            "optionB": "  Chase ",
            "optionC": "  Mendel ",
            "optionD": "  Drawin ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tWalther Fleming first studied the process of cell division in animals. ",
            "keyString": "376629s40m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which division provides a means of transmitting unchange information to the daughter cells?",
            "optionA": "  Mitosis ",
            "optionB": "  Meiosis ",
            "optionC": "  Binary fission ",
            "optionD": "  Fragmention ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMitosis allows for cells to produce identical copies of themselves, which means the genetic material is duplicated from parent to daughter cells. ",
            "keyString": "376660s40m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following does not occur during mitosis?",
            "optionA": "  Spindle formation ",
            "optionB": "  Condensation of the chromosomes ",
            "optionC": "  Breakdown of the nuclear membrane ",
            "optionD": "  Replication of the DNA ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tReplication of DNA does not occur in mitosis. Replication of DNA occurs during S phase, an entirely different phase of cell division. ",
            "keyString": "376673s40m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Meiosis II is similar to mitosis in that",
            "optionA": "  The daughter cells are diploid ",
            "optionB": "  Sister chromatids separate during anaphase ",
            "optionC": "  DNA replicates before the division ",
            "optionD": "  All of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMeiosis 2 is similar to mitosis because it separates the chromosomes to have sister chromatids in each cell. In both processes, you are separating the chromosome and dividing the cell to make 2 cells out of 1. ",
            "keyString": "376686s40m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In animal cells, cell division starts with the division of ",
            "optionA": "  Centromeres ",
            "optionB": "  Centrioles ",
            "optionC": "  Centrosomes ",
            "optionD": "  Ribosomes ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn animal cells, cell division starts with the division of centrioles. ",
            "keyString": "376696s40m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The site of RBC formation in human body is",
            "optionA": "  Heart ",
            "optionB": "  Spleen ",
            "optionC": "  Liver ",
            "optionD": "  Bone marrow ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRed blood cells are formed in the red bone marrow of bones. Stem cells in the red bone marrow called hemocytoblasts give rise to all of the formed elements in blood. ",
            "keyString": "411402s40m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Important component that helps in clotting of the blood is called ________ .",
            "optionA": "  Haemoglobin ",
            "optionB": "  Platelets ",
            "optionC": "  Serum ",
            "optionD": "  Plasma ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe main job of platelets, or thrombocytes, is blood clotting. Platelets are much smaller in size than the other blood cells. They group together to form clumps, or a plug, in the hole of a vessel to stop bleeding. ",
            "keyString": "411432s40m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The valve present between left auricle and left ventricle is",
            "optionA": "  Mitral ",
            "optionB": "  Tricuspid ",
            "optionC": "  Semilunar ",
            "optionD": "  Pulmonary ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe valve present between left auricle and left ventricle is mitral valve. ",
            "keyString": "411445s40m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Function of heart in human body is",
            "optionA": "  Work like pumping machines ",
            "optionB": "  To release energy ",
            "optionC": "  To increase temperature ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFunction of heart in human body is work like pumping machines. ",
            "keyString": "411457s40m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Function of haemoglobin is",
            "optionA": "  To transport oxygen ",
            "optionB": "  Destruction of bacteria ",
            "optionC": "  To check the loss of blood ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tHemoglobin is essential for transferring oxygen in your blood from the lungs to the tissues. Myoglobin, in muscle cells, accepts, stores, transports and releases oxygen. ",
            "keyString": "411468s40m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The study of structure and functions of cells is termed as ",
            "optionA": "  Genetics ",
            "optionB": "  Ecology ",
            "optionC": "  Embrylogy ",
            "optionD": "  Cell Biology ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCell biology is the study of cell structure and function, and it revolves around the concept that the cell is the fundamental unit of life. ",
            "keyString": "446916s40m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Where in the cell are chromosomes located?",
            "optionA": "  Mitochondria ",
            "optionB": "  DNA ",
            "optionC": "  RNA ",
            "optionD": "  Nucleus ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tChromosomes are thread-like structures located inside the nucleus of animal and plant cells. Each chromosome is made of protein and a single molecule of deoxyribonucleic acid (DNA). ",
            "keyString": "446944s40m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which are called the factory of protein synthesis?",
            "optionA": "  Ribosomes ",
            "optionB": "  Lysosmes ",
            "optionC": "  Golgi Bodies ",
            "optionD": "  Mitochondria ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRibosomes are known as the protein factory of the cell. As they synthesizes the proteins by gathering and assembling amino acids into protein chains. ",
            "keyString": "446958s40m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who is known as father of Biology?",
            "optionA": "  Aristotle ",
            "optionB": "  Drawin ",
            "optionC": "  Lamark ",
            "optionD": "  Purkenja ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDevelopment as a sequential knowledge of biology took place in the era of the famous Greek philosopher Aristotle (384- 322 B.C.). He revealed his thoughts about various aspects of the life of plants and animals. Therefore, Aristotle is called as the Father of Biology. ",
            "keyString": "446969s40m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who is known as father of Biology",
            "optionA": "  Aristotle ",
            "optionB": "  Darwin ",
            "optionC": "  Lamark ",
            "optionD": "  Linneus ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": "\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tNo explanation is given for this questionLet's Discuss on Board ",
            "keyString": "446980s40m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Saliva secreted from mouth digest",
            "optionA": "  Protein ",
            "optionB": "  Starch ",
            "optionC": "  Fat ",
            "optionD": "  Vitamin ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSaliva contains special enzymes that help digest the starches in your food. An enzyme called amylase breaks down starches (complex carbohydrates) into sugars, which your body can more easily absorb. Saliva also contains an enzyme called lingual lipase, which breaks down fats. ",
            "keyString": "481656s40m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which organ has finger like outgrowths which are called as Villi (Singular Villus)?",
            "optionA": "  Large Intestine ",
            "optionB": "  Bladder ",
            "optionC": "  Small Intestine ",
            "optionD": "  Stomach ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe internal walls of the small intestine are covered in finger-like tissue called villi. Each of these villi is covered in even smaller finger-like structures called microvilli. ",
            "keyString": "481685s40m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "A large number of bacteria in our digestive system, especially in the ________ and large intestine are important in completing digestive processes.",
            "optionA": "  Large intestine ",
            "optionB": "  Small intestine ",
            "optionC": "  Stomach ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA large number of bacteria in our digestive system, especially in the small intestine and large intestine are important in completing digestive processes. ",
            "keyString": "481699s40m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Pepsin is an enzyme that digests ________ .",
            "optionA": "  Proteins ",
            "optionB": "  Starch ",
            "optionC": "  Carbohydrate ",
            "optionD": "  Fats ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPepsin is a stomach enzyme that serves to digest proteins found in ingested food. Gastric chief cells secrete pepsin as an inactive zymogen called pepsinogen. Parietal cells within the stomach lining secrete hydrochloric acid that lowers the pH of the stomach. ",
            "keyString": "481710s40m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which among the following is used to treat indigestion?",
            "optionA": "  Antacid ",
            "optionB": "  Antiseptic ",
            "optionC": "  Analgesic ",
            "optionD": "  Antibiotic ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAntacid is used to treat indigestion. ",
            "keyString": "481721s40m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which organelle performs cellular respiration?",
            "optionA": "  Mitochondria ",
            "optionB": "  Cytolasm ",
            "optionC": "  Chloroplasts ",
            "optionD": "  All of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": "\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\t\tNo explanation is given for this questionLet's Discuss on Board ",
            "keyString": "517849s40m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The great contribution of Schwan was ",
            "optionA": "  what he saw ",
            "optionB": "  how interpreted what he saw ",
            "optionC": "  cell theory ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe great contribution of Schwan was cell theory. ",
            "keyString": "517877s40m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What organelle carries out photosynthesis?",
            "optionA": "  Chloroplasts ",
            "optionB": "  Ribosomes ",
            "optionC": "  Chromosomes ",
            "optionD": "  All of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tChloroplasts are organelles found in plant cells and eukaryotic algae that conduct photosynthesis. Chloroplasts absorb sunlight and use it in conjunction with water and carbon dioxide gas to produce food for the plant. ",
            "keyString": "517891s40m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which organelles are unique to plant cells?",
            "optionA": "  Central vacuole ",
            "optionB": "  Chlorophyll ",
            "optionC": "  Cell wall ",
            "optionD": "  All of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPlant cells have certain distinguishing features, including chloroplasts, cell walls, and intracellular vacuoles. Photosynthesis takes place in chloroplasts; cell walls allow plants to have strong, upright structures; and vacuoles help regulate how cells handle water and storage of other molecules. ",
            "keyString": "517902s40m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Membrane bound organelles are not found in the cells of",
            "optionA": "  Eukaryotes ",
            "optionB": "  Prokaryotes ",
            "optionC": "  Both A & B ",
            "optionD": "  Nokaryotes ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMembrane bound organelles are not found in the cells of prokaryotes whereas eukaryotes have nucleus and membrane bound organelles.",
            "keyString": "517912s40m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In cross section each centriole consists of a cylindrical array of how many microtubules?",
            "optionA": "  9 ",
            "optionB": "  8 ",
            "optionC": "  7 ",
            "optionD": "  6 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCentrioles are built from a cylindrical array of 9 microtubules, each of which has attached to it 2 partial microtubules. ",
            "keyString": "553661s40m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which phase's intiation is indicated by the appearance of the chromosomes as thin threads in the nucleus?",
            "optionA": "  Prophase ",
            "optionB": "  Metaphase ",
            "optionC": "  Telophase ",
            "optionD": "  Anaphase ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDuring prophase chromosomes appear as thin threads in the nucleus.",
            "keyString": "553696s40m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which of these mitosis is missing and the cell divided by binary fission?",
            "optionA": "  Prokaryotes ",
            "optionB": "  Eukaryotes ",
            "optionC": "  Arthropdes ",
            "optionD": "  All of these ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMitosis is missing and the cell is divided by binary fission in prokaryotes. ",
            "keyString": "553714s40m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which event occurs during interphase?",
            "optionA": "  Centrioles appear ",
            "optionB": "  Spindle fibers begin to form ",
            "optionC": "  The cell grows ",
            "optionD": "  Centromeres divide ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDuring interphase, the cell grows and the nuclear DNA is duplicated. ",
            "keyString": "553728s40m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The stage of mitosis at which chromatids separate as independent chromosomes is the ",
            "optionA": "  Prophase ",
            "optionB": "  Metaphase ",
            "optionC": "  Anaphase ",
            "optionD": "  Telophase ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe sister chromatids are pairs of identical copies of DNA joined at a point called the centromere. During anaphase, each pair of chromosomes is separated into two identical, independent chromosomes. The chromosomes are separated by a structure called the mitotic spindle. ",
            "keyString": "553742s40m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "A species inhabiting different geographical areas is known as",
            "optionA": "  Allopatric species ",
            "optionB": "  Sympatric species ",
            "optionC": "  Bio species ",
            "optionD": "  Sibling species ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA species inhabiting different geographical areas is known as allopatric species. This geographical isolation prevents mating between the two organism of same species. ",
            "keyString": "588566s40m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Lichen is a composite combination of two organisms.",
            "optionA": "  Fungi and Bryophyta ",
            "optionB": "  Fungi and Fern ",
            "optionC": "  Algae and Bryophyta ",
            "optionD": "  Algae and Fungi ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA lichen is a composite organism that emerges from algae or cyanobacteria living among the filaments (hyphae) of the fungi in a mutually beneficial symbiotic relationship. The fungi benefit from the carbohydrates produced by the algae or cyanobacteria via photosynthesis. ",
            "keyString": "588601s40m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Nitrogen Fixation is carried out primarily by",
            "optionA": "  Plants ",
            "optionB": "  Humans ",
            "optionC": "  Consumers ",
            "optionD": "  Bacteria ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNitrogen fixation is carried out naturally in soil by microorganisms termed diazotrophs that include bacteria such as Azotobacter and archaea. Some nitrogen-fixing bacteria have symbiotic relationships with plant groups, especially legumes. ",
            "keyString": "588618s40m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Organisms that depend only on raw plant products are said to be ",
            "optionA": "  Herbivorous ",
            "optionB": "  Vegetarian ",
            "optionC": "  Carnivorous ",
            "optionD": "  Omnivorous ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOrganisms that depend only on raw plant products are said to be herbivorous. ",
            "keyString": "588631s40m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The scientific study of how organisms interact with their environment is called",
            "optionA": "  Ecology  ",
            "optionB": "  Evolution  ",
            "optionC": "  Zoology  ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above  ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe scientific study of how organisms interact with their environment is called Ecology. ",
            "keyString": "588644s40m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In 1910, who proved the idea of W.S.Sutton that genes are located on chromosomes?",
            "optionA": "  T.H.Morgan ",
            "optionB": "  De Duve ",
            "optionC": "  Palade ",
            "optionD": "  Waldeyer ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn 1910, T.H.Morgan proved the idea of W.S.Sutton that genes are located on chromosomes. ",
            "keyString": "644475s40m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Different forms of genes are called",
            "optionA": "  Genomes ",
            "optionB": "  Allele ",
            "optionC": "  Genotypes ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAn allele is a variant form of a gene. Some genes have a variety of different forms, which are located at the same position, or genetic locus, on a chromosome.",
            "keyString": "644505s40m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Fruitfly has",
            "optionA": "  4 chromosomes ",
            "optionB": "  6 chromosomes ",
            "optionC": "  8 chromosomes ",
            "optionD": "  10 chromosomes ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFruitfly has 8 chromosomes. ",
            "keyString": "644519s40m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which nitrogenous base is not found in dna?",
            "optionA": "  Uracil ",
            "optionB": "  Thymine ",
            "optionC": "  Cytosine ",
            "optionD": "  Guanine ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tUracil is present in RNA and binds to adenine whereas thymine is present in DNA and binds to adenine. ",
            "keyString": "644531s40m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Gregor Johann Mendel worked on",
            "optionA": "  Edible pea ",
            "optionB": "  Wild pea ",
            "optionC": "  Garden pea ",
            "optionD": "  Pigeon pea ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGregor Johann Mendel worked on Garden pea. ",
            "keyString": "644542s40m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Prokaryotic cells lack",
            "optionA": "  Membrane bound by organelles ",
            "optionB": "  Nucleolus ",
            "optionC": "  Nuclear membrane ",
            "optionD": "  All the above ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA prokaryotic cell is a cell which doesn't have an organized cellular structure. The membrane-bounded nucleus is absent and the genetic material is scattered directly in the cytoplasm. The membrane-bounded organelles are absent in a prokaryotic cell e.g., a bacterial cell. ",
            "keyString": "680235s40m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The science related with the study of living is",
            "optionA": "  Physics ",
            "optionB": "  Chemistry ",
            "optionC": "  Biology ",
            "optionD": "  Mathematic ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBiology is the science of life. Its name is derived from the Greek words \"bios\" (life) and \"logos\" (study).",
            "keyString": "680264s40m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Ribosomes are produced in the ",
            "optionA": "  Nucleus ",
            "optionB": "  Vacuole ",
            "optionC": "  Endoplasmic Reticulum ",
            "optionD": "  Cytoplasm ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn bacterial cells, ribosomes are synthesized in the cytoplasm through the transcription of multiple ribosome gene operons. In eukaryotes, the process takes place both in the cell cytoplasm and in the nucleolus, which is a region within the cell nucleus. ",
            "keyString": "680278s40m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following organelle is known as the 'Power House' of the cell?",
            "optionA": "  Golgi Bodies ",
            "optionB": "  Ribosomes ",
            "optionC": "  Mitochondria ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMitochondria are tiny organelles inside cells that are involved in releasing energy from food. This process is known as cellular respiration. It is for this reason that mitochondria are often referred to as the powerhouses of the cell. ",
            "keyString": "680289s40m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Smallest cell in human body is",
            "optionA": "  Ovum ",
            "optionB": "  Nerve cell ",
            "optionC": "  Sperm ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe sperm is the smallest cell in human biology, but also one of the most complex. ",
            "keyString": "680300s40m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one among the following statements is correct?",
            "optionA": "  All arteries carry oxygenated blood ",
            "optionB": "  All veins carry oxygenated blood ",
            "optionC": "  Except the pulmonary artery, all other arteries carry oxygenated blood ",
            "optionD": "  Except the pulmonary vein, all other veins carry oxygenated blood ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tExcept the pulmonary artery, all other arteries carry oxygenated blood. ",
            "keyString": "714703s40m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "To complete one heart beat the time taken is",
            "optionA": "  1 sec ",
            "optionB": "  1 minute ",
            "optionC": "  1.5 sec ",
            "optionD": "  0.8 second ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTo complete one heart beat the time taken is 0.8 second. ",
            "keyString": "714729s40m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Pace maker is related with",
            "optionA": "  Kidney ",
            "optionB": "  Brain ",
            "optionC": "  Lung ",
            "optionD": "  Heart ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA pacemaker is a small device that's placed in the chest or abdomen to help control abnormal heart rhythms. This device uses electrical pulses to prompt the heart to beat at a normal rate. ",
            "keyString": "714742s40m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "PH of human blood is",
            "optionA": "  7.4 ",
            "optionB": "  6.2 ",
            "optionC": "  9 ",
            "optionD": "  7.5 - 8.0 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe pH scale, ranges from 0 (strongly acidic) to 14 (strongly basic or alkaline). A pH of 7.0, in the middle of this scale, is neutral. Blood is normally slightly basic, with a normal pH range of about 7.35 to 7.45.",
            "keyString": "714753s40m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "PH value of human blood is",
            "optionA": "  8.1 ",
            "optionB": "  8.4 ",
            "optionC": "  7.4 ",
            "optionD": "  9.2 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPH value of human blood is 7.4. ",
            "keyString": "714763s40m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The scientific study of livings is called",
            "optionA": "  Zoology ",
            "optionB": "  Anotomy ",
            "optionC": "  Ecology ",
            "optionD": "  Biology ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe organised study of a topic or knowledge is known as science. The different fields of study are classified as the branches of science. The study of the living organisms is known as biology. This includes the details and all the study facts with respect to the living things like plants, animals and microbes.",
            "keyString": "750286s40m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "They are present in the underground parts of the plants and stored food.",
            "optionA": "  Leucoplasts ",
            "optionB": "  Chromoplasts ",
            "optionC": "  Chloroplasts ",
            "optionD": "  Lysosomes ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tLeucoplasts are present in the underground parts of the plants and stored food. ",
            "keyString": "750315s40m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following groups is present in animal cells ?",
            "optionA": "  Mitochondria, Cell membrane, Cell wall, Cytoplasm ",
            "optionB": "  Chloroplasts, Cytoplasm, Vacuole, Nucleus ",
            "optionC": "  Nucleus, Cell membrane, Mitochondria, Cytoplasm ",
            "optionD": "  Vacuole, Cell membrane, Nucleus, Mitochondria ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNucleus, Cell membrane, Mitochondria and Cytoplasm is present in animal cells. ",
            "keyString": "750328s40m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What is the full form of DNA?",
            "optionA": "  Diribo nucleic acid ",
            "optionB": "  Di nucleic acid ",
            "optionC": "  Dual nitrogen acid ",
            "optionD": "  Deoxyribonucleic acid ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe full form of DNA is Deoxyribonucleic Acid. ",
            "keyString": "750342s40m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What is the full form of RNA?",
            "optionA": "  Ribonucleic Acid ",
            "optionB": "  Ribonitric Acid ",
            "optionC": "  Ribonutrient Acid ",
            "optionD": "  Reverse Nucleic Acid ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRibonucleic acid is the full form of RNA. ",
            "keyString": "750353s40m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Fusion of two gametes is called",
            "optionA": "  Fertilization ",
            "optionB": "  Development ",
            "optionC": "  Regeneration ",
            "optionD": "  Pollination ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFusion of two gametes is called fertilization. ",
            "keyString": "785688s40m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Flowers in which polllination takes place by insect their pollen grains are ________ ",
            "optionA": "  Smooth and dry ",
            "optionB": "  Rough and sticky ",
            "optionC": "  Rough and dry ",
            "optionD": "  Large in Size ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFlowers in which pollination takes place by insect their pollen grains are rough and sticky. ",
            "keyString": "785719s40m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Ornithology is the study of",
            "optionA": "  Mammal ",
            "optionB": "  Birds ",
            "optionC": "  Fishes ",
            "optionD": "  Bat ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOrnithology, a branch of zoology dealing with the study of birds. ",
            "keyString": "785734s40m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Pollination is best defined as",
            "optionA": "  Growth of pollen tube in ovule ",
            "optionB": "  Visiting flowers by insects ",
            "optionC": "  Germination of pollen grains ",
            "optionD": "  Transfer of pollen from anther to stigma ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPollination can be best defined as the transfer of pollen from the male anther of a flower to the female stigma to produce new offspring. ",
            "keyString": "785745s40m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Self pollination will lead to",
            "optionA": "  Inbreeding ",
            "optionB": "  Over breeding ",
            "optionC": "  Outbreeding ",
            "optionD": "  Rare breeding ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSelf pollination will lead to inbreeding. ",
            "keyString": "785756s40m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Jaundice in human beings is the result of",
            "optionA": "  Incomplete metabolism of biliverdin ",
            "optionB": "  Complete metabolism of biliverdin ",
            "optionC": "  Incomplete metabolism of bilirubin ",
            "optionD": "  Complete metabolism of bilirubin ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tJaundice is caused by a buildup of bilirubin, a waste material, in the blood. An inflamed liver or obstructed bile duct can lead to jaundice, as well as other underlying conditions. ",
            "keyString": "820590s40m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following can be a symptom of AIDS?",
            "optionA": "  Hair loss ",
            "optionB": "  Severe weight gain ",
            "optionC": "  Tiredness ",
            "optionD": "  All the above ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAs the virus continues to multiply and destroy your immune cells \u2014 the cells in your body that help fight off germs \u2014 you may develop mild infections or chronic signs and symptoms such as: Fever, Fatigue and Swollen lymph nodes. ",
            "keyString": "820618s40m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following is a hereditary disease?",
            "optionA": "  Cataract ",
            "optionB": "  Haemophilia ",
            "optionC": "  Pellagra ",
            "optionD": "  Osteoporosis ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tHaemophilia is a hereditary disease. ",
            "keyString": "820632s40m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Malaria is more common in",
            "optionA": "  Tropical areas ",
            "optionB": "  Southern areas ",
            "optionC": "  Eastern areas ",
            "optionD": "  All over the word ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMalaria occurs in more than 100 countries and territories. About half of the world's population is at risk. Large areas of Africa and South Asia and parts of Central and South America, the Caribbean, Southeast Asia, the Middle East, and Oceania are considered areas where malaria transmission occurs. ",
            "keyString": "820644s40m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Pathology is the branch of science which deal with the study of",
            "optionA": "  Nature of disease ",
            "optionB": "  Development of disease ",
            "optionC": "  Control of disease ",
            "optionD": "  All of them ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPathology is a branch of medical science that involves the study and diagnosis of disease through the examination of surgically removed organs, tissues (biopsy samples), bodily fluids, and in some cases the whole body (autopsy). ",
            "keyString": "820654s40m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Jellyfish belongs to which phylum?",
            "optionA": "  Porifera  ",
            "optionB": "  Cnidaria  ",
            "optionC": "  Nematoda  ",
            "optionD": "  Mollusca  ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThis jellyfish, a member of the phylum Cnidaria, can have tentacles up to 190 feet long (58 meters) and a bell almost 7 feet (2 meters) in diameter. ",
            "keyString": "856248s40m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which group of animals was the first to evolve to fly?",
            "optionA": "  Reptiles  ",
            "optionB": "  Mammals  ",
            "optionC": "  Insects  ",
            "optionD": "  Birds  ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tInsects were the first to evolve to fly. ",
            "keyString": "856279s40m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The skeleton secreting cells in poriferans are known as",
            "optionA": "  Scleroblasts  ",
            "optionB": "  Collenocytes  ",
            "optionC": "  Archaeocytes  ",
            "optionD": "  Pinacocytes  ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe spicules are secreted by specialized mesenchyme cells known as scleroblasts. Scleroblast secreting a calcareous spicule is called calcoblast while that producing a siliceous spicule is called silicoblast. ",
            "keyString": "856294s40m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one is the basic unit of classification?",
            "optionA": "  Division  ",
            "optionB": "  Family  ",
            "optionC": "  Class  ",
            "optionD": "  Species  ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBasic unit or smallest taxon of taxonomy/ classification is species. Species is a group of individuals that remain relatively constant in their characteristics; can be distinguished from other species and do not normally interbreed. ",
            "keyString": "856307s40m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following phylum is characterised by absence of true coelom?",
            "optionA": "  Nematoda  ",
            "optionB": "  Echinodermata  ",
            "optionC": "  Mollusca  ",
            "optionD": "  Annelida  ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNematodais characterised by absence of true coelom. ",
            "keyString": "856318s40m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Oxygen crosses a plasma membrane by",
            "optionA": "  Osmosis ",
            "optionB": "  Evaporation ",
            "optionC": "  Concatenation ",
            "optionD": "  Diffusion ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOxygen crosses a plasma membrane by diffusion. ",
            "keyString": "891133s40m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is true of osmosis?",
            "optionA": "  It is a type of diffusion ",
            "optionB": "  Movement is against water's concentration gradient ",
            "optionC": "  Requires energy ",
            "optionD": "  All of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAll of the above statements are true about osmosis. ",
            "keyString": "891159s40m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The water readily available to plants for absorption by roots is",
            "optionA": "  Gravitational water ",
            "optionB": "  Rain water ",
            "optionC": "  Hygroscopic water ",
            "optionD": "  Capillary water ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCapillary water is the water held by micropores of soil. This water is available for the plant because it gets trap in soil solution near the root of the plants. And some water is retained in mineral salts by chemical bonds but it does not increase the absorption capacity of roots. This is called chemically combined water. Thus the only water available for the plant is capillary water so the correct option is C. ",
            "keyString": "891172s40m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The process of evaporation occurs from",
            "optionA": "  Root ",
            "optionB": "  Stem ",
            "optionC": "  Leaf ",
            "optionD": "  Entire 'plants' surface ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe process of evaporation occurs from leaf. ",
            "keyString": "891184s40m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which process requires cellular energy?",
            "optionA": "  Passive transport ",
            "optionB": "  Active transport ",
            "optionC": "  Both A & B ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn cellular biology, active transport is the movement of molecules across a cell membrane from a region of lower concentration to a region of higher concentration\u2014against the concentration gradient. Active transport requires cellular energy to achieve this movement. ",
            "keyString": "891195s40m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Two species occupying same or overlapping area are",
            "optionA": "  Allopatric  ",
            "optionB": "  Parapatric  ",
            "optionC": "  Sympatric  ",
            "optionD": "  Peripatric  ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTwo species occupying same or overlapping geographical areas are called as sympatric species. The species occupying distinct geographical areas are called as allopatric species.",
            "keyString": "965134s40m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The ecosystem of a pond is referred as",
            "optionA": "  Lotic  ",
            "optionB": "  Lentic  ",
            "optionC": "  Xeric  ",
            "optionD": "  Benthic  ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA pond or lake ecosystem includes biotic (living) plants, animals and micro-organisms, as well as abiotic (nonliving) physical and chemical interactions. Pond and lake ecosystems are a prime example of lentic ecosystems. Lentic refers to stationary or relatively still water, from the Latin lentus, which means sluggish. ",
            "keyString": "965165s40m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following systems in man is affected by the bite of cobra ?",
            "optionA": "  Digestive ",
            "optionB": "  Nervous ",
            "optionC": "  Excretory ",
            "optionD": "  Circulatory ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe venom of elapids, including sea snakes, kraits, cobras, king cobra, mambas, and many Australian species, contains toxins which attack the nervous system, causing neurotoxicity. The person may present with strange disturbances to their vision, including blurriness. ",
            "keyString": "965179s40m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "________ is a thyroid hormone which controls the balance of calcium in the body.",
            "optionA": "  Calcitonin ",
            "optionB": "  Thyroxine ",
            "optionC": "  Calmodulin ",
            "optionD": "  All of these ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCalcitonin is a hormone that is produced in humans by the parafollicular cells (commonly known as C-cells) of the thyroid gland. Calcitonin is involved in helping to regulate levels of calcium and phosphate in the blood, opposing the action of parathyroid hormone. ",
            "keyString": "965190s40m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is known as master gland in man?",
            "optionA": "  Pancrease ",
            "optionB": "  Pituitary ",
            "optionC": "  Adrenal ",
            "optionD": "  Thyroid ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe pituitary gland, which hangs by a thin stalk from the hypothalamus, is called the master gland of the body because it regulates the activity of the endocrine glands. ",
            "keyString": "965201s40m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Pigmentation of skin is due to",
            "optionA": "  lymphocytes ",
            "optionB": "  monocytes ",
            "optionC": "  leucocytes ",
            "optionD": "  melanocytes ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA common cause of hyperpigmentation is an excess production of melanin. Melanin is a pigment that gives skin its color. It's produced by skin cells called melanocytes. ",
            "keyString": "999582s40m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Norepinephrine increases",
            "optionA": "  respiration ",
            "optionB": "  urine production ",
            "optionC": "  saliva production ",
            "optionD": "  blood pressure ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTogether with adrenaline, norepinephrine increases heart rate and blood pumping from the heart. It also increases blood pressure and helps break down fat and increase blood sugar levels to provide more energy to the body. ",
            "keyString": "999610s40m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Night blindness is cause by lack of which vitamin?",
            "optionA": "  Vitamin A ",
            "optionB": "  Vitamin B ",
            "optionC": "  Vitamin C ",
            "optionD": "  Vitamin D ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNight blindness is caused by lack of vitamin A. ",
            "keyString": "999623s40m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Monocot root differs from dicot root in having",
            "optionA": "  open vascular bundles ",
            "optionB": "  scattered vascular bundles ",
            "optionC": "  well developed pith ",
            "optionD": "  radially arranged vascular bundles ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn dicot root, well developed pith is absent. In monocot root, well developed pith is present. ",
            "keyString": "999634s40m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Radioactivity is a phenomenon of the spontaneous emission of",
            "optionA": "  protons (alpha particles) ",
            "optionB": "  electrons (beta particles) ",
            "optionC": "  gamma rays (short wave electromagnetic waves) ",
            "optionD": "  All of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRadioactivity is a phenomenon of the spontaneous emission of protons, electrons and gamma rays. ",
            "keyString": "999646s40m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In how many parts is the human brain divided?",
            "optionA": "  2 ",
            "optionB": "  3 ",
            "optionC": "  4 ",
            "optionD": "  5 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAll the parts of the brain work together, but each part has its own special properties. The brain can be divided into three basic units: the forebrain, the midbrain, and the hindbrain. ",
            "keyString": "35623s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Centre of reflex action",
            "optionA": "  Cerebrum ",
            "optionB": "  Cerebellum ",
            "optionC": "  Spinal cord ",
            "optionD": "  Nerve cell ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCentral nervous system (specifically cerebellum) is the control centre of a reflex action. The impulse for reflex action travels to and from spinal cord. ",
            "keyString": "35652s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Cerebro spinal fluid protects",
            "optionA": "  Heart ",
            "optionB": "  Brain ",
            "optionC": "  Liver ",
            "optionD": "  Kidney ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCerebro spinal fluid protects the brain tissue from injury when jolted or hit, by providing a fluid buffer that acts as a shock absorber from some forms of mechanical injury.",
            "keyString": "35666s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Cerebrum is related to",
            "optionA": "  Liver ",
            "optionB": "  Heart ",
            "optionC": "  Brain ",
            "optionD": "  Kidney ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe cerebrum is the largest part of the brain. It is responsible for memory, speech, the senses, and emotional response. It is divided into four sections called lobes: the frontal, temporal, parietal, and occipital.",
            "keyString": "35678s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which part of brain controls fine movement, maintains balance and equilibrium of the body and muscle tone in a human being ?",
            "optionA": "  Cerebrum ",
            "optionB": "  Thalamus ",
            "optionC": "  Cerebellum ",
            "optionD": "  Hypothalamus ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe cerebellum (back of brain) is located at the back of the head. Its function is to coordinate voluntary muscle movements and to maintain posture, balance, and equilibrium. ",
            "keyString": "35689s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "How many teeth in man comes out twice?",
            "optionA": "  4 ",
            "optionB": "  12 ",
            "optionC": "  20 ",
            "optionD": "  28 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t20 teeth in man comes out twice. ",
            "keyString": "71597s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Appetite is triggered by",
            "optionA": "  Stomach enzymes ",
            "optionB": "  Pancreatic enzymes ",
            "optionC": "  Physiological drive ",
            "optionD": "  Environmental cues such as the smell or taste of food ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAppetite is triggered by environmental cues such as the smell or taste of food. Appealing foods can stimulate appetite even when hunger is absent. ",
            "keyString": "71626s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Where are the taste receptors located?",
            "optionA": "  Epiglottis ",
            "optionB": "  Upper esophagus ",
            "optionC": "  Tip of the tongue ",
            "optionD": "  All of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe taste receptors are located in epiglottis, upper esophagus and tip of the tongue. ",
            "keyString": "71640s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Assertion (A): In human body liver has an important role in fat digestion.Reason (R) : Liver produces two important fat digesting enzymes.Codes",
            "optionA": "  Both A and R are individually true and R is the correct explanation of A ",
            "optionB": "  Both A and R are individually true, but R is not the correct explanation of A ",
            "optionC": "  A is true R is false ",
            "optionD": "  A is false but R is true ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAssertion is true but the reason is false. ",
            "keyString": "71651s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Fat is completely digested in the",
            "optionA": "  Small intestine ",
            "optionB": "  Mouth ",
            "optionC": "  Large intestine ",
            "optionD": "  Stomach ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe majority of fat digestion happens once it reaches the small intestine. This is also where the majority of nutrients are absorbed. Your pancreas produces enzymes that break down fats, carbohydrates, and proteins. Your liver produces bile that helps you digest fats and certain vitamins. ",
            "keyString": "71664s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following bacterium causes crown gall disease in plants?",
            "optionA": "  Bacillus thurigiensis ",
            "optionB": "  Agrobacterium tumefaciens ",
            "optionC": "  Pseudomonas fluorescens ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCrown gall is caused by the bacterial plant pathogen, Agrobacterium tumefaciens. Crown gall bacteria enter plant roots through wounds. ",
            "keyString": "106094s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Fossils of blue green algae were found in lime stones with the age almost as old as",
            "optionA": "  1.3 Billion years ",
            "optionB": "  2.3 Billion years ",
            "optionC": "  3.3 Billion years ",
            "optionD": "  4.3 Billion years ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFossils of blue green algae were found in lime stones with the age almost as old as 2.3 Billion years. ",
            "keyString": "106122s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "They have also proved extremely useful in our quest of knowledge of outer space.",
            "optionA": "  Bacteria ",
            "optionB": "  Fungi ",
            "optionC": "  Yeasts ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tYeasts have also proved extremely useful in our quest of knowledge of outer space. ",
            "keyString": "106135s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Chemicals like ________ may be added to different foods or fruits to prevent or retard the growth microorganisms.",
            "optionA": "  Potasium ",
            "optionB": "  Calcium ",
            "optionC": "  Potassium metabisulphite ",
            "optionD": "  Sulphur ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tChemicals like potassium metabisulphite may be added to different foods or fruits to prevent or retard the growth microorganisms. ",
            "keyString": "106147s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Eutrophication is the result of",
            "optionA": "  Bryophytes ",
            "optionB": "  Algae and aquatic plants ",
            "optionC": "  Gymnosperm ",
            "optionD": "  Pteridophytes ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tEutrophication is the result of algae and aquatic plants. ",
            "keyString": "106158s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is a work done by the placenta tissue in humans?",
            "optionA": "  Support the embryo ",
            "optionB": "  Removes waste matter from the embryo and provide nutrition to the embryo ",
            "optionC": "  Provide nutrition to the embryo ",
            "optionD": "  Remove waste matter from the embryo ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe placenta performs myriad functions to support fetal development, including facilitating blood flow, gas exchange, waste elimination, and serving as a protective barrier for the fetus against any infections the mother experiences during pregnancy. ",
            "keyString": "143457s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Corpus luteum is associated with",
            "optionA": "  Liver  ",
            "optionB": "  Brain  ",
            "optionC": "  Kidney  ",
            "optionD": "  Ovary  ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe corpus luteum secretes estrogens and progesterone. The latter hormone causes changes in the uterus that make it more suitable for implantation of the fertilized ovum and the nourishment of the embryo. If the egg is not fertilized, the corpus luteum becomes inactive after 10\u201314 days, and menstruation occurs. ",
            "keyString": "143488s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "A gland below the bladder and surrounding the urethra is",
            "optionA": "  Prostate ",
            "optionB": "  Seminal vesicle ",
            "optionC": "  Bartholin ",
            "optionD": "  Vas deferens ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tProstate gland is about the size of a walnut, and surrounds the neck of the bladder and urethra\u2014the tube that carries urine from the bladder. ",
            "keyString": "143503s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Snakes receive sound vibrations by",
            "optionA": "  Tympanum ",
            "optionB": "  Body ",
            "optionC": "  Internal ear ",
            "optionD": "  Earth ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSome snakes are able to perceive and react to substrate-borne vibrations. The vibrations are transmitted directly from skull to inner ear where it is sensed by brain. They also detect vibrations directly with receptors on their body surface. Thus, the correct answer is option B. ",
            "keyString": "143514s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "A man with colour blindness will see red as",
            "optionA": "  Green ",
            "optionB": "  Red ",
            "optionC": "  Orange ",
            "optionD": "  Yellow ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA person with color-blindness has trouble seeing red, green, blue, or mixtures of these colors. The most common type is red-green color-blindness, where red and green are seen as the same color. ",
            "keyString": "143526s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What type of tissue is Blood?",
            "optionA": "  Epithelial  ",
            "optionB": "  Cardiac  ",
            "optionC": "  Connective  ",
            "optionD": "  Muscular  ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBlood is connective tissue. ",
            "keyString": "179293s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The layer of cells between endodermis and vascular bundles is called",
            "optionA": "  Hypodermis  ",
            "optionB": "  Cortex  ",
            "optionC": "  Pith  ",
            "optionD": "  Pericycle  ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe layer of cells between endodermis and vascular bundles is called pericycle. ",
            "keyString": "179323s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Gymnosperms are characterized by the",
            "optionA": "  Absence of seeds ",
            "optionB": "  Presence of flowers ",
            "optionC": "  Presence of seeds in cones ",
            "optionD": "  Absence of vascular tissues ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGymnosperms are characterized by the absence of seeds. ",
            "keyString": "179337s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In a bisexual flower if androecium and gynoecium mature at different time the phenomenon is known as ________ ",
            "optionA": "  Dichogamy ",
            "optionB": "  Herpogamy ",
            "optionC": "  Haterogamy ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn bisexual flower the production of male and female flower androecium and gynoecium mature at different times to avoid self-fertilization. That is called dichogamy. ",
            "keyString": "179349s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The pollen grains of Pinus are carried to its female cone through the ",
            "optionA": "  Pollen tube ",
            "optionB": "  Wind ",
            "optionC": "  Insects ",
            "optionD": "  Animals ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe pollen grains of Pinus are carried to its female cone through the wind. ",
            "keyString": "179359s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The horizonatally growing hyphae of Rhizopus are called ",
            "optionA": "  Rhizoids ",
            "optionB": "  Stolons ",
            "optionC": "  Sporangiophores ",
            "optionD": "  Holdfast ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe horizonatally growing hyphae of Rhizopus are called stolons. ",
            "keyString": "213801s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following scientists first time saw bacteria through a microscope made by himself ?",
            "optionA": "  Antonie Van Leeuwenhoek ",
            "optionB": "  Louis Pasteur ",
            "optionC": "  Robert Hooke ",
            "optionD": "  Robert Virchow ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAntonie van Leeuwenhoek used single-lens microscopes, which he made, to make the first observations of bacteria and protozoa. ",
            "keyString": "213829s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The unicellular algae used to supply and regulate the oxygen in space programmes is",
            "optionA": "  Spyrogyra ",
            "optionB": "  Chlorella ",
            "optionC": "  Ulothrix ",
            "optionD": "  Odogonium ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIt is estimated that 2.3 kilograms of alga Chlorella pyrenoidosa produce enough oxygen to supply one man is space. ",
            "keyString": "213843s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Amoeba moves in water with the help of locomotory organs called",
            "optionA": "  Setae ",
            "optionB": "  Tube feet ",
            "optionC": "  Pseudopodia ",
            "optionD": "  Flame cell ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe locomotory organs of amoeba are called pseudopodia, which means 'fake feet'. ",
            "keyString": "213854s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Bacteria are (were) considered more as plants than animals because of the presence of",
            "optionA": "  Small nucleus ",
            "optionB": "  Plasma membrane ",
            "optionC": "  Cell wall ",
            "optionD": "  Spore formation ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBoth, plant cells and bacteria contain cell wall surrounding the cell membrane. Therefore, bacteria is said to be more like plant cell than animal cell. ",
            "keyString": "213864s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Function of pace maker is",
            "optionA": "  To regulate the formation of urine ",
            "optionB": "  To regulate the process of digestion ",
            "optionC": "  To initiate heart beat ",
            "optionD": "  To start the process of respiration ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA pacemaker is a small device that's placed in the chest or abdomen to help control abnormal heart rhythms. This device uses electrical pulses to prompt the heart to beat at a normal rate. ",
            "keyString": "249129s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which blood group is called universal donor?",
            "optionA": "  AB- ",
            "optionB": "  O- ",
            "optionC": "  AB+ ",
            "optionD": "  O+ ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tO- is called universal donor. ",
            "keyString": "249159s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Blood group which has both antibodies is ",
            "optionA": "  A ",
            "optionB": "  B ",
            "optionC": "  AB ",
            "optionD": "  O ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBlood group O is common, and individuals with this blood type will have both anti-A and anti-B in their serum.",
            "keyString": "249171s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which among the following carries impure blood to human heart?",
            "optionA": "  Aorta ",
            "optionB": "  Pulmonary vein ",
            "optionC": "  Pulmonary arteries ",
            "optionD": "  Vena Cava ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe pulmonary artery carries impure blood to the right and left lungs. The left half of the heart collects and pumps pure (oxygenated) blood from the lungs to all parts of the body. ",
            "keyString": "249182s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "A person with 'AB' blood group is sometimes called a universal recipient because of the",
            "optionA": "  Lack of antigen in his b lood ",
            "optionB": "  Lack of antibodies in his blood ",
            "optionC": "  Lack of both antigen and antibodies in his blood ",
            "optionD": "  Presence of antibodies in his blood ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA person with blood group AB is considered as the universal recipient as it contains both antigens such as A and B but no antibodies in plasma and thus, can accept all the blood type. ",
            "keyString": "249192s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following plays an important part in photosynthesis?",
            "optionA": "  Chloroplast ",
            "optionB": "  Centrosome ",
            "optionC": "  Tonoplast ",
            "optionD": "  Nematoblast ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Chloroplast contains the wonder green pigment chlorophyll which is able to trap solar energy and use it for synthesis of food. ",
            "keyString": "283857s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following plays an important role in photosynthesis?",
            "optionA": "  Chloroplast ",
            "optionB": "  Centrosome ",
            "optionC": "  Tonoplast ",
            "optionD": "  Nematoblast ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tChloroplast plays an important role in photosynthesis. ",
            "keyString": "283887s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following gas is necessary for the process of photosynthesis?",
            "optionA": "  O2 ",
            "optionB": "  CO ",
            "optionC": "  N2 ",
            "optionD": "  CO2 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTo perform photosynthesis, plants need three things: carbon dioxide, water, and sunlight. ",
            "keyString": "283900s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Photosynthesis fulfills which of the following requirements of the autotrophic organisms?I. CarbonII. WaterIII. Energy",
            "optionA": "  Only I ",
            "optionB": "  Only III ",
            "optionC": "  I and III ",
            "optionD": "  All I, II and III ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCarbon and energy requirements are fulfilled by photosynthesis. ",
            "keyString": "283912s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The gas released during the photosynthesis by the green plants is",
            "optionA": "  Oxygen ",
            "optionB": "  Nitrogen ",
            "optionC": "  Water vapour ",
            "optionD": "  Carbon dioxide ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe energy from light causes a chemical reaction that breaks down the molecules of carbon dioxide and water and reorganizes them to make the sugar (glucose) and oxygen gas. ",
            "keyString": "283925s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What base does guanine pair with?",
            "optionA": "  Adenine ",
            "optionB": "  Thymine ",
            "optionC": "  Uracil ",
            "optionD": "  Cytosine ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tWithin the DNA molecule, guanine bases located on one strand form chemical bonds with cytosine bases on the opposite strand. ",
            "keyString": "319068s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which describes the correct pairing of DNA bases?",
            "optionA": "  Guanine - cytosine ",
            "optionB": "  Adenine - cytosine ",
            "optionC": "  Guanine - thymine ",
            "optionD": "  Thymine - cytosine ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGuanine - cytosine describes the correct pairing of DNA bases. ",
            "keyString": "319096s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Sex determination of child is done by the chromosome of",
            "optionA": "  Father ",
            "optionB": "  Mother ",
            "optionC": "  Both father and mother ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe sex of the child depends on the male chromosome which is transferred to the offspring. This happens because males have a mismatched pair of chromosome XY which is responsible for deciding the sex of the child. ",
            "keyString": "319108s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The principle of dominance states that",
            "optionA": "  Some alleles are dominant, while others are recessive ",
            "optionB": "  All alleles are recessive ",
            "optionC": "  All alleles are dominant ",
            "optionD": "  Alleles are neither dominant nor recessive ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMendel's law of dominance states that in a heterozygote, one trait will conceal the presence of another trait for the same characteristic. Rather than both alleles contributing to a phenotype, the dominant allele will be expressed exclusively. ",
            "keyString": "319119s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which chemical is not found in DNA nucleotides?",
            "optionA": "  Thymine ",
            "optionB": "  Uracil ",
            "optionC": "  Adenine ",
            "optionD": "  All of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe only other difference in the nucleotides of DNA and RNA is that one of the four organic bases differs between the two polymers. The bases adenine, guanine, and cytosine are found in both DNA and RNA; thymine is found only in DNA, and uracil is found only in RNA. ",
            "keyString": "319129s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Nitrogenous bases in DNA and RNA?",
            "optionA": "  Adenine ",
            "optionB": "  Cytosine ",
            "optionC": "  Guanine ",
            "optionD": "  All the above ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe five-carbon sugar ring and the content of the nitrogenous base between DNA and RNA are slightly different from each other. Four different types of nitrogenous bases are found in DNA: adenine (A), thymine (T), cytosine (C), and guanine (G). In RNA, the thymine is replaced by uracil (U). ",
            "keyString": "354534s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "It is the study of hereditary characters transmitted from parents to offspring.",
            "optionA": "  Genetics ",
            "optionB": "  Evolution ",
            "optionC": "  Embryology ",
            "optionD": "  Molecular Biology ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGenetics is the study of how heritable traits are transmitted from parents to offspring. Humans have long observed that traits tend to be similar in families. ",
            "keyString": "354578s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The inherited traits of an organism are controlled by",
            "optionA": "  DNA ",
            "optionB": "  Enzymes ",
            "optionC": "  Nucleotides ",
            "optionD": "  RNA ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe inherited traits of an organism are controlled by DNA molecules. ",
            "keyString": "354593s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which chromosomes are identical to each other on the basis of their morphology, position of centromere and other characteristics?",
            "optionA": "  Autosome chromosomes ",
            "optionB": "  Sex chromosomes ",
            "optionC": "  Heterozygous chromosomes ",
            "optionD": "  Homologous chromosomes ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tHomologous chromosomes are identical to each other on the basis of their morphology, position of centromere and other characteristics. ",
            "keyString": "354604s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which is the correct pair of inherited chromosomes for the child to be a girl?",
            "optionA": "  X from father and Y from mother ",
            "optionB": "  Y from father and X from mother ",
            "optionC": "  Y from father and Y from mother ",
            "optionD": "  X from father and X from mother ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t X from father and X from mother is the correct pair of inherited chromosomes for the child to be a girl. ",
            "keyString": "354616s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In plants which one of the following tissues is dead ?",
            "optionA": "  Parenchyma ",
            "optionB": "  Collenchyma ",
            "optionC": "  Sclerenchyma ",
            "optionD": "  Phloem ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSclerenchyma cells are the permanent tissues present in the plants. They provide hardness and stiffness to the plant and are composed of dead cells. This tissue is present in stems around vascular bundles in the veins of leaves and in hard covering of seeds and nuts. ",
            "keyString": "389317s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "________ connects muscle to the bones.",
            "optionA": "  Cartilage ",
            "optionB": "  Areolar ",
            "optionC": "  Ligaments ",
            "optionD": "  Tendons ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA tendon is a fibrous connective tissue which attaches muscle to bone.",
            "keyString": "389348s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In animals like Annelids, Molluscs, organs have associated to form functional systems, each system concerned with a specific physiological function. This pattern is called ________ system level of organization.",
            "optionA": "  Organ ",
            "optionB": "  Open ",
            "optionC": "  Closed ",
            "optionD": "  Coelom ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn animals like Annelids, Molluscs, organs have associated to form functional systems, each system concerned with a specific physiological function. This pattern is called organ system level of organization. ",
            "keyString": "389364s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Xylem helps in transportation of which of the following?",
            "optionA": "  Food ",
            "optionB": "  Water ",
            "optionC": "  Nutrients ",
            "optionD": "  Both food and water ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tXylem is one of the two types of transport tissue in vascular plants, phloem being the other. The basic function of xylem is to transport water from roots to stems and leaves, but it also transports nutrients. ",
            "keyString": "389376s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Blood and lymph are types of",
            "optionA": "  Muscular tissue ",
            "optionB": "  Epithelial tissue ",
            "optionC": "  Connective tissue ",
            "optionD": "  Permanent tissue ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBlood and lymph are types of connective tissues. ",
            "keyString": "389388s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Haemoglobin is an important component of",
            "optionA": "  RBC ",
            "optionB": "  WBC ",
            "optionC": "  Platletes ",
            "optionD": "  Cytoplasm ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tHemoglobin is the most important component of red blood cells. It is composed of a protein called heme, which binds oxygen. In the lungs, oxygen is exchanged for carbon dioxide. ",
            "keyString": "427257s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Hemoglobin, the oxygen carrying substance in red blood cells, is a ",
            "optionA": "  Nuclei acid ",
            "optionB": "  Carbohydrates ",
            "optionC": "  Fats ",
            "optionD": "  Proteins ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tHemoglobin (Hgb) is an important protein in the red blood cells that carries oxygen from the lungs to all parts of our body. The main job of white blood cells, or leukocytes, is to fight infection. ",
            "keyString": "427288s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What carries blood back to the heart?",
            "optionA": "  Veins ",
            "optionB": "  Arteries ",
            "optionC": "  Both A & B ",
            "optionD": "  None ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe circulatory system is made up of blood vessels that carry blood away from and towards the heart. Arteries carry blood away from the heart and veins carry blood back to the heart. ",
            "keyString": "427302s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The smallest blood vessels which are one-cell thick, are called ________ ",
            "optionA": "  Vena cava ",
            "optionB": "  Arteries ",
            "optionC": "  Veins ",
            "optionD": "  Capillaries ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA capillary is a small blood vessel from 5 to 10 micrometres (\u03bcm) in diameter, and having a wall one endothelial cell thick. They are the smallest blood vessels in the body: they convey blood between the arterioles and venules. ",
            "keyString": "427313s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Name the blood cells in which nucleus is absent.",
            "optionA": "  Lymphocytes ",
            "optionB": "  Blood Platelets ",
            "optionC": "  Monocytes ",
            "optionD": "  Eosinophils ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBlood Platelets doesn't have a nucleus. ",
            "keyString": "427325s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Pellagra is caused due to the deficiency of",
            "optionA": "  Niacin ",
            "optionB": "  Riboflavin ",
            "optionC": "  Thiamine ",
            "optionD": "  Pyridoxine ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPellagra is caused by having too little niacin or tryptophan in the diet. It can also occur if the body fails to absorb these nutrients. Pellagra may also develop due to: Gastrointestinal diseases. ",
            "keyString": "462473s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Rickets is caused due to the deficiency of",
            "optionA": "  Carotene ",
            "optionB": "  Cyanocobalamine ",
            "optionC": "  Thiamine ",
            "optionD": "  Calciferol ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRickets is caused due to the deficiency of Calciferol. ",
            "keyString": "462504s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The element found in bone and teeth is",
            "optionA": "  Potassium and calcium ",
            "optionB": "  Calcium and Magnesium ",
            "optionC": "  Calcium and phosphorus ",
            "optionD": "  Phosphorus and sulpher ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe element found in bone and teeth is calcium and phosphorus. ",
            "keyString": "462517s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In Carbohydrates the ratio of hydrogen to oxygen is ",
            "optionA": "  2:1 ",
            "optionB": "  1:3 ",
            "optionC": "  2:4 ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA carbohydrate is a biomolecule consisting of carbon (C), hydrogen (H) and oxygen (O) atoms, usually with a hydrogen\u2013oxygen atom ratio of 2:1 (as in water) and thus with the empirical formula Cm(H2O)n (where m may be different from n). ",
            "keyString": "462529s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The story of vitamins dates back to",
            "optionA": "  15th century ",
            "optionB": "  16th century ",
            "optionC": "  17th century ",
            "optionD": "  18th century ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe story of vitamins dates back to 18th century. ",
            "keyString": "462540s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The main thinking part of the brain is",
            "optionA": "  Midbrain ",
            "optionB": "  Hypothalamus ",
            "optionC": "  Forebrain ",
            "optionD": "  Hindbrain ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe main thinking part of the brain is forebrain. ",
            "keyString": "500471s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What is the first thing that alcohol effects?",
            "optionA": "  Judgement ",
            "optionB": "  Speech ",
            "optionC": "  Vision ",
            "optionD": "  Balance ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAlcohol is absorbed into the lining of the stomach and then passes directly into the bloodstream and reaches your brain within minutes after consumption. A person's judgment is the first thing affected after drinking an alcoholic beverage. ",
            "keyString": "500500s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Largest part of human brain is",
            "optionA": "  Cerebellum ",
            "optionB": "  Cerebrum ",
            "optionC": "  Olfactory labbe ",
            "optionD": "  Mid brain ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe largest part of the brain, the cerebrum has two hemispheres (or halves). ",
            "keyString": "500515s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The functional connection between two neurons is a",
            "optionA": "  Axon ",
            "optionB": "  Synapse ",
            "optionC": "  Neuroglia ",
            "optionD": "  Dendrites ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSynapse, also called neuronal junction, the site of transmission of electric nerve impulses between two nerve cells (neurons) or between a neuron and a gland or muscle cell (effector). A synaptic connection between a neuron and a muscle cell is called a neuromuscular junction. ",
            "keyString": "500528s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The functional unit of the nervous system is the",
            "optionA": "  Nephrons ",
            "optionB": "  Axons ",
            "optionC": "  Neurons ",
            "optionD": "  All of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNeurons, or nerve cell, are the main structural and functional units of the nervous system. Every neuron consists of a body (soma) and a number of processes (neurites). ",
            "keyString": "500539s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Red colour of blood is due to presence of",
            "optionA": "  Plasma ",
            "optionB": "  Hemoglobin ",
            "optionC": "  RBC ",
            "optionD": "  WBC ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRed colour of blood is due to presence of Hemoglobin. ",
            "keyString": "537938s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Average life span of human R.B.C is",
            "optionA": "  100 days ",
            "optionB": "  90 days ",
            "optionC": "  120 days ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAverage life span of human R.B.C is 120 days. ",
            "keyString": "537966s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "With which of the following body organ is 'pace-maker' associated?",
            "optionA": "  Liver ",
            "optionB": "  Brain ",
            "optionC": "  Heart ",
            "optionD": "  Lungs ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPacemaker is associated with heart. Pacemaker are implanted on the body of the patient to give artificial heart beat when the normal body heart beat fails to function in the body of the patient. They are implanted temporarily to treat a slow heartbeat after a heart attack, surgery or overdose of medication. ",
            "keyString": "537979s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following blood group is called universal donor ?",
            "optionA": "  A+ ",
            "optionB": "  B+ ",
            "optionC": "  O- ",
            "optionD": "  AB+ ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tO- is called universal donor. ",
            "keyString": "537991s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What carries blood away from the heart?",
            "optionA": "  Arteries ",
            "optionB": "  Veins ",
            "optionC": "  Both A & B ",
            "optionD": "  None ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArteries carry blood away from the heart. Pulmonary arteries transport blood that has a low oxygen content from the right ventricle to the lungs. Systemic arteries transport oxygenated blood from the left ventricle to the body tissues. ",
            "keyString": "538001s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following parts of human brain is the regulating centre for swallowing and vomiting?",
            "optionA": "  Cerebellum ",
            "optionB": "  Cerebrum ",
            "optionC": "  Medulla oblongata ",
            "optionD": "  Cortex ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe medulla oblongata helps regulate breathing, heart and blood vessel function, digestion, sneezing and swallowing. This part of the brain is a center for respiration and circulation. Sensory and motor neurons (nerve cells) from the forebrain and midbrain travel through the medulla. ",
            "keyString": "572832s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Compared to land, the open oceans",
            "optionA": "  Are rich in silica and iron ",
            "optionB": "  Are nutrient-poor environments ",
            "optionC": "  Contain unlimited nitrogen ",
            "optionD": "  Are nutrient-rich environments ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCompared to land, the open oceans are nutrient-poor environments. ",
            "keyString": "572860s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Study of effect of radiation on plant and animal is",
            "optionA": "  Pathology ",
            "optionB": "  Etiology ",
            "optionC": "  Radiobiology ",
            "optionD": "  Cosmology ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tStudy of effect of radiation on plant and animal is Radiobiology. ",
            "keyString": "572874s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Melvin calvin got Noble Prize for his studies on",
            "optionA": "  Light reaction ",
            "optionB": "  Plant hormones ",
            "optionC": "  Carbon fixation ",
            "optionD": "  Photons ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Nobel Prize in Chemistry 1961 was awarded to Melvin Calvin \"for his research on the carbon dioxide assimilation in plants.\" ",
            "keyString": "572885s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Kyoto Protocol is associated with",
            "optionA": "  Species conservation ",
            "optionB": "  Climate change ",
            "optionC": "  Wetland Conservation ",
            "optionD": "  Medicinal plants ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Kyoto Protocol is an international agreement that aimed to manage and reduce carbon dioxide emissions and greenhouse gases. The Protocol was adopted at a conference in Kyoto, Japan, in 1997 and became international law on February 16, 2005. ",
            "keyString": "572896s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Out of proteins, lipids and carbohydrates present in a cell membrane, what is true?",
            "optionA": "  Lipids are maximum ",
            "optionB": "  Carbohydrates are minimum ",
            "optionC": "  Carbohydrates are maximum ",
            "optionD": "  All three are in equal proportion ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCarbohydrates are minimum in a cell membrane. ",
            "keyString": "647867s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Potato is a modified form (outgrowth) of:",
            "optionA": "  root ",
            "optionB": "  stem ",
            "optionC": "  fruit ",
            "optionD": "  leaf ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPotato is a modified form (outgrowth) of stem. ",
            "keyString": "647896s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Of the following taxonomic categories which is the most inclusive (i.e. is the highest in hierarchy)?",
            "optionA": "  Order ",
            "optionB": "  Subspecies ",
            "optionC": "  Class ",
            "optionD": "  Genus ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOf the following taxonomic categories class is the most inclusive (i.e. is the highest in hierarchy). ",
            "keyString": "647909s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Prothrombin which helps in clotting of blood is released by",
            "optionA": "  lymphocytes ",
            "optionB": "  erythrocytes ",
            "optionC": "  monocytes ",
            "optionD": "  blood platelets ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tProthrombin is a plasma protein which is converted into thrombin in the presence of thromboplastin released by platelets at the site of injury. The thrombin then converts protein fibrinogen into insoluble fibrin and thus aids in blood clotting. ",
            "keyString": "647920s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Myopia is connected with",
            "optionA": "  ears ",
            "optionB": "  eyes ",
            "optionC": "  lungs ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMyopia is connected with eyes. ",
            "keyString": "647931s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Pituitary gland is situated in",
            "optionA": "  Brain ",
            "optionB": "  Throat ",
            "optionC": "  Kidney ",
            "optionD": "  Pancrease ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe pituitary gland is a small gland that sits in the sella turcica, a bony hollow in the base of the skull, underneath the brain and behind the bridge of the nose. ",
            "keyString": "682224s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The gland that is present close to trachea",
            "optionA": "  Pancreas ",
            "optionB": "  Liver ",
            "optionC": "  Adrenal ",
            "optionD": "  Thyroid ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThyroid glands are located in the neck, in close approximation to the first part of the trachea. In humans, the thyroid gland has a \"butterfly\" shape, with two lateral lobes that are connected by a narrow section called the isthmus. ",
            "keyString": "682252s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Study of ductless gland is called",
            "optionA": "  Embrayology ",
            "optionB": "  Endocrinology ",
            "optionC": "  Ecology ",
            "optionD": "  Euthenics ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tStudy of ductless gland is called endocrinology. ",
            "keyString": "682264s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Cretinism is due to the disorder of the ______ gland.",
            "optionA": "  Thymus ",
            "optionB": "  Parathyroid ",
            "optionC": "  Thyroid ",
            "optionD": "  Adrenal ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCretinism is due to the disorder of the thyroid gland. ",
            "keyString": "682275s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Pancreas secretes",
            "optionA": "  Insulin  ",
            "optionB": "  Glucagon  ",
            "optionC": "  Pancreatic juice  ",
            "optionD": "  All of the above  ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPancreas secretes insulin, glucagon and pancreatic juice. ",
            "keyString": "682285s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "At the time of inspiration the diaphragm",
            "optionA": "  Expand ",
            "optionB": "  Contract ",
            "optionC": "  Relaxed ",
            "optionD": "  Does not under any change ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tWhen the lungs inhale, the diaphragm contracts and pulls downward. At the same time, the muscles between the ribs contract and pull upward. This increases the size of the thoracic cavity and decreases the pressure inside. As a result, air rushes in and fills the lungs. ",
            "keyString": "717350s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Rate of breathing in a minute by man is",
            "optionA": "  16-18 ",
            "optionB": "  20-25 ",
            "optionC": "  11-15 ",
            "optionD": "  70-72 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA normal breathing rate for an adult at rest is 8 to 16 breaths per minute. ",
            "keyString": "717381s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The C shape of the tracheal cartilage is important because",
            "optionA": "  Divide the nasal cavity ",
            "optionB": "  Allows for expansion or contraction of the trachea ",
            "optionC": "  Provide a surface for the sense of smell ",
            "optionD": "  All of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe cartilaginous rings are C-shaped to allow the trachea to collapse slightly at the opening so that food can pass down the esophagus. ",
            "keyString": "717395s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Alveoli is related to which of the following system of human body?",
            "optionA": "  Circulatory system ",
            "optionB": "  Excretory system ",
            "optionC": "  Reproductive system ",
            "optionD": "  Respiratory system ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAlveoli are tiny air sacs in your lungs that take up the oxygen you breathe in and keep your body going. Although they're microscopic, alveoli are the workhorses of your respiratory system. ",
            "keyString": "717406s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Complete oxidation of sucrose in presence of oxygen into CO2, water and energy is called",
            "optionA": "  Aerobic respiration ",
            "optionB": "  Anaerobic respiration ",
            "optionC": "  Glycolysis ",
            "optionD": "  Hydrolysis ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAerobic respiration takes place in the presence of oxygen and finally degrades glucose to carbon dioxide and water with release of energy in form of ATP. So, the correct answer is option A. ",
            "keyString": "717417s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Blood vessels bringing blood into Bowman's capsule is",
            "optionA": "  Afferent arteriole ",
            "optionB": "  Efferent arteriole ",
            "optionC": "  Renal vein ",
            "optionD": "  Renal portal vein ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe blood enters the Bowman's capsule into the glomerulus through the afferent arterioles of the renal circulation. This is the vessel that brings blood into the Bowman's capsule. The filtered blood leaves the glomerulus through the efferent arteriole. ",
            "keyString": "753083s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which organ filters blood in human body?",
            "optionA": "  Lungs ",
            "optionB": "  Heart ",
            "optionC": "  Liver ",
            "optionD": "  Kidneys ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tKidneys filter waste and toxins out of the blood. They are responsible for taking waste out of other fluids in the body as well. ",
            "keyString": "753114s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The renal corpuscle is made up of",
            "optionA": "  Bowman's capsule ",
            "optionB": "  Glomerulus ",
            "optionC": "  Both A & B ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe renal corpuscle is made up of Bowman's capsule and Glomerulus. ",
            "keyString": "753129s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Main nitrogenous product formed in man is",
            "optionA": "  Urea ",
            "optionB": "  Ammonia ",
            "optionC": "  Uric acid ",
            "optionD": "  Ammonium nitrate ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe principle nitrogenous excretory compound in humans is urea. Urea is produced in a series of reactions (urea cycle) which take place in the mitochondrial matrix and cytosol of liver cells. ",
            "keyString": "753143s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Loop of henle is related with",
            "optionA": "  Excretory system ",
            "optionB": "  Reproductive system ",
            "optionC": "  Urinogenital system ",
            "optionD": "  Nervous system ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tLoop of henle is related with excretory system. ",
            "keyString": "753155s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What is the study of cells called?",
            "optionA": "  Cellogysm ",
            "optionB": "  Cytology ",
            "optionC": "  Cell Biology ",
            "optionD": "  Both B & C ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe study of cells is called cytology or cellogysm. ",
            "keyString": "788711s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Closely stacked flattened sacs (plants only) is called",
            "optionA": "  Vacuoles ",
            "optionB": "  Lysosomes ",
            "optionC": "  Golgi apparatus ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tClosely stacked flattened sacs (plants only) is called Golgi apparatus. ",
            "keyString": "788741s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one among the following cell organelles is semi-permeable ?",
            "optionA": "  Cell membrane ",
            "optionB": "  Plasma membrane ",
            "optionC": "  Cell wall ",
            "optionD": "  Nucleus ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAmong the given example only nucleus is a cell organelle and rest are not cell organelle therefore nucleus is the correct answer. ",
            "keyString": "788754s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Any foreign object that gains entry into the cell is immediately engulfed by the ________ and is completely broken into simple digestible pieces.",
            "optionA": "  R.",
            "optionB": "Cs ",
            "optionC": "  Platelets ",
            "optionD": "  Haemoglobin ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAny foreign object that gains entry into the cell is immediately engulfed by the lysosomes and is completely broken into simple digestible pieces. ",
            "keyString": "788765s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The function of nucleolus is the synthesis of",
            "optionA": "  DNA ",
            "optionB": "  M-RNA ",
            "optionC": "  R-RNA ",
            "optionD": "  T-RNA ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe function of nucleolus is the synthesis of R-RNA. ",
            "keyString": "788775s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is necessary for digestion of food?",
            "optionA": "  Air ",
            "optionB": "  Water ",
            "optionC": "  Enzyme ",
            "optionD": "  Mineral ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tEnzyme is necessary for digestion of food. ",
            "keyString": "844689s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Where are Enzymes found?",
            "optionA": "  Food ",
            "optionB": "  Human body ",
            "optionC": "  Medicines ",
            "optionD": "  None ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tEnzymes are produced naturally in the body. For example, enzymes are required for proper digestive system function. Digestive enzymes are mostly produced in the pancreas, stomach, and small intestine. ",
            "keyString": "844718s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Enzymes are important because they",
            "optionA": "  Maintain cell shape ",
            "optionB": "  Transfer genetic information ",
            "optionC": "  Contain water ",
            "optionD": "  Speeds up chemical reactions ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tEnzymes create chemical reactions in the body. They actually speed up the rate of a chemical reaction to help support life. The enzymes in your body help to perform very important tasks. ",
            "keyString": "844731s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one is the largest gland of human body?",
            "optionA": "  Liver  ",
            "optionB": "  Thyroid  ",
            "optionC": "  Pituitary  ",
            "optionD": "  Intestine  ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tLiver is the largest gland in body. It stores its waste bile in Gall Bladder. ",
            "keyString": "844742s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Colon and rectum is a part of",
            "optionA": "  Small Intestine  ",
            "optionB": "  Large Intestine  ",
            "optionC": "  Stomach  ",
            "optionD": "  Ureter  ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe colon and rectum are part of large intestine, which is long, hollow tubes that run from stomach to anal opening. ",
            "keyString": "844752s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Placenta is the structure formed",
            "optionA": "  by the union of foetal and uterine tissue ",
            "optionB": "  by foetus only ",
            "optionC": "  by fusion of germ layers ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPlacenta is the structure formed by the union of foetal and uterine tissue. ",
            "keyString": "880615s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Plants hormone that induces cell division is",
            "optionA": "  auxins ",
            "optionB": "  gibberellins ",
            "optionC": "  kinins ",
            "optionD": "  domins ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPlants hormone that induces cell division is gibberellins. ",
            "keyString": "880645s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Neurospora is used as genetic material because",
            "optionA": "  it has short life cycle of 10 days ",
            "optionB": "  the product of single meiosis can be easily analysed ",
            "optionC": "  meiotic products are linearly arranged in the form of ordered tetrads ",
            "optionD": "  is a diploid fungus ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNeurospora is used as genetic material because it has short life cycle of 10 days. ",
            "keyString": "880658s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Phloem is a tissue found in",
            "optionA": "  reproductive organs of animals ",
            "optionB": "  plants ",
            "optionC": "  insects ",
            "optionD": "  mammals ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPhloem, also called bast, tissues in plants that conduct foods made in the leaves to all other parts of the plant. Phloem is composed of various specialized cells called sieve tubes, companion cells, phloem fibres, and phloem parenchyma cells. ",
            "keyString": "880670s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "N2 content is kept constant in the biosphere due to",
            "optionA": "  N2 fixation ",
            "optionB": "  industrial pollution ",
            "optionC": "  nitrogen cycle ",
            "optionD": "  absorption of N2 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tN2 content is kept constant in the biosphere due to nitrogen cycle. ",
            "keyString": "880681s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Lichens are the best indicator of",
            "optionA": "  Air pollution  ",
            "optionB": "  Water pollution  ",
            "optionC": "  Soil pollution  ",
            "optionD": "  Noise pollution  ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tLichens are sensitive to atmospheric pollution such as nitrogen (N) because they receive all their nutrients and water from wet and dry atmospheric deposition (fall out). ",
            "keyString": "917547s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following processes takes place in lakes during eutrophication?",
            "optionA": "  Rapid destruction of algal growth ",
            "optionB": "  Excessive availability of dissolved oxygen ",
            "optionC": "  Loss of dissolved nutrients from water ",
            "optionD": "  Excessive entry of nutrient into water ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn lakes, when there's a excess entry ofnutrients in water, the growth of plant life takes place. This phenomenon is called Eutrophication. Thus, the correct answer is (d). ",
            "keyString": "917575s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which organelles supply energy to the cell?",
            "optionA": "  Mitochondria ",
            "optionB": "  Cytoplasm ",
            "optionC": "  Ribosomes ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMitochondria are membrane-bound cell organelles (mitochondrion, singular) that generate most of the chemical energy needed to power the cell's biochemical reactions. Chemical energy produced by the mitochondria is stored in a small molecule called adenosine triphosphate (ATP). ",
            "keyString": "917589s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who of the following is known as the Father of Biology?",
            "optionA": "  Darwin ",
            "optionB": "  Lamarck ",
            "optionC": "  Aristotle ",
            "optionD": "  Theophrastus ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDevelopment as a sequential knowledge of biology took place in the era of the famous Greek philosopher Aristotle (384-322 B.C.). He revealed his thoughts about various aspects of the life of plants and animals. Therefore, Aristotle is called as the Father of Biology. ",
            "keyString": "917602s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which is not a function of the cell membrane?",
            "optionA": "  Helps substances pass from the cytoplasm into the nucleus ",
            "optionB": "  Keeps materials within the cell separated from the environment outside the cell ",
            "optionC": "  Helps control the movement of materials into and out of the cell ",
            "optionD": "  Allows the cell to change shape under pressure ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCell membrane does not help substances pass from the cytoplasm into the nucleus. ",
            "keyString": "917613s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The terminal part of the carpel in a flower, which may be sticky is ________ ",
            "optionA": "  Ovary ",
            "optionB": "  Style ",
            "optionC": "  Stigma ",
            "optionD": "  Anther ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe stigma is the top and sticky portion of a carpel or pistil that traps pollens. ",
            "keyString": "955773s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The study of flower is known as",
            "optionA": "  Anthology  ",
            "optionB": "  Physiology  ",
            "optionC": "  Agrostology  ",
            "optionD": "  Phycology  ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAnthology is the branch of biology that deals with the study of flowers. ",
            "keyString": "955804s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The innermost part of a flower is known as",
            "optionA": "  Pistils  ",
            "optionB": "  Sepals  ",
            "optionC": "  Stamens  ",
            "optionD": "  Petals  ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe innermost part of a flower is known as Stamens. ",
            "keyString": "955819s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Ophthalmology is the branch of science in which we study about",
            "optionA": "  Nose ",
            "optionB": "  Tongue ",
            "optionC": "  Eye ",
            "optionD": "  Ear ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOphthalmology is the branch of medicine which deals with the diseases of the eye and their treatment. ",
            "keyString": "955832s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "At which stage in its life cycle does the silkworm yield the fiber of commercial use?",
            "optionA": "  Larva ",
            "optionB": "  Egg ",
            "optionC": "  Pupa ",
            "optionD": "  Imago ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSilkworm yield the fiber of commercial use at pupa stage. ",
            "keyString": "955844s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Octopus belongs to the phylum",
            "optionA": "  Mollusca ",
            "optionB": "  Cnidaria ",
            "optionC": "  Echinodermata ",
            "optionD": "  Chordata ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOctopus belongs to the phylum Mollusca. ",
            "keyString": "991560s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Octopus is",
            "optionA": "  An arthropod ",
            "optionB": "  An echionoderm ",
            "optionC": "  A hemichordate ",
            "optionD": "  A mollusc ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOctopus is a mollusc. ",
            "keyString": "991592s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In coelenterates mesoderm gives rise to",
            "optionA": "  Digestive System ",
            "optionB": "  Neverous System ",
            "optionC": "  Circulatory System ",
            "optionD": "  Lining of the gut ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn coelentrates mesoderm gives rise to circulatory system. ",
            "keyString": "991607s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "It is the study of internal organs of organisms.",
            "optionA": "  Anatomy ",
            "optionB": "  Physiology ",
            "optionC": "  Morphology ",
            "optionD": "  Cell Biology ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe best known aspect of morphology, usually called anatomy, is the study of gross structure, or form, of organs and organisms. ",
            "keyString": "991619s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Their cells have a very well defined nucleus ,in which nuclear material (chromosomes or DNA) is enclosed in double nuclear membrane.",
            "optionA": "  Prokaryotes ",
            "optionB": "  Bacterial ",
            "optionC": "  Viral ",
            "optionD": "  Eukaryotes ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tEukaryotes cells have a very well defined nucleus, in which nuclear material (chromosomes or DNA) is enclosed in double nuclear membrane. ",
            "keyString": "991630s41m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The subcellular organelle not bound by a single membrane is",
            "optionA": "  Golgi apparatus  ",
            "optionB": "  Endoplasmic Reticulum  ",
            "optionC": "  Mitochondria  ",
            "optionD": "  Lysosomes  ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe subcellular organelle not bound by a single membrane is Lysosomes. ",
            "keyString": "26215s42m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one is not found in the composition of plasma membrane?",
            "optionA": "  Minerals  ",
            "optionB": "  Phospholipids  ",
            "optionC": "  Carbohydrates  ",
            "optionD": "  Proteins  ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMinerals is not found in the composition of plasma membrane. ",
            "keyString": "26249s42m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which organelle in the cell, other than nucleus contains DNA?",
            "optionA": "  Golgi body  ",
            "optionB": "  Mitochondria  ",
            "optionC": "  Lysosome  ",
            "optionD": "  Centriole  ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMitochondria contain DNA other than nucleus. ",
            "keyString": "26265s42m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The single membrane surrounding vacuoles in plant cells is known as",
            "optionA": "  Apoplast  ",
            "optionB": "  Symplast  ",
            "optionC": "  Tonoplast  ",
            "optionD": "  Chloroplast  ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAlso called the vacuolar membrane, the tonoplast is the cytoplasmic membrane surrounding a vacuole, separating the vacuolar contents from the cell's cytoplasm. ",
            "keyString": "26278s42m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Cellular respiration occurs in",
            "optionA": "  Centromere  ",
            "optionB": "  Nucleus  ",
            "optionC": "  Mitochondria  ",
            "optionD": "  Golgi complex  ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCellular respiration occurs in the double-membrane organelle called the mitochondrion. ",
            "keyString": "26291s42m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Gaseous exchange takes place in leaves through tiny pores for the purpose of photosynthesis. What are these pores?",
            "optionA": "  Chloroplast ",
            "optionB": "  Stomata ",
            "optionC": "  Chlorophyl ",
            "optionD": "  Vacuole ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tStomata are tiny, microscopic pores that critical for photosynthesis. ",
            "keyString": "61645s42m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The photosynthesis occurs in the",
            "optionA": "  Day ",
            "optionB": "  Night ",
            "optionC": "  Day and Night ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe photosynthesis occurs in the day. ",
            "keyString": "61680s42m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The oxygen released during photosynthesis process comes from",
            "optionA": "  H2O  ",
            "optionB": "  CO2 ",
            "optionC": "  NO2 ",
            "optionD": "  Glucose  ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe oxygen released during photosynthesis process comes from glucose. ",
            "keyString": "61696s42m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In plants, photosynthesis mainly occurs in the",
            "optionA": "  Leaves  ",
            "optionB": "  Flowers  ",
            "optionC": "  Root  ",
            "optionD": "  Bark  ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn plants, the process of photosynthesis takes place in the mesophyll of the leaves, inside the chloroplasts. Chloroplasts contain disc-shaped structures called thylakoids, which contain the pigment chlorophyll. ",
            "keyString": "61710s42m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one is important in photosynthesis to allows plants to absorb energy from light?",
            "optionA": "  Xanthophyll  ",
            "optionB": "  Carotene  ",
            "optionC": "  Chlorophyll  ",
            "optionD": "  Phaeophytin  ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPhotosynthetic cells contain special pigments that absorb light energy. Different pigments respond to different wavelengths of visible light. Chlorophyll, the primary pigment used in photosynthesis, reflects green light and absorbs red and blue light most strongly. ",
            "keyString": "61723s42m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Tissue in which cells have lost the capacity of cell division is",
            "optionA": "  Mesristmatic tissue ",
            "optionB": "  Permanent tissue ",
            "optionC": "  Both a and b ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn permanent tissue cells have lost the capacity of cell division. ",
            "keyString": "98155s42m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Plant tissues are of how many types?",
            "optionA": "  3 ",
            "optionB": "  2 ",
            "optionC": "  5 ",
            "optionD": "  6 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPlant tissue differentiate into three main types: dermal, vascular, and ground tissue. Dermal tissue covers and protects the plant. Vascular tissue transports water, minerals, and sugars to different parts of the plant. ",
            "keyString": "98191s42m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Detail study of internal organs at level of tissue with the help of microscope is called",
            "optionA": "  Histology ",
            "optionB": "  Anatomy ",
            "optionC": "  Ecology ",
            "optionD": "  Taxonomy ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tHistology, also known as microscopic anatomy or microanatomy, is the branch of biology which studies the microscopic anatomy of biological tissues. Histology is the microscopic counterpart to gross anatomy, which looks at larger structures visible without a microscope. ",
            "keyString": "98205s42m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In plants and mineral salts from soil to the aerial parts of the plant are conducted through ",
            "optionA": "  Xylem vessels ",
            "optionB": "  Phloem vessels ",
            "optionC": "  Vascular bundle ",
            "optionD": "  All of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tXylem is associated with translocation of mainly water, mineral salts, some organic nitrogen and hormones, from roots to the aerial parts of the plants. The phloem translocates a variety of organic and inorganic solutes, mainly from the leaves to other parts of the plants. ",
            "keyString": "98217s42m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Smooth muscles are likely to be found in",
            "optionA": "  Muscles of legs ",
            "optionB": "  Muscles of arms ",
            "optionC": "  Stomach ",
            "optionD": "  Heart ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSmooth muscle (so-named because the cells do not have striations) is present in the walls of hollow organs like the urinary bladder, uterus, stomach, intestines, and in the walls of passageways, such as the arteries and veins of the circulatory system, and the tracts of the respiratory, urinary, and reproductive system. ",
            "keyString": "98228s42m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The group of pistils or carpels is collectively spoken off as a",
            "optionA": "  Androecium ",
            "optionB": "  Gynoecium ",
            "optionC": "  Callyx ",
            "optionD": "  Corolla ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe group of pistils or carpels is collectively spoken off as a Gynoecium. ",
            "keyString": "135469s42m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Each stamen has a slender stalk or filament at the top of which a pollen bearing organ is present.",
            "optionA": "  Stigma ",
            "optionB": "  Anther ",
            "optionC": "  Filament ",
            "optionD": "  Ovary ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe part of the stamen where pollen is produced is called anther. ",
            "keyString": "135502s42m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "All sepals collectively constitute a structure termed as",
            "optionA": "  Calyx ",
            "optionB": "  Corolla ",
            "optionC": "  Gynaecium ",
            "optionD": "  Androecium ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSepals (collectively called the calyx) are modified leaves that encase the developing flower. They are sterile floral parts and may be either green or leaflike or composed of petal-like tissue. ",
            "keyString": "135515s42m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "An expanded basal portion of carpel is called as",
            "optionA": "  Stigma ",
            "optionB": "  Ovary ",
            "optionC": "  Style ",
            "optionD": "  Pollen tube ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA pistil typically consists of an expanded basal portion called the ovary, an elongated section called a style and an apical structure that receives pollen called a stigma. ",
            "keyString": "135527s42m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Taken together the petals constitute",
            "optionA": "  Calyx ",
            "optionB": "  Corolla ",
            "optionC": "  Gynaecium ",
            "optionD": "  Androecium ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTogether, all of the petals of a flower are called corolla.",
            "keyString": "135538s42m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Blood group which have no antibodies",
            "optionA": "  A ",
            "optionB": "  B ",
            "optionC": "  AB ",
            "optionD": "  O ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBlood group AB \u2013 has both A and B antigens, but no antibodies. ",
            "keyString": "171672s42m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The sound lub-dub lub-dub is produced by",
            "optionA": "  Liver ",
            "optionB": "  Kidney ",
            "optionC": "  Heart ",
            "optionD": "  Lung ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe sound lub-dub lub-dub is produced by heart. ",
            "keyString": "171701s42m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Blood is red in colour due to the presence of ________ ",
            "optionA": "  Cytochrome ",
            "optionB": "  Chlorophyll ",
            "optionC": "  Hemocyanin ",
            "optionD": "  Haemoglobin ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tHemoglobin is iron-containing oxygen transport protein in the red blood cells of all vertebrates. It has an oxygen binding capacity and gives the red colour to the blood. ",
            "keyString": "171714s42m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Life of red blood cells in the body is",
            "optionA": "  60 days ",
            "optionB": "  120 days ",
            "optionC": "  365 days ",
            "optionD": "  465 days ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tHuman red blood cells (RBC), after differentiating from erythroblasts in the bone marrow, are released into the blood and survive in the circulation for approximately 120 days. In humans and some other species, RBC normally survive in a nonrandom manner. ",
            "keyString": "171725s42m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The upper chambers of the heart are the",
            "optionA": "  Ventricles ",
            "optionB": "  Atria ",
            "optionC": "  Both A & B ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe upper chambers of the heart are the atria. ",
            "keyString": "171735s42m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Diphtheria disease is caused by ",
            "optionA": "  Corynebacterium diphtheria ",
            "optionB": "  Diplococus pneumo ",
            "optionC": "  Pasteurella pestis ",
            "optionD": "  Streptomyces species ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDiphtheria is a serious infection caused by strains of bacteria called Corynebacterium diphtheriae that make a toxin (poison). ",
            "keyString": "206847s42m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following disease is non-communicable in nature?",
            "optionA": "  Cholera ",
            "optionB": "  Chicken-pox ",
            "optionC": "  Tuberculosis ",
            "optionD": "  Cancer ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCancer is a non communicable disease. ",
            "keyString": "206880s42m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "When a disease break out and spread from one place to another affecting large number of peoples it is called",
            "optionA": "  Edemic ",
            "optionB": "  Epidemic ",
            "optionC": "  Endemic ",
            "optionD": "  Sporadic ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tWhen a disease break out and spread from one place to another affecting large number of peoples it is called epidemic. ",
            "keyString": "206894s42m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following disease is caused by female Anopheles mosquito?",
            "optionA": "  Chicken Pox ",
            "optionB": "  Malaria ",
            "optionC": "  Black Fever ",
            "optionD": "  Cholera ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMalaria is transmitted to humans by female mosquitoes of the genus Anopheles. Female mosquitoes take blood meals for egg production, and these blood meals are the link between the human and the mosquito hosts in the parasite life cycle. ",
            "keyString": "206907s42m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one among the following water-borne diseases is not caused by a bacteria ?",
            "optionA": "  Cholera ",
            "optionB": "  Typhoid ",
            "optionC": "  Bacillary dysentery ",
            "optionD": "  Hepatitis A ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tHepatitis A is not caused by a bacteria. ",
            "keyString": "206918s42m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Surgical procedure in which a small portion of sperm duct is removed and cut end ligated in male is called",
            "optionA": "  Vasectomy ",
            "optionB": "  Tubectomy ",
            "optionC": "  Neurotomy ",
            "optionD": "  Psycotomy ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSurgical procedure in which a small portion of sperm duct is removed and cut end ligated in male is called vasectomy. ",
            "keyString": "244104s42m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following serves as a nutritive tissue for the growing embryo?",
            "optionA": "  Ovule ",
            "optionB": "  Zygote ",
            "optionC": "  Ovary ",
            "optionD": "  Endosperm ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe endosperm is a tissue produced inside the seeds of most of the flowering plants following fertilization. It is triploid (meaning three chromosome sets per nucleus) in most species. It surrounds the embryo and provides nutrition in the form of starch, though it can also contain oils and protein. ",
            "keyString": "244134s42m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In the human being, normally in which one of the following parts, does the sperm fertilize the ovum?",
            "optionA": "  Cervix ",
            "optionB": "  Fallopian tube ",
            "optionC": "  Lower part of uterus ",
            "optionD": "  Upper part of uterus ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tHuman fertilization is the union of a human egg and sperm, usually occurring in the ampulla of the fallopian tube. The result of this union is the production of a zygote cell, or fertilized egg, initiating prenatal development. ",
            "keyString": "244148s42m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Finger like ends of the fallopian tubes are called",
            "optionA": "  Fimbriae ",
            "optionB": "  Cysts ",
            "optionC": "  Papillae ",
            "optionD": "  Labia ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe fimbriae of the uterine tube, also known as fimbriae tubae, are small, finger like projections at the end of the fallopian tubes, through which eggs move from the ovaries to the uterus. The fimbriae are connected to the ovary. ",
            "keyString": "244161s42m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Gestation period in human",
            "optionA": "  6 month ",
            "optionB": "  7 month ",
            "optionC": "  8 month ",
            "optionD": "  9 month ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGestation period in human is 9 month. ",
            "keyString": "244172s42m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The camel's hump is composed of a tissue which provides water when oxidized. It is",
            "optionA": "  Skeletal tissue ",
            "optionB": "  Areolar tissue ",
            "optionC": "  Adipose tissue ",
            "optionD": "  Muscular tissue ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCamels humps are made from fatty adipose tissue. This concentrated fat minimizes heat trapping throughout the rest of the body. When the fat tissue is metabolized, it becomes energy and also yields more than 1gram of water. ",
            "keyString": "280249s42m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which among the following is not a connective tissue?",
            "optionA": "  Blood ",
            "optionB": "  Bone ",
            "optionC": "  Skin ",
            "optionD": "  Cartilage ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSkin is composed of epithelial cells, and is therefore not an example of connective tissue. The major types of connective tissue include bone, adipose, blood, and cartilage. ",
            "keyString": "280294s42m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The transport of organic substances in plants is through",
            "optionA": "  Xylem  ",
            "optionB": "  Phloem  ",
            "optionC": "  Fibers  ",
            "optionD": "  Wood  ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe transport of organic substances in plants is through phloem. ",
            "keyString": "280311s42m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who is regarded as father of plant tissue culture?",
            "optionA": "  Haberlandt  ",
            "optionB": "  White  ",
            "optionC": "  Linnaeus  ",
            "optionD": "  Skoog  ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOn the basis of that 1902 address and his pioneering experimentation before and later, Haberlandt is justifiably recognized as the father of plant tissue culture. ",
            "keyString": "280327s42m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What is common in both striated and cardiac cell?",
            "optionA": "  Shape  ",
            "optionB": "  Number  ",
            "optionC": "  Striations  ",
            "optionD": "  Contractions  ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tStriations is common in both striated and cardiac cell. ",
            "keyString": "280342s42m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Normal adult human male has",
            "optionA": "  10 gram of haemoglobin/100 gram of blood ",
            "optionB": "  14 gram of haemoglobin/100 gram of blood ",
            "optionC": "  18 gram of haemoglobin/100 gram of blood ",
            "optionD": "  24 gram of haemoglobin/100 gram of blood ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNormal adult human male has 14 gram of haemoglobin/100 gram of blood. ",
            "keyString": "406366s42m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Plants wilt due to excess of",
            "optionA": "  transpiration ",
            "optionB": "  photosynthesis ",
            "optionC": "  absorption ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tWilting is a condition when the amount of water lost from the plant during transpiration is greater the amount of water absorbed from the soil. It is the loss of rigidity of non-woody parts of the plants. This occurs when the turgor pressure in non-lignified plant cells falls towards zero, as a result of diminished water in the cells.",
            "keyString": "406436s42m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Monotremes are unique mammals because they",
            "optionA": "  posses hair ",
            "optionB": "  give birth to live young ",
            "optionC": "  secret milk in a pouch ",
            "optionD": "  lay eggs ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMonotremes are different from other mammals because they lay eggs and have no teats. Monotremes are different from other mammals because they lay eggs and have no teats. The milk is provided for their young by being secreted by many pores on the female's belly. ",
            "keyString": "406489s42m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Poison glands of snakes are homologous to",
            "optionA": "  electric organs of fishes ",
            "optionB": "  stings of rays ",
            "optionC": "  sebaceous glands of mammals ",
            "optionD": "  salivary glands of vertebrates ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tHere Homologous Means having the same relation or relative position or structure.Here snakes poison is in glands and here salivary glands are in Vertebrates ",
            "keyString": "406538s42m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Radical vascular bundles are those in which",
            "optionA": "  xylem is surrounded by phloem ",
            "optionB": "  phloem is surrounded by xylem ",
            "optionC": "  xylem and phloem occur on the same radius ",
            "optionD": "  xylem and phloem occur on the different radii ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRadical vascular bundles are those in which xylem and phloem occur on the different radii. ",
            "keyString": "406597s42m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Bacteria were first discovered by",
            "optionA": "  Robert Koch ",
            "optionB": "  Robert Hooke ",
            "optionC": "  Louis Pasteur ",
            "optionD": "  ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTwo men are credited today with the discovery of microorganisms using primitive microscopes: Robert Hooke who described the fruiting structures of molds in 1665 and Antoni van Leeuwenhoek who is credited with the discovery of bacteria in 1676. ",
            "keyString": "482405s42m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "It is very serious disease of brain which is caused by fungi.",
            "optionA": "  Rust ",
            "optionB": "  Meningitis ",
            "optionC": "  Smut ",
            "optionD": "  Ringworm ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMeningitis is very serious disease of brain which is caused by fungi. ",
            "keyString": "552745s42m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Administering a vaccine provides protection by inducing synthesis of antibodies (proteins) specific of the vaccine. The cell in the body responsible for the production of antibodies is",
            "optionA": "  Granulocyte ",
            "optionB": "  Lymphocyte ",
            "optionC": "  Erythrocyte (red blood cell) ",
            "optionD": "  Platelet ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tLymphocyte is responsible for production of antibodies. ",
            "keyString": "552778s42m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "As an infant, the ability to produce antibodies is",
            "optionA": "  About 80% of that of an adult ",
            "optionB": "  Nonexistent ",
            "optionC": "  Limited ",
            "optionD": "  The same as an adult ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAs an infant, the ability to produce antibodies is limited. ",
            "keyString": "552793s42m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Antigen is a substance which",
            "optionA": "  Lowers body temperature ",
            "optionB": "  Destroys harmful bacteria ",
            "optionC": "  Triggers the immune system ",
            "optionD": "  Is used as an antidote to poison ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAn antigen is any substance that causes your immune system to produce antibodies against it. This means your immune system does not recognize the substance, and is trying to fight it off. An antigen may be a substance from the environment, such as chemicals, bacteria, viruses, or pollen. ",
            "keyString": "552805s42m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "AIDS is caused by the organisms which are",
            "optionA": "  Bacteria ",
            "optionB": "  Fungi ",
            "optionC": "  Viruses (HIV) ",
            "optionD": "  ProtoZoa ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAcquired immunodeficiency syndrome (AIDS) is a chronic, potentially life-threatening condition caused by the human immunodeficiency virus (HIV). ",
            "keyString": "552817s42m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is not the part of digestive system ?",
            "optionA": "  Liver ",
            "optionB": "  Gall bladder ",
            "optionC": "  Cornea ",
            "optionD": "  Intestine ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCornea is not the part of digestive system. ",
            "keyString": "593257s42m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The enzyme found in saliva",
            "optionA": "  Renine ",
            "optionB": "  Ptylin ",
            "optionC": "  Tenin ",
            "optionD": "  Resin ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe enzyme found in saliva is Ptylin. ",
            "keyString": "593357s42m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is the largest gland in human body?",
            "optionA": "  Thyroid ",
            "optionB": "  Liver ",
            "optionC": "  Kidney ",
            "optionD": "  Pancreas ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tLiver is the largest gland in body. It stores its waste bile in Gall Bladder. Bile is released into duodenum and helps in digestion of fats. ",
            "keyString": "593387s42m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is not a digestive enzyme in the human system?",
            "optionA": "  Trypsin ",
            "optionB": "  Gastrin ",
            "optionC": "  Ptyalin ",
            "optionD": "  Pepsin ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGastrin is not a digestive enzyme, but a hormone. ",
            "keyString": "593416s42m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In the human body which structure is the appendix attached to",
            "optionA": "  Large intestine ",
            "optionB": "  The small intestine ",
            "optionC": "  The gall bladder ",
            "optionD": "  The stomach ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe appendix sits at the junction of the small intestine and large intestine. It's a thin tube about four inches long. Normally, the appendix sits in the lower right abdomen. The function of the appendix is unknown. ",
            "keyString": "593440s42m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In a healthy person rate of heart beat on one minute is",
            "optionA": "  58 times ",
            "optionB": "  67 times ",
            "optionC": "  72 times ",
            "optionD": "  90 times ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn a healthy person rate of heart beat on one minute is 72 times. ",
            "keyString": "639400s42m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The word histology is related with",
            "optionA": "  Hepatology ",
            "optionB": "  Hematalogy ",
            "optionC": "  Histology ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe word histology is related with hematology. ",
            "keyString": "639431s42m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following statements regarding haemoglobin is correct?",
            "optionA": "  Haemoglobin present in RBC can carry only oxygen but not carbon dioxide ",
            "optionB": "  Haemoglobin of RBC can carry both oxygen and carbon dioxide ",
            "optionC": "  Haemoglobin of RBC can carry only carbon dioxide ",
            "optionD": "  Haemoglobin is only used for blood clotting and not for carrying gases ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDuring respiration, about 97% of oxygen is transported by Red Blood Cells in blood and the remaining 3% gets dissolved in the plasma.Around 20-25% of carbon dioxide is carried by haemoglobin as carbamino-haemoglobin. Oxygen enters the blood from the lungs and carbon dioxide is expelled out of the blood into the lungs. The blood serves to transport both gases. Oxygen is carried to the cells. Carbon dioxide is carried away from the cells. ",
            "keyString": "639445s42m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The vitamin required for coagulation of blood is",
            "optionA": "  B6 ",
            "optionB": "  C ",
            "optionC": "  K ",
            "optionD": "  B ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tVitamin K is an essential vitamin that is needed by the body for blood clotting, bone building, and other important processes. ",
            "keyString": "639457s42m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Amount of blood found in the body of man is",
            "optionA": "  10% of total body weight ",
            "optionB": "  25% of total body weight ",
            "optionC": "  7% total body weight ",
            "optionD": "  9% of total body weight ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAmount of blood found in the body of man is 7% total body weight. ",
            "keyString": "639468s42m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "We get pulse rate from",
            "optionA": "  Vein ",
            "optionB": "  Artery ",
            "optionC": "  Skin ",
            "optionD": "  Nerve ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tWe get pulse rate from artery. ",
            "keyString": "689249s42m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following are involved directly in pulmonary circulation?",
            "optionA": "  Left ventricle, aorta, and inferior vena cava ",
            "optionB": "  Right atrium, aorta, and left ventricle ",
            "optionC": "  Superior vena cava, right atrium, and left ventricle ",
            "optionD": "  Right ventricle, pulmonary artery, and left atrium ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe pulmonary circulation is the portion of the circulatory system which carries deoxygenated blood away from the right ventricle, to the lungs, and returns oxygenated blood to the left atrium and ventricle of the heart. ",
            "keyString": "689282s42m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Rh factor is discovered by",
            "optionA": "  Landsteiner ",
            "optionB": "  Weiner ",
            "optionC": "  Landsteiner and Weiner ",
            "optionD": "  Leuen hook ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Rh factor was discovered in 1940 by Landsteiner and Wiener. 5 Rabbits were injected with the blood of the rhesus monkey (Macacus rhesus). ",
            "keyString": "689297s42m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Rh factor is related with",
            "optionA": "  Bear ",
            "optionB": "  Monkey ",
            "optionC": "  Man ",
            "optionD": "  Cat ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRh factor is related with monkey. ",
            "keyString": "689312s42m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What is the main purpose of white blood corpuscles?",
            "optionA": "  To carry nutrients ",
            "optionB": "  To combat infection ",
            "optionC": "  To carry oxygen ",
            "optionD": "  To give strength ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe main purpose of white blood corpuscles is to combat infection. ",
            "keyString": "689324s42m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Ordinary table salt is sodium chloride. What is baking soda?",
            "optionA": "  Potassium chloride ",
            "optionB": "  Potassium carbonate ",
            "optionC": "  Potassium hydroxide ",
            "optionD": "  Sodium bicarbonate ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSodium bicarbonate is baking soda. ",
            "keyString": "757098s42m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Ozone hole refers to",
            "optionA": "  hole in ozone layer ",
            "optionB": "  decrease in the ozone layer in troposphere ",
            "optionC": "  decrease in thickness of ozone layer in stratosphere ",
            "optionD": "  increase in the thickness of ozone layer in troposphere ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe term 'ozone hole' refers to the depletion of the protective ozone layer in the upper atmosphere (stratosphere) over Earth's polar regions. Stratospheric ozone is constantly produced by the action of the sun's ultraviolet radiation on oxygen molecules (known as photochemical reactions). ",
            "keyString": "757130s42m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Pine, fir, spruce, cedar, larch and cypress are the famous timber-yielding plants of which several also occur widely in the hilly regions of India. All these belong to",
            "optionA": "  angiosperms ",
            "optionB": "  gymnosperms ",
            "optionC": "  monocotyledons ",
            "optionD": "  dicotyledons ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPine, fir, spruce, cedar, larch and cypress are the famous timber-yielding plants of which several also occur widely in the hilly regions of India. All these belong to gymnosperms, a taxonomic class that includes plants whose seeds are not enclosed in an ovule.",
            "keyString": "757144s42m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Pollination is best defined as",
            "optionA": "  transfer of pollen from anther to stigma ",
            "optionB": "  germination of pollen grains ",
            "optionC": "  growth of pollen tube in ovule ",
            "optionD": "  visiting flowers by insects ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPollination can be best defined as the transfer of pollen from the male anther of a flower to the female stigma to produce new offspring. ",
            "keyString": "757155s42m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Plants receive their nutrients mainly from",
            "optionA": "  chlorophyll ",
            "optionB": "  atmosphere ",
            "optionC": "  light ",
            "optionD": "  soil ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPlants receive their nutrients mainly from soil. ",
            "keyString": "757165s42m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The corner of the cells of collenchyma tissue in plant are thickened due to deposition of ________ ",
            "optionA": "  Lignin and suberin ",
            "optionB": "  Suberin and cutin ",
            "optionC": "  Cellulose and pectin ",
            "optionD": "  Chitin and lignin ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe collenchyma is thickened due to deposition of pectin and cellulose. ",
            "keyString": "800496s42m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which plant cells give support to plant body?",
            "optionA": "  Phloem cells ",
            "optionB": "  Xylem cells ",
            "optionC": "  Sclerenchymatous cells ",
            "optionD": "  Parenchyma cells ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSclerenchyma cells also provide support to the plant, but unlike collenchyma cells, many of them are dead at maturity. ",
            "keyString": "800552s42m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which plants have vascular tissues i.e .xylem and phloem vessel?",
            "optionA": "  Tracheophytes ",
            "optionB": "  Bryophytes ",
            "optionC": "  Thallophytes ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTracheophytes have vascular tissues i.e .xylem and phloem vessel. ",
            "keyString": "800567s42m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Branch of science which deals with the study of tissue found in the body of organism is",
            "optionA": "  Hepatology ",
            "optionB": "  Histology ",
            "optionC": "  Haematology ",
            "optionD": "  Herpetology ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tHistology is the branch of biology concerned with the composition and structure of plant and animal tissues in relation to their specialized functions. ",
            "keyString": "800581s42m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following is modification of parenchyma?",
            "optionA": "  Fibres found in phloem ",
            "optionB": "  Tracheids ",
            "optionC": "  Vessel ",
            "optionD": "  Chlorenchyma ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tParenchyma cells with chloroplast to carry out photosynthesis are called as chlorenchyma cells. Therefore, option D is correct. ",
            "keyString": "800594s42m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Protein synthesis in a bacterial cell is done by",
            "optionA": "  Centrioles  ",
            "optionB": "  Flagella  ",
            "optionC": "  Thylakoids  ",
            "optionD": "  Ribosomes  ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRibosomes are protein-making factories found in all cells, from humans to bacteria. The ribosome will scan down the RNA, like a train going down tracks, adding in amino acids to the protein being produced. When the ribosome reaches the end of the RNA, the protein is released. This process is called translation. ",
            "keyString": "841203s42m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one is the first organelle to be discovered?",
            "optionA": "  Chloroplast  ",
            "optionB": "  Nucleus  ",
            "optionC": "  Vacuole  ",
            "optionD": "  Lysosome  ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn 1833, Brown observed and described the nucleus, the first organelle. In 1838, the many and various observations were converted into a cell theory by Schleiden, who proposed that all plant tissues were composed of nucleated cells. ",
            "keyString": "841233s42m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The cell was discovered by",
            "optionA": "  Hooke ",
            "optionB": "  Schleiden  ",
            "optionC": "  Oken  ",
            "optionD": "  Darwin  ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe cell was discovered by Robert Hooke. ",
            "keyString": "841246s42m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Powerhouse of the cell is",
            "optionA": "  Chloroplast  ",
            "optionB": "  Nucleus  ",
            "optionC": "  Endoplasmic reticulum  ",
            "optionD": "  Mitochondria  ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tWork on mitochondria did not stop in the 1950s after it was named \u201cthe powerhouse of the cell.\u201d ",
            "keyString": "841257s42m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which year, Schwann and Schleiden suggested that cells were the basic unit of life",
            "optionA": "  1832  ",
            "optionB": "  1839  ",
            "optionC": "  1849  ",
            "optionD": "  1852  ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCredit for developing cell theory is usually given to three scientists: Theodor Schwann, Matthias Jakob Schleiden, and Rudolf Virchow. In 1839, Schwann and Schleiden suggested that cells were the basic unit of life. ",
            "keyString": "841268s42m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Nitrogenous Food is",
            "optionA": "  Proteins ",
            "optionB": "  Carbohydrates ",
            "optionC": "  Salts ",
            "optionD": "  Lipids ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tProteins are nitrogenous foods. Nitrogenous foods as it is clear from the name are those foods which are high in the quantity of nitrogen they possess. Foods with nitrogen are the main ingredients when anyone talks about good health. ",
            "keyString": "880837s42m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following crops would be preffered for sowing in order to enrich the soil with nitrogen?",
            "optionA": "  Wheat ",
            "optionB": "  Mustard ",
            "optionC": "  Sunflower ",
            "optionD": "  Gram ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe \"gram crops\" would be preferred for sowing in order to enrich the \"soil with nitrogen\". ",
            "keyString": "880923s42m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The temperature danger zone for food is",
            "optionA": "  5 - 63 deg ",
            "optionB": "  Above 45 deg ",
            "optionC": "  Below 15 deg ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe temperature danger zone for food is 5 - 63 degree. ",
            "keyString": "880944s42m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Some species of which of the below kinds of organisms are employed as biopesticides?\n1. Bacteria\n2. Fungi\n3. Flowering plants",
            "optionA": "  1 only ",
            "optionB": "  2 and 3 only ",
            "optionC": "  1 and 3 only ",
            "optionD": "  1, 2 and 3 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBacteria are employed as biopesticides. ",
            "keyString": "880959s42m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Golden rice has the highest quantity of",
            "optionA": "  Vitamin A ",
            "optionB": "  Vitamin B ",
            "optionC": "  Vitamin C ",
            "optionD": "  Vitamin K ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGolden rice is a variety of rice (Oryza sativa) produced through genetic engineering to biosynthesize beta-carotene, a precursor of vitamin A, in the edible parts of rice. ",
            "keyString": "880980s42m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which phylum nerve cells are found but nerves are absent?",
            "optionA": "  Porifera ",
            "optionB": "  Coelenterata ",
            "optionC": "  Platyhelminthes ",
            "optionD": "  Nemathelminthes ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn Coelenterata nerve cells are found but nerves are absent. ",
            "keyString": "921111s42m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The non-vascular land plants are included in the group called ",
            "optionA": "  Thallophyta ",
            "optionB": "  Bryophyta ",
            "optionC": "  Tracheophyta ",
            "optionD": "  Pteridophyta ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNon vascular plants (often referred to collectively as the bryophytes) include three groups: the mosses (Bryophyta), approximately 15,000 species; liverworts (Hepaticophyta), approximately 7500 species; and hornworts (Anthocerophyta), approximately 250 species. ",
            "keyString": "921150s42m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The animals in which the body cavity is absent are known as ________ .",
            "optionA": "  Coelomates ",
            "optionB": "  Wild ",
            "optionC": "  Pseudocoelomates ",
            "optionD": "  Acoelomates ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIf the body cavity is absent called as acoelom and animal called as acoelomate e.g., Platyhelminthes. ",
            "keyString": "921164s42m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who is called the Father of Taxonomy?",
            "optionA": "  Aristotle ",
            "optionB": "  Carolus Linnaeus ",
            "optionC": "  Theophrastus ",
            "optionD": "  Lamarck ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCarolus Linnaeus is called the Father of Taxonomy. ",
            "keyString": "921176s42m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Spiders belong to the phylum",
            "optionA": "  Mollusca ",
            "optionB": "  Annelida ",
            "optionC": "  Cnidaria ",
            "optionD": "  Arthropoda ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArthropod, (phylum Arthropoda), any member of the phylum Arthropoda, the largest phylum in the animal kingdom, which includes such familiar forms as lobsters, crabs, spiders, mites, insects, centipedes, and millipedes. ",
            "keyString": "921187s42m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In plants, exchange of gases takes place through",
            "optionA": "  Stomata ",
            "optionB": "  Palisade tissue ",
            "optionC": "  Spongy tissue ",
            "optionD": "  Mid rib ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe exchange of oxygen and carbon dioxide in the leaf (as well as the loss of water vapour in transpiration) occurs through pores called stomata (singular = stoma). Normally stomata open when the light strikes the leaf in the morning and close during the night. ",
            "keyString": "958606s42m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The numerous minute pores in the epidermis of a leaf are called",
            "optionA": "  Stomata  ",
            "optionB": "  Lenticels  ",
            "optionC": "  Hydathodes  ",
            "optionD": "  Perforation  ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe numerous minute pores in the epidermis of a leaf are called stomata. ",
            "keyString": "958636s42m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Stomata helps in",
            "optionA": "  Exchange of gases  ",
            "optionB": "  Exchange of lipids  ",
            "optionC": "  Exchange of water  ",
            "optionD": "  Exchange of proteins  ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tStomata helps in exchange of gases. ",
            "keyString": "958648s42m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Release of water from plants as water droplets is known as",
            "optionA": "  Root pressure  ",
            "optionB": "  Transpiration  ",
            "optionC": "  Osmotic pressure  ",
            "optionD": "  Guttation  ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGuttation is the loss of water in the form of water droplets from hydathodes (small pores) on the leaf margin of a small herbacious plant.",
            "keyString": "958660s42m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Stomata open at night in",
            "optionA": "  CAM plants  ",
            "optionB": "  C3 plants  ",
            "optionC": "  C4 plants  ",
            "optionD": "  Succulent plants  ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn CAM plants, stomata are open during the night and closed during day time. This is an adaptation of cutting transpiration loss of water. CAM plants grow in deserts and are exposed to high temperatures.Their stomata are open during the night for carbon dioxide uptake but closed during the day to prevent water loss. Thus, the correct answer is option C. ",
            "keyString": "958670s42m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Chiropterophily is the process of pollination by",
            "optionA": "  Bee  ",
            "optionB": "  Bat  ",
            "optionC": "  Insect  ",
            "optionD": "  Bird  ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tChiropterophily or bat pollination is the pollination of flowering plants by bats. Plants adapted to use bats or moths as pollinators typically have white petals, strong scent and flower at night, whereas plants that use birds as pollinators tend to produce copious nectar and have red petals. ",
            "keyString": "2338s43m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following may cause the breakdown of pyruvate into lactic acid in our muscles?",
            "optionA": "  Lack of water ",
            "optionB": "  Lack of Oxygen ",
            "optionC": "  Lack of carbon dioxide ",
            "optionD": "  Lack of nitrogen ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tLack of oxygen may cause the breakdown of pyruvate into lactic acid in our muscles. ",
            "keyString": "2400s43m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The main result of aerobic respiration is the",
            "optionA": "  Production of lactic acid as an end product ",
            "optionB": "  Production of ATP from the breakdown of glucose ",
            "optionC": "  Conversion of radiant energy into chemical energy ",
            "optionD": "  Storage of energy in a polysaccharide ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAerobic respiration is the aerobic catabolism of nutrients to carbon dioxide, water, and energy, and involves an electron transport system in which molecular oxygen is the final electron acceptor. ",
            "keyString": "2421s43m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What compound directly provides energy for cellular work?",
            "optionA": "  ATP ",
            "optionB": "  ADP ",
            "optionC": "  NADP ",
            "optionD": "  NADH ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tATP compound directly provides energy for cellular work. ",
            "keyString": "2437s43m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The outer membrane that covers the lungs",
            "optionA": "  Dura mater ",
            "optionB": "  Pleura ",
            "optionC": "  Pia mater ",
            "optionD": "  Myelin sheath ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe outer surfaces of the lungs are covered with a membrane called the pleura. ",
            "keyString": "2454s43m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following is a rich source of iron?",
            "optionA": "  Carrot ",
            "optionB": "  Pea ",
            "optionC": "  Rice ",
            "optionD": "  Spinach ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSpinach is a rich source of iron. ",
            "keyString": "51055s43m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The vitamin that is destroyed on heating is ",
            "optionA": "  Vitamin E ",
            "optionB": "  Vitamin C ",
            "optionC": "  Vitamin A ",
            "optionD": "  Vitamin B ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tVitamin C is a water-soluble and temperature-sensitive vitamin, so is easily degraded during cooking, and elevated temperatures and long cooking times have been found to cause particularly severe losses of vitamin C [12]. ",
            "keyString": "51151s43m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which among the following is a vitamin?",
            "optionA": "  Citric acid ",
            "optionB": "  Follic acid ",
            "optionC": "  Glutonic acid ",
            "optionD": "  None ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFollic acid is a vitamin. ",
            "keyString": "51214s43m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "They play key roles in the contraction of muscles,digestion of food and clotting of blood.",
            "optionA": "  Fats ",
            "optionB": "  Carbohydrates ",
            "optionC": "  Proteins ",
            "optionD": "  Vitamins ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tProteins play key roles in the contraction of muscles,digestion of food and clotting of blood. ",
            "keyString": "51270s43m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following organisms is dependent on saprophytic mode of nutrition?",
            "optionA": "  Agaricus ",
            "optionB": "  Ulothrix ",
            "optionC": "  Riccia ",
            "optionD": "  Cladophora ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSaprophytic fungi feed on dead plant and animal remains. Many are extremely beneficial, breaking down this organic material into humus, minerals and nutrients that can be utilised by plants. Agaricus is one among them. ",
            "keyString": "51317s43m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which structure connects one bone to another bone?",
            "optionA": "  Cartilage  ",
            "optionB": "  Tendons  ",
            "optionC": "  Ligaments  ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above  ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA tendon serves to move the bone or structure. A ligament is a fibrous connective tissue which attaches bone to bone, and usually serves to hold structures together and keep them stable. ",
            "keyString": "114125s43m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Hinge joint is present between",
            "optionA": "  Humerus and pactoral griddle  ",
            "optionB": "  Femur acetabulum  ",
            "optionC": "  Humerus and radio-ulna  ",
            "optionD": "  Femur and pelvic gridle  ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tHinge joint is present between humerus and radio-ulna. ",
            "keyString": "114258s43m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is not a form of Monosaccharide Sugar?",
            "optionA": "  Galactose ",
            "optionB": "  Glucose ",
            "optionC": "  Fructose ",
            "optionD": "  Maltose ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMaltose is not a form of Monosaccharide Sugar. ",
            "keyString": "114331s43m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "All of the following are fat-soluble vitamins except",
            "optionA": "  Vitamin C ",
            "optionB": "  Vitamin A ",
            "optionC": "  Vitamin D ",
            "optionD": "  Vitamin K ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAll of the following are fat-soluble vitamins except Vitamin C. ",
            "keyString": "114395s43m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Marasmus usually is associated with a deficiency of",
            "optionA": "  Vitamins ",
            "optionB": "  Calories ",
            "optionC": "  Proteins ",
            "optionD": "  Fats ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMarasmus usually is associated with a deficiency of Calories. ",
            "keyString": "114448s43m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Nucleoli are present during",
            "optionA": "  Prophase ",
            "optionB": "  Anaphase ",
            "optionC": "  Interphase ",
            "optionD": "  Prometaphase ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNucleoli are present during interphase. ",
            "keyString": "163746s43m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Unlike Mitosis, Meiosis results in the formation of",
            "optionA": "  2N daughter cells ",
            "optionB": "  Haploid cells ",
            "optionC": "  Body cells ",
            "optionD": "  Diploid cells ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tUnlike Mitosis, Meiosis results in the formation of 4 Genetically different cells. Meiosis results in the formation of 4 Haploid daughter cells from one Diploid parent cell. ",
            "keyString": "163859s43m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "How many daughter cells are produced in mitosis?",
            "optionA": "  2 ",
            "optionB": "  4 ",
            "optionC": "  8 ",
            "optionD": "  None ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t2 daughter cells are produced in mitosis. ",
            "keyString": "163891s43m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Chromosome start separating at which stage of mitosis?",
            "optionA": "  Early metaphase ",
            "optionB": "  Late metaphase ",
            "optionC": "  Early anaphase ",
            "optionD": "  Early telophase ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn anaphase, the sister chromatids separate from each other and are pulled towards opposite ends of the cell.",
            "keyString": "163920s43m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Almost all kinds of vegetative reproduction are carried out by the division known as",
            "optionA": "  Mitosis ",
            "optionB": "  Meiosis ",
            "optionC": "  Multiple fission ",
            "optionD": "  Budding ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAlmost all kinds of vegetative reproduction are carried out by the division known as mitosis. ",
            "keyString": "163940s43m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The scientific study of plants is termed as",
            "optionA": "  Zoology ",
            "optionB": "  Botany ",
            "optionC": "  Ecology ",
            "optionD": "  Taxonomoy ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBotany, also called plant science(s), plant biology or phytology, is the science of plant life and a branch of biology. A botanist, plant scientist or phytologist is a scientist who specialises in this field. ",
            "keyString": "212836s43m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Lobsters belong to which one of the following classes of organisms?",
            "optionA": "  Arachnids ",
            "optionB": "  Crustaceans ",
            "optionC": "  Insects ",
            "optionD": "  Myriopods ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tLobsters are farther categorized into the class Crustacea, along with other marine organisms like crabs and shrimp. These crustaceans are distinguishable from other Arthropods with hard exoskeletons, like mussels and clams, because their shell is softer and more flexible. ",
            "keyString": "212890s43m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Fishes have a ________ chambered heart.",
            "optionA": "  Single ",
            "optionB": "  Three ",
            "optionC": "  Four ",
            "optionD": "  Two ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFish have a two-chambered heart with unidirectional circulation. Amphibians have a three-chambered heart, which has some mixing of the blood, and they have double circulation. Most non-avian reptiles have a three-chambered heart, but have little mixing of the blood; they have double circulation. ",
            "keyString": "212909s43m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following is not a chordate?",
            "optionA": "  Starfish ",
            "optionB": "  Dolphin ",
            "optionC": "  Shark ",
            "optionD": "  Snake ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tStarfish is not a chordate. ",
            "keyString": "212935s43m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Carica papaya is the scientific name of ________ .",
            "optionA": "  Peepal ",
            "optionB": "  Papaya ",
            "optionC": "  Tamarind ",
            "optionD": "  Drumstick ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCarica papaya is the scientific name of papaya. ",
            "keyString": "212972s43m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Number of cranial nerve found in man is",
            "optionA": "  10 pair ",
            "optionB": "  12 pair ",
            "optionC": "  24 pair ",
            "optionD": "  36 pair ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMost doctors claim to have 12 cranial nerves, whereas humans in fact have 24 (12 pairs). ",
            "keyString": "330129s43m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Centre of intelligence in human brain is",
            "optionA": "  Gerebellum ",
            "optionB": "  Cerebrum ",
            "optionC": "  Medulla oblangate ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCentre of intelligence in human brain is Cerebrum. ",
            "keyString": "330177s43m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The schwann cell forms a myelin sheath around the",
            "optionA": "  Nodes of Ranvier ",
            "optionB": "  Dendrites ",
            "optionC": "  Nucleus ",
            "optionD": "  Axon ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMyelin is formed by Schwann cells in the peripheral nervous system (PNS) and oligodendrocytes in the central nervous system (CNS). Each Schwann cell forms a single myelin sheath around an axon. ",
            "keyString": "330196s43m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The peripheral nervous system consists of",
            "optionA": "  Nerves from eyes to CNS ",
            "optionB": "  Nerves from ears to CNS ",
            "optionC": "  Nerves from skin to CNS ",
            "optionD": "  All of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe peripheral nervous system consists of the nerves that branch out from the brain and spinal cord. These nerves form the communication network between the CNS and the body parts. The peripheral nervous system is further subdivided into the somatic nervous system and the autonomic nervous system. ",
            "keyString": "330210s43m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which part of the brain plays an important role in motor control?",
            "optionA": "  Cerebellum ",
            "optionB": "  Cerebrum ",
            "optionC": "  Medulla ",
            "optionD": "  Pons ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn humans, the cerebellum plays an important role in motor control. It may also be involved in some cognitive functions such as attention and language as well as emotional control such as regulating fear and pleasure responses, but its movement-related functions are the most solidly established. ",
            "keyString": "330223s43m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Nephron is related to which of the following system of human body?",
            "optionA": "  Circulatory system ",
            "optionB": "  Excretory system ",
            "optionC": "  Reproductive system ",
            "optionD": "  Respiratory system ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tExcretory system consists of specialized structures and capillary networks that assist in the excretory process. The human excretory system includes the kidneys and their functional unit, the nephron. ",
            "keyString": "378415s43m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Dialysis is used to perform the function of",
            "optionA": "  Lung ",
            "optionB": "  Heart ",
            "optionC": "  Liver ",
            "optionD": "  Kidney ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tWhen your kidneys fail, dialysis keeps your body in balance by: removing waste, salt and extra water to prevent them from building up in the body, keeping a safe level of certain chemicals in your blood, such as potassium, sodium and bicarbonate and helping to control blood pressure. ",
            "keyString": "378449s43m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Excretion is best described as the removal of",
            "optionA": "  Undigested material from the digestive tract ",
            "optionB": "  Metabolic wastes from a cell ",
            "optionC": "  Toxic wastes by the process of cyclosis ",
            "optionD": "  Water molecules from dipeptide hydrolysis ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tExcretion is best described as the removal of metabolic wastes from a cell. ",
            "keyString": "378466s43m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Islets of Langerhans are present in",
            "optionA": "  Kidney ",
            "optionB": "  Liver ",
            "optionC": "  Pancreas ",
            "optionD": "  Trachea ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIslets of Langerhans are islands of endocrine cells scattered throughout the pancreas. ",
            "keyString": "378480s43m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Filtration of blood occur in",
            "optionA": "  Lung ",
            "optionB": "  Bowmen's capsule ",
            "optionC": "  Uriniferous tubule ",
            "optionD": "  Ureater ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFiltration of blood occur in Bowmen's capsule. ",
            "keyString": "378493s43m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which among the following does not have a cell wall?",
            "optionA": "  Euglena ",
            "optionB": "  Paramecium ",
            "optionC": "  Gonyaulax ",
            "optionD": "  Mycoplasma ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMycoplasma are a mollicute genus of bacteria that lack a cell wall around their cell membranes. Mycoplasma species are the smallest bacterial cells yet discovered, can survive without oxygen, and come in various shapes. ",
            "keyString": "427137s43m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The ability to fix atmospheric nitrogen is found in the ",
            "optionA": "  Leaves of some crop plants ",
            "optionB": "  Some marine red algae ",
            "optionC": "  Some blue-green algae ",
            "optionD": "  Cholera ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe ability to fix atmospheric nitrogen is found in the blue-green algae. ",
            "keyString": "427170s43m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The number of chloroplasts in a cell of Spirogyra is",
            "optionA": "  1-4 ",
            "optionB": "  1-8 ",
            "optionC": "  1-14 ",
            "optionD": "  2-8 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe number of chloroplasts in a cell of Spirogyra is 1-14. ",
            "keyString": "427185s43m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "'Pond silk' is the common name of",
            "optionA": "  Spongilla ",
            "optionB": "  Chlorella ",
            "optionC": "  Selaginella ",
            "optionD": "  Spirogyra ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSpirogyra is free-floating green algae present in freshwater habitats such as ponds, lakes, etc. Spirogyra is commonly known as water silk or pond silk. ",
            "keyString": "427199s43m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Potato blight is caused by",
            "optionA": "  Penicillium ",
            "optionB": "  Meningitis ",
            "optionC": "  Smut ",
            "optionD": "  Ringworm ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPotato blight is caused by meningitis. ",
            "keyString": "427211s43m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is the cellular respiratory centre?",
            "optionA": "  Nucleus ",
            "optionB": "  Mitochondria ",
            "optionC": "  Ribosome ",
            "optionD": "  Golgi body ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCellular respiratory centre is the mitochondria. ",
            "keyString": "480252s43m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The first root produced from a seed is known as",
            "optionA": "  Conical root  ",
            "optionB": "  Fusiform root  ",
            "optionC": "  Radicle  ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above  ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe primary root, or radicle, is the first organ to appear when a seed germinates. It grows downward into the soil, anchoring the seedling. In gymnosperms and dicotyledons (angiosperms with two seed leaves), the radicle becomes a taproot.",
            "keyString": "480289s43m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The site in ovule where funicle is attached",
            "optionA": "  Nucellus  ",
            "optionB": "  Chalaza  ",
            "optionC": "  Raphe  ",
            "optionD": "  Hilum  ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNucellus is the wall of megasporangium and the part of ovule in which embryo sac develops. Nucellus provide nutrition to the growing embryo and also protects the embryo. Chalaza is the portion of ovule which is opposite to the region of attachment of nucellus, integuments and funicle. Micropyle is a small opening covered by the integuments and it is the site of entry of pollen tube during fertilisation. Hilum is a structure by which the body of ovule is attached to the funicle. So, the correct answer is D. ",
            "keyString": "480305s43m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The seeds which contain abundant glyoxysomes are",
            "optionA": "  Dry seeds  ",
            "optionB": "  Germinating seeds  ",
            "optionC": "  Wet seeds  ",
            "optionD": "  Shrunken seeds  ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe seeds which contain abundant glyoxysomes are germinating seeds. ",
            "keyString": "480318s43m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Skin is an example of what type of tissue?",
            "optionA": "  Epithelial ",
            "optionB": "  Connective ",
            "optionC": "  Nervous ",
            "optionD": "  All of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSkin is an example of epithelial tissue. ",
            "keyString": "480330s43m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What is the effect of oversecretion of hormone from pituitary gland?",
            "optionA": "  Increase growth in length ",
            "optionB": "  Unbalanced development of body ",
            "optionC": "  Body became curve ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tWhen the pituitary gland produces excess growth hormones the result is excessive growth, called acromegaly. The excessive growth occurs first in the hands and feet, as soft tissue begins to swell. ",
            "keyString": "528229s43m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is not a gland?",
            "optionA": "  Thyroid ",
            "optionB": "  Gastrine ",
            "optionC": "  Liver ",
            "optionD": "  Pancreas ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGastrine is not a gland. ",
            "keyString": "528262s43m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Oxytocin hormone is secreted by gland",
            "optionA": "  Pituitary ",
            "optionB": "  Pineal ",
            "optionC": "  Adrenal ",
            "optionD": "  Ovary ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOxytocin is produced in the hypothalamus and is secreted into the bloodstream by the posterior pituitary gland. Secretion depends on electrical activity of neurons in the hypothalamus \u2013 it is released into the blood when these cells are excited. ",
            "keyString": "528277s43m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Enlargment of _______ gland takes place due to deficiency of iodine",
            "optionA": "  Thyroid ",
            "optionB": "  Pituitary ",
            "optionC": "  Adrenal ",
            "optionD": "  Parotid ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tEnlargment of thyroid gland takes place due to deficiency of iodine. ",
            "keyString": "528289s43m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of following is not a endocrine gland?",
            "optionA": "  Adrenal ",
            "optionB": "  Pituitary ",
            "optionC": "  Thyroid ",
            "optionD": "  Liver ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tEndocrine glands are the ductless glands that secrete their products into bloodstream from where they are carried to the target organs. Pancreas, testes and thymus are endocrine glands as they secrete hormones. Pancreas secrete insulin and glucagon, testes secrete testosterone and thymus secrete thymosin hormone. Liver is not an endocrine gland instead, it is a digestive organ which secretes bile juice which is necessary for emulsification of fats. ",
            "keyString": "528300s43m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Branch of science which deal with the study of causative agent of disease is",
            "optionA": "  Ecology ",
            "optionB": "  Etiology ",
            "optionC": "  Eugenics ",
            "optionD": "  Euthenics ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tEtiology is the science of causes; especially of disease. ",
            "keyString": "575026s43m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Select the correct statement about active and passive immunity.",
            "optionA": "  A vaccination is an example of the introduction of passive immunity into the body ",
            "optionB": "  Active and passive humoral immunity are both mechanisms of adaptive immunity that use antibodies ",
            "optionC": "  Immunological memory is established by passive immunization ",
            "optionD": "  The antibodies utilized in active immunity are acquired from another organism ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tActive and passive humoral immunity are both mechanisms of adaptive immunity that use antibodies. ",
            "keyString": "575083s43m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Polio is caused by",
            "optionA": "  Bacteria ",
            "optionB": "  Virus ",
            "optionC": "  Fungus ",
            "optionD": "  Protozoa ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPolio, or poliomyelitis, is a disabling and life-threatening disease caused by the poliovirus. The virus spreads from person to person and can infect a person's spinal cord, causing paralysis. ",
            "keyString": "575097s43m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Rhinitis is the disease that effects which body part?",
            "optionA": "  Brain ",
            "optionB": "  Nose ",
            "optionC": "  Blood ",
            "optionD": "  Skin ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRhinitis is inflammation and swelling of the mucous membrane of the nose, characterized by a runny nose and stuffiness and usually caused by the common cold or a seasonal allergy. Colds and allergies are the most common causes of rhinitis. ",
            "keyString": "575109s43m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which disease is caused due to deficiency of Iodine?",
            "optionA": "  Rickets ",
            "optionB": "  Scurvy ",
            "optionC": "  Goitre ",
            "optionD": "  Growth retardation ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tWorldwide, iodine deficiency is the most common cause of thyroid enlargement and goiter. Within a goiter, nodules can develop. Patients with a large goiter may experience symptoms of choking, especially when lying down, and difficulty swallowing and breathing. ",
            "keyString": "575120s43m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Example of a single celled organism.",
            "optionA": "  Algae ",
            "optionB": "  Amoeba ",
            "optionC": "  Paramaecium ",
            "optionD": "  All of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAlgae, Amoeba and Paramaecium all are single celled organism. ",
            "keyString": "620006s43m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Chlamydomonas prefers water rich in ",
            "optionA": "  Ammonic compounds ",
            "optionB": "  Uric acid compounds ",
            "optionC": "  Sulphur compounds ",
            "optionD": "  Urea compounds ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tChlamydomonas is widely distributed in freshwater or damp soil. It is generally found in a habitat rich in ammonium salt. ",
            "keyString": "620092s43m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The number of pyrenoids in a cell of Spirogyra is ",
            "optionA": "  1 ",
            "optionB": "  2 ",
            "optionC": "  3-5 ",
            "optionD": "  Numerous ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe biological parameters, which included cell width, cell length, number of chloroplast spirals, and number of pyrenoids, ranged from 40 to 90 \u03bcm, 85 to 263 \u03bcm, 5.5 to 16 spiral, and 50 to 240 pyrenoids, respectively. ",
            "keyString": "620116s43m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Nuclear membrane is absent in",
            "optionA": "  Volvox ",
            "optionB": "  Penicillium ",
            "optionC": "  Agaricus ",
            "optionD": "  Nostoc ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPenicillium and Agaricus are fungi while Volvox is an alga. All three are eukaryotes thus have a membrane bound nucleus. Nostoc is a cyanobacterium, i.e., prokaryote, so it lacks true nucleus, thus nuclear membrane is absent. ",
            "keyString": "620138s43m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Microscopic organism which passively float on the surface of water is called",
            "optionA": "  Phytoplanktons ",
            "optionB": "  Zooplanktons ",
            "optionC": "  Both (a) and (b) both ",
            "optionD": "  None to these ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMicroscopic organism which passively float on the surface of water is called Zooplanktons and Phytoplanktons. ",
            "keyString": "620157s43m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The term biology is derived from the language",
            "optionA": "  French ",
            "optionB": "  Latin ",
            "optionC": "  Purthgali ",
            "optionD": "  Greek ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe word biology is derived from the greek words \"bios\" meaning life and \"logos\" meaning study and is defined as the science of life and living organisms. ",
            "keyString": "661474s43m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which structure is common to plant and animal cells?",
            "optionA": "  Centriole ",
            "optionB": "  Chloroplast ",
            "optionC": "  Central Vacuole ",
            "optionD": "  Mitochondria ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAnimal cells and plant cells share the common components of a nucleus, cytoplasm, mitochondria and a cell membrane. Plant cells have three extra components, a vacuole, chloroplast and a cell wall. ",
            "keyString": "661503s43m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which observation proves that a cell is a eukaryote?",
            "optionA": "  It contains DNA ",
            "optionB": "  It contains ribosomes ",
            "optionC": "  It has a cell membrane ",
            "optionD": "  It has DNA inside a nucleus ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA eukaryotic cell is a cell which exhibit membrane-bound organelles. They exhibit a well-defined membrane bound nucleus in which the DNA (deoxyribonucleic acid) resides it is the genetic material which is passed on from parents to their offsprings. ",
            "keyString": "661516s43m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Physical basis of life is",
            "optionA": "  Cytoplasm ",
            "optionB": "  Neucleoplasm ",
            "optionC": "  Protoplasm ",
            "optionD": "  Haloplasm ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAccording to Huxley the protoplasm is the physical basis of life. Inside the cell wall of living cell the living substance is known as protoplasm. The protoplasm is a thick fluid or jellylike substance. ",
            "keyString": "661528s43m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Where does cellular respiration take place in the cell?",
            "optionA": "  Cytoplasm ",
            "optionB": "  Mitochodria ",
            "optionC": "  Ribosomes ",
            "optionD": "  Chromosomes ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe enzymatic reactions of cellular respiration begin in the cytoplasm, but most of the reactions occur in the mitochondria. Cellular respiration occurs in the double-membrane organelle called the mitochondrion. The folds in the inner membrane are called cristae. ",
            "keyString": "661538s43m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of following is smallest gland of body?",
            "optionA": "  Liver ",
            "optionB": "  Thyroid ",
            "optionC": "  Pituitary ",
            "optionD": "  Slivary gland ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPituitary is smallest gland of body among the following. ",
            "keyString": "707345s43m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Deficiency of which minerals causes goitre?",
            "optionA": "  Magnesium ",
            "optionB": "  Calcium ",
            "optionC": "  Iodine ",
            "optionD": "  Sulphur ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDeficiency of iodine causes goitre. ",
            "keyString": "707375s43m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Chemical co-ordination in the body is brought out by",
            "optionA": "  Blood ",
            "optionB": "  Lymph ",
            "optionC": "  Enzymes ",
            "optionD": "  Hormones ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn vertebrates the chemical coordination is brought about by endocrine glands which secrete hormones.",
            "keyString": "707389s43m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The disease Goitre is caused in persons who do not have in their diet sufficient",
            "optionA": "  Calcium ",
            "optionB": "  Sodium ",
            "optionC": "  Iodine ",
            "optionD": "  Iron ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGoitre is caused in persons who do not have sufficient iodine in their diet. ",
            "keyString": "707401s43m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In case of a heart attack, a hormone is injected as an emergency measure, Which one is it?",
            "optionA": "  Thyroxine ",
            "optionB": "  Adrenaline ",
            "optionC": "  Heparin ",
            "optionD": "  Insulin ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn the case of a heart attack, the hormone that injected as an emergency measure is Adrenaline. An adrenaline shot can increase the chance that the heart will regain a normal rhythm or restart your heart after a cardiac arrest by directing the flow of blood to the heart. ",
            "keyString": "707411s43m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which parts of the heart receive blood from the lungs?",
            "optionA": "  Right ventricle ",
            "optionB": "  Left atrium ",
            "optionC": "  Left ventricle ",
            "optionD": "  Right atrium ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe left atrium receives oxygen-rich blood from the lungs and pumps it to the left ventricle through the mitral valve. The left ventricle pumps the oxygen-rich blood through the aortic valve out to the rest of the body. ",
            "keyString": "748344s43m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The universal donor belongs to blood group",
            "optionA": "  A ",
            "optionB": "  B ",
            "optionC": "  AB ",
            "optionD": "  O ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe universal donor belongs to blood group O. ",
            "keyString": "748459s43m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Person having blood group 'B' can donate the blood to person having blood group",
            "optionA": "  A and O ",
            "optionB": "  B and O ",
            "optionC": "  A and AB ",
            "optionD": "  B and AB ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPerson having blood group 'B' can donate the blood to person having blood group B and AB. ",
            "keyString": "748482s43m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Scientist who discovered blood groups was",
            "optionA": "  Krebs ",
            "optionB": "  Pavlov ",
            "optionC": "  Karl Landsteiner ",
            "optionD": "  Darwin ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tKarl Landsteiner, was an Austrian biologist, physician, and immunologist. He distinguished the main blood groups in 1900, having developed the modern system of classification of blood groups. ",
            "keyString": "748506s43m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Where do arteries carry blood?",
            "optionA": "  Heart ",
            "optionB": "  Lungs ",
            "optionC": "  Tissues ",
            "optionD": "  Brain ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArteries carry blood away from the heart. Pulmonary arteries transport blood that has a low oxygen content from the right ventricle to the lungs. Systemic arteries transport oxygenated blood from the left ventricle to the body tissues. ",
            "keyString": "748523s43m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Bile produced by",
            "optionA": "  Liver ",
            "optionB": "  Stomach ",
            "optionC": "  Pancrease ",
            "optionD": "  Dudeneum ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBile is a fluid that is made and released by the liver and stored in the gallbladder. Bile helps with digestion. It breaks down fats into fatty acids, which can be taken into the body by the digestive tract. ",
            "keyString": "793498s43m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Digestion starts in man from",
            "optionA": "  Rectum ",
            "optionB": "  Stomach ",
            "optionC": "  Mouth ",
            "optionD": "  Intestine ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAn adult's digestive tract is about 30 feet (about 9 meters) long. Digestion begins in the mouth, well before food reaches the stomach. When we see, smell, taste, or even imagine a tasty meal, our salivary glands in front of the ear, under the tongue, and near the lower jaw begin making saliva (spit). ",
            "keyString": "793528s43m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Where does digestion of protein begins?",
            "optionA": "  Mouth ",
            "optionB": "  Pharynx ",
            "optionC": "  Stomach ",
            "optionD": "  Liver ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMechanical digestion of protein begins in the mouth and continues in the stomach and small intestine. Chemical digestion of protein begins in the stomach and ends in the small intestine. The body recycles amino acids to make more proteins. ",
            "keyString": "793542s43m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "After digestion protein is converted into",
            "optionA": "  Fat ",
            "optionB": "  Glucose ",
            "optionC": "  Amino acid ",
            "optionD": "  Fractose ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tWhen you eat food the body's digestive system breaks down the protein into the individual amino acids, which are absorbed and used by cells to build other proteins and a few other macromolecules, such as DNA. ",
            "keyString": "793554s43m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Digestion of starch in mouth takes place by",
            "optionA": "  Amylase ",
            "optionB": "  Ptyline ",
            "optionC": "  Pepsin ",
            "optionD": "  Lipase ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDigestion of starch in mouth takes place by Ptyline. ",
            "keyString": "793565s43m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Out of 900 reported species of living gymnosperms, conifers are represented by about 500 species, About 2,50,000 species of angiosperms (flowering plants) have also been reported in the world. The vast and dominant woodlands in Europe, Asia, North America and mountains such as Himalayas are wooded with",
            "optionA": "  all gymnosperms, except conifers ",
            "optionB": "  only angiosperms ",
            "optionC": "  only conifers ",
            "optionD": "  angiosperms and all gymnosperms except conifers ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOut of 900 reported species of living gymnosperms, conifers are represented by about 500 species, About 2,50,000 species of angiosperms (flowering plants) have also been reported in the world. The vast and dominant woodlands in Europe, Asia, North America and mountains such as Himalayas are wooded with only conifers. ",
            "keyString": "839130s43m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "One of the following is not a function of bones.",
            "optionA": "  Place for muscle attachment ",
            "optionB": "  Protection of vital organs ",
            "optionC": "  Secretion of hormones for calcium regulation in blood and bones ",
            "optionD": "  Production of blood corpuscles ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSecretion of hormones for calcium regulation in blood and bones is not a function of a bone. ",
            "keyString": "839254s43m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Plants absorb most part of water needed by them through their",
            "optionA": "  embryonic zone ",
            "optionB": "  growing point ",
            "optionC": "  root hairs ",
            "optionD": "  zone of elongation ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRoot hair cells are specialized epidermal cells that greatly increase the surface area of roots. The function of root hairs is to collect water and mineral nutrients present in the soil and take this solution up through the roots to the rest of the plant. ",
            "keyString": "839290s43m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Photo-oxidation is",
            "optionA": "  photorespiration ",
            "optionB": "  photolysis ",
            "optionC": "  light and oxygen induced breakdown ",
            "optionD": "  All of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPhoto-oxidation involves all of the above process. ",
            "keyString": "839318s43m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Process of cell division can take place by",
            "optionA": "  heterosis ",
            "optionB": "  fusion ",
            "optionC": "  mitosis ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMitosis is a process of nuclear division in eukaryotic cells that occurs when a parent cell divides to produce two identical daughter cells. During cell division, mitosis refers specifically to the separation of the duplicated genetic material carried in the nucleus. ",
            "keyString": "839355s43m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is a mixed gland?",
            "optionA": "  Pituitary ",
            "optionB": "  Adrenal ",
            "optionC": "  Pancreas ",
            "optionD": "  Ovary ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPancreas is a mixed gland having both endocrine and exocrine functions. Endocrine portion secretes hormones, insulin and glucagon while the exocrine portion secretes an alkaline pancreatic juice containing enzymes and bicarbonate. ",
            "keyString": "887433s43m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Female reproductive hormones is",
            "optionA": "  Estrogen ",
            "optionB": "  Progestron ",
            "optionC": "  Relaxin ",
            "optionD": "  All of these ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tReproductive hormones are usually made in the ovaries (in females) and testes (in males). Female reproductive hormones include estrogen and progesterone. They help develop and maintain female sex characteristics and play an important role in the menstrual cycle, fertility, and pregnancy. ",
            "keyString": "887704s43m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is an endocrine gland?",
            "optionA": "  Mammary glands ",
            "optionB": "  Apocrine sweat glands ",
            "optionC": "  Reproductive glands ",
            "optionD": "  Salivary glands ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tReproductive glands is an endocrine gland. ",
            "keyString": "887929s43m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Growth hormone is secreted from",
            "optionA": "  Thyroid ",
            "optionB": "  Adrenal ",
            "optionC": "  Gonads ",
            "optionD": "  Pituitary ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGrowth hormone (GH) is an ancestral hormone secreted episodically from somatotroph cells in the anterior pituitary. ",
            "keyString": "888114s43m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Most important gland of human body is",
            "optionA": "  Thyroid ",
            "optionB": "  Pituitary ",
            "optionC": "  Pancreas ",
            "optionD": "  Liver ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe pituitary gland is a small pea-sized gland that plays a major role in regulating vital body functions and general wellbeing. It is referred to as the body's 'master gland' because it controls the activity of most other hormone-secreting glands. ",
            "keyString": "888283s43m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Through nitrogen fixation process nitrogen in the atmosphere is converted into",
            "optionA": "  Ammonium  ",
            "optionB": "  Hydroxide  ",
            "optionC": "  Nitrate  ",
            "optionD": "  Chlorite  ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFixation converts nitrogen in the atmosphere into ammonium that plants can absorb through their root systems. A small amount of nitrogen can be fixed when lightning provides the energy needed for N2 to react with oxygen, producing nitrogen oxide, NO, and nitrogen dioxide, NO2. ",
            "keyString": "938310s43m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In plants, which cells carry out photosynthesis?",
            "optionA": "  Chlorenchymatous ",
            "optionB": "  Sclerenchymatous ",
            "optionC": "  Paranchymatous ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn plants, Chlorenchymatous carry out photosynthesis. ",
            "keyString": "938379s43m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Part of the plant where photosynthesis generally occurs",
            "optionA": "  Roots ",
            "optionB": "  Leaves ",
            "optionC": "  Branches ",
            "optionD": "  Flowers ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn plants, the process of photosynthesis takes place in the mesophyll of the leaves, inside the chloroplasts. Chloroplasts contain disc-shaped structures called thylakoids, which contain the pigment chlorophyll. ",
            "keyString": "938431s43m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The energy stored in photosynthesis is obtained from",
            "optionA": "  Sunlight ",
            "optionB": "  Oxidation of glucose ",
            "optionC": "  Breakdown of proteins ",
            "optionD": "  Breakdown of glucose ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe energy stored in photosynthesis is obtained from sunlight. ",
            "keyString": "938480s43m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Maximum fixation of solar energy is done by",
            "optionA": "  Fungi ",
            "optionB": "  Protozoa ",
            "optionC": "  Bacteria ",
            "optionD": "  Green plants ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe maximum 20% of the input of solar energy falling on leaves is converted into chemical energy by green plants. Green plants utilize solar energy and synthesize sugar from CO2 and water through the process of photosynthesis. However, they are able to utilize only 3% of the light energy that strikes on their green parts; the rest is dissipated as heat. ",
            "keyString": "938528s43m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Pickles, candies, jams and breads are preserved by the much of adding ",
            "optionA": "  Preservattives ",
            "optionB": "  Enzymes ",
            "optionC": "  Minerals ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThere are many chemical preservatives used in food industry. Sodium benzoate is generally used is ketchups, pickles, jams etc. ",
            "keyString": "985033s43m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which type of bacteria get their food from dead organic matter?",
            "optionA": "  Parasitic ",
            "optionB": "  Autotrophic ",
            "optionC": "  Saprophytic ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSaprophytic bacteria get their food from dead organic matter. ",
            "keyString": "985148s43m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Heterocysts, specialised for nitrogen fixation, occur in certain",
            "optionA": "  Red brown algae ",
            "optionB": "  Blue green algae ",
            "optionC": "  Ferns ",
            "optionD": "  Mosses ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tHeterocysts, specialised for nitrogen fixation, occur in certain Blue green algae. ",
            "keyString": "985179s43m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The number pyrenoids in Chlamydomonas is ",
            "optionA": "  1 ",
            "optionB": "  2 ",
            "optionC": "  3 ",
            "optionD": "  4 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe number pyrenoids in Chlamydomonas is 1. ",
            "keyString": "985215s43m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Commercial agar is obtained from",
            "optionA": "  Chlorella ",
            "optionB": "  Gracilaria ",
            "optionC": "  Parphyro ",
            "optionD": "  Volvox ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe gelling agent in agar is an unbranched polysaccharide obtained from the cell walls of some species of red algae, primarily from tengusa (Gelidiaceae) and ogonori (Gracilaria). For commercial purposes, it is derived primarily from ogonori. ",
            "keyString": "985243s43m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "It is an oxygen carrying protein of red colour concentrated in red blood cells.",
            "optionA": "  Insulin ",
            "optionB": "  Haemoglobin ",
            "optionC": "  Gastrin ",
            "optionD": "  Actin ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tHaemoglobin is an oxygen carrying protein of red colour concentrated in red blood cells. ",
            "keyString": "28819s44m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which blood group is a universal recipient?",
            "optionA": "  A ",
            "optionB": "  B ",
            "optionC": "  AB ",
            "optionD": "  O ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tABis a universal recipient. ",
            "keyString": "28848s44m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The largest artery in human body is",
            "optionA": "  Aorta ",
            "optionB": "  Capillary ",
            "optionC": "  Vena cava ",
            "optionD": "  Pulmonary vein ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe largest artery in the body is the aorta, which is connected to the heart and extends down into the abdomen. ",
            "keyString": "28862s44m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Number of chamber found in human heart is",
            "optionA": "  2 ",
            "optionB": "  3 ",
            "optionC": "  4 ",
            "optionD": "  5 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe heart consists of four chambers in which blood flows. Blood enters the right atrium and passes through the right ventricle. The right ventricle pumps the blood to the lungs where it becomes oxygenated. The oxygenated blood is brought back to the heart by the pulmonary veins which enter the left atrium. ",
            "keyString": "28874s44m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Blood pressure is the pressure exerted on the wall of",
            "optionA": "  Heart ",
            "optionB": "  Vein ",
            "optionC": "  Artery ",
            "optionD": "  Cell ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBlood pressure is the pressure that blood exerts on the wall of the blood vessels. This pressure originates in the contraction of the heart, which forces blood out of the heart and into the blood vessels. Two mechanisms take place in the heart: diastole and systole. ",
            "keyString": "28885s44m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Longest bone found in man is",
            "optionA": "  Stapes ",
            "optionB": "  Fibula ",
            "optionC": "  Tibia ",
            "optionD": "  Femur ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe femur is one of the most researched bones in the human anatomy and forensic medicine. ",
            "keyString": "75030s44m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What is the total number of bones in the human body?",
            "optionA": "  206 ",
            "optionB": "  103 ",
            "optionC": "  309 ",
            "optionD": "  412 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe adult human body has 206 bones. ",
            "keyString": "75067s44m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Number of bones found in skull is",
            "optionA": "  8 ",
            "optionB": "  30 ",
            "optionC": "  32 ",
            "optionD": "  34 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNumber of bones found in skull is 8. ",
            "keyString": "75084s44m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "How many pairs of ribs are there in human body?",
            "optionA": "  10 ",
            "optionB": "  11 ",
            "optionC": "  12 ",
            "optionD": "  13 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn humans there are normally 12 pairs of ribs. The first seven pairs are attached directly to the sternum by costal cartilages and are called true ribs.",
            "keyString": "75097s44m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Total number of bone found in man is",
            "optionA": "  212 ",
            "optionB": "  206 ",
            "optionC": "  202 ",
            "optionD": "  200 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTotal number of bone found in man is 206. ",
            "keyString": "75110s44m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What do eukaryotic cells have that prokaryotic cells do not?",
            "optionA": "  Nucleus ",
            "optionB": "  Cytoplasm ",
            "optionC": "  Ribosomes ",
            "optionD": "  DNA ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe primary distinction between these two types of organisms is that eukaryotic cells have a membrane-bound nucleus and prokaryotic cells do not. The nucleus is where eukaryotes store their genetic information. ",
            "keyString": "167807s44m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The sea horse belongs to the class of",
            "optionA": "  Fishes ",
            "optionB": "  Mammals ",
            "optionC": "  Reptiles ",
            "optionD": "  Mollusc ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe sea horse belongs to the class of fishes. ",
            "keyString": "167835s44m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "They are considered to be the most primitive and are surely the first of the vertebrates.",
            "optionA": "  Frogs ",
            "optionB": "  Reptiles ",
            "optionC": "  Amphibinas ",
            "optionD": "  Jawless fishes ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tJawless fishes are considered to be the most primitive and are surely the first of the vertebrates. ",
            "keyString": "167848s44m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "They are extremely diverse group of organisms.",
            "optionA": "  Mosses ",
            "optionB": "  Algae ",
            "optionC": "  Angiosperms ",
            "optionD": "  Fungi ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFungi are extremely diverse group of organisms. ",
            "keyString": "167859s44m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In Animal Kingdom classification, which of the following is not a Phylum?",
            "optionA": "  Mollusca ",
            "optionB": "  Chordata ",
            "optionC": "  Coelomates ",
            "optionD": "  Anneldia ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn Animal Kingdom classification, coelomates is not a phylum. ",
            "keyString": "167870s44m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which is a homologous chromosome pair?",
            "optionA": "  Tetrad ",
            "optionB": "  Gamate ",
            "optionC": "  Chromatid ",
            "optionD": "  Zygote ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTetrad is a homologous chromosome pair. ",
            "keyString": "202773s44m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "A multicellular organism grows by ________ .",
            "optionA": "  Cell addition ",
            "optionB": "  Cell explosion ",
            "optionC": "  Cell implosion ",
            "optionD": "  Cell division ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAll multicellular organisms use cell division for growth and the maintenance and repair of cells and tissues. Single-celled organisms use cell division as their method of reproduction. ",
            "keyString": "202801s44m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "At anaphase stage of mitosis in plant cells, interzonal of the spindle fibres gets transformed into ",
            "optionA": "  Equatorial plate ",
            "optionB": "  Nucleoplast ",
            "optionC": "  Phragmoplast ",
            "optionD": "  Chloroplast ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAt anaphase stage of mitosis in plant cells, interzonal of the spindle fibres gets transformed into Phragmoplast. ",
            "keyString": "202814s44m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "During which stage of mitosis does cytokinesis usually occur in animals?",
            "optionA": "  Prophase ",
            "optionB": "  Metaphase ",
            "optionC": "  Anaphase ",
            "optionD": "  Telophase ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDuring telophase cytokinesis usually occur in animals. ",
            "keyString": "202825s44m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "During the metaphase and anaphase stages of cell division, each chromosome comprises of two unseparated replicas known as the",
            "optionA": "  Chiasmata ",
            "optionB": "  Plastids ",
            "optionC": "  Chromatids ",
            "optionD": "  Tetrads ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDuring the metaphase and anaphase stages of cell division, each chromosome comprises of two unseparated replicas known as the chromatids. ",
            "keyString": "202835s44m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Karl Landsteiner discovered",
            "optionA": "  Blood corpuscles ",
            "optionB": "  Blood groups ",
            "optionC": "  Blood vessels ",
            "optionD": "  Proteins in Blood ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tKarl Landsteiner discovered blood groups. ",
            "keyString": "238890s44m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Systolic and diastolic pressure in a healthy man is",
            "optionA": "  120 mm and 80 mm ",
            "optionB": "  201 mm and 110 mm ",
            "optionC": "  90 mm and 60 mm ",
            "optionD": "  85 mm and 55 mm ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFor a normal reading, your blood pressure needs to show a top number (systolic pressure) that's between 90 and less than 120 and a bottom number (diastolic pressure) that's between 60 and less than 80. ",
            "keyString": "238918s44m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Red blood corpuscles is produced into",
            "optionA": "  Spleen ",
            "optionB": "  Kidney ",
            "optionC": "  Liver ",
            "optionD": "  Bone marrow ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRed blood cells are formed in the red bone marrow of bones. Stem cells in the red bone marrow called hemocytoblasts give rise to all of the formed elements in blood. ",
            "keyString": "238931s44m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Oxygenated blood flows through which vessel?",
            "optionA": "  Pulmonary Veins ",
            "optionB": "  Pulmonary Arteries ",
            "optionC": "  Both A & B ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe oxygenated blood is brought back to the heart by the pulmonary veins which enter the left atrium. From the left atrium blood flows into the left ventricle. The left ventricle pumps the blood to the aorta which will distribute the oxygenated blood to all parts of the body. ",
            "keyString": "238941s44m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following cells produce antibodies?",
            "optionA": "  Plasma cells ",
            "optionB": "  Monocytes ",
            "optionC": "  Mast cells ",
            "optionD": "  Neutrophils ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPlasma cells produce antibodies. ",
            "keyString": "238952s44m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Main function of white blood corpuscles is",
            "optionA": "  Transport of CO2 ",
            "optionB": "  Transport of oxygen ",
            "optionC": "  To produce immune system of body ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThey protect you against illness and disease. Think of white blood cells as your immunity cells. In a sense, they are always at war. They flow through your bloodstream to fight viruses, bacteria, and other foreign invaders that threaten your health. ",
            "keyString": "275667s44m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What is the average Life span of RBC?",
            "optionA": "  120 days ",
            "optionB": "  99 days ",
            "optionC": "  101 days ",
            "optionD": "  111 days ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe average Life span of RBC is 120 days. ",
            "keyString": "275698s44m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Red blood corpuscles is also known as",
            "optionA": "  Erythrocytes ",
            "optionB": "  Leucocytes ",
            "optionC": "  Thrombocytes ",
            "optionD": "  Esinophils ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRed blood cell, also called erythrocyte, cellular component of blood, millions of which in the circulation of vertebrates give the blood its characteristic colour and carry oxygen from the lungs to the tissues. ",
            "keyString": "275711s44m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Blood group which have no antigen",
            "optionA": "  A ",
            "optionB": "  B ",
            "optionC": "  AB ",
            "optionD": "  O ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBlood group O \u2013 has no antigens, but both anti-A and anti-B antibodies in the plasma. blood group AB \u2013 has both A and B antigens, but no antibodies. ",
            "keyString": "275723s44m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The normal blood pressure in human beings is",
            "optionA": "  80/120 ",
            "optionB": "  120/80 ",
            "optionC": "  80/110 ",
            "optionD": "  110/90 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNormal blood pressure: 90/60 to under 120/80 mm Hg in human beings. ",
            "keyString": "275734s44m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which is the cause of malaria infection?",
            "optionA": "  Bacteria ",
            "optionB": "  Plasmodium ",
            "optionC": "  Algae ",
            "optionD": "  Viruses ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMalaria is caused by the Plasmodium parasite. The parasite can be spread to humans through the bites of infected mosquitoes. ",
            "keyString": "311700s44m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In human beings influenza is caused by",
            "optionA": "  Bacteria ",
            "optionB": "  Viruses ",
            "optionC": "  Fungi ",
            "optionD": "  Algae ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tInfluenza, commonly known as \"the flu\", is an infectious disease caused by an influenza virus. Symptoms can be mild to severe. ",
            "keyString": "311728s44m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Asthma is caused due to",
            "optionA": "  Infection of trachea ",
            "optionB": "  Infection of lung ",
            "optionC": "  Bleeding into pleural cavity ",
            "optionD": "  Spasm in bronchial muscles ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAsthma is caused due to inflammation of lungs and spasm in bronchial muscles. The peculiar symptoms of the disease are coughing, chest tightness, and shortness of breath. It is mainly caused due to environmental and genetic factor. ",
            "keyString": "311742s44m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Cancer is caused by",
            "optionA": "  Loss of immunity of cells ",
            "optionB": "  Uncontrolled meiosis ",
            "optionC": "  Uncontrolled mitosis ",
            "optionD": "  Rupturing of cells ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tWhen cells of the body at a particular site start to grow out of control, they may become cancerous. ",
            "keyString": "311754s44m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Sickle-cell anemia is a disease caused due to the abnormality in",
            "optionA": "  White blood cell ",
            "optionB": "  Red blood cell ",
            "optionC": "  Thrombocytes ",
            "optionD": "  Blood plasma composition ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSickle cell anemia is caused by a mutation in the gene that tells your body to make the iron-rich compound that makes blood red and enables red blood cells to carry oxygen from your lungs throughout your body (hemoglobin). ",
            "keyString": "311765s44m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Mitochondria are also known as",
            "optionA": "  Store house of the cell ",
            "optionB": "  Power house of the cell ",
            "optionC": "  Factory of protein synthesis ",
            "optionD": "  Factory of ribosomes synthesis ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMitochondria are often called the \u201cpowerhouses\u201d or \u201cenergy factories\u201d of a cell because they are responsible for making adenosine triphosphate (ATP), the cell's main energy-carrying molecule.",
            "keyString": "347534s44m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which is the basic structural as well as functional unit for all organisms?",
            "optionA": "  Tissue ",
            "optionB": "  Cell ",
            "optionC": "  Gland ",
            "optionD": "  Atom ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn all life forms, including bacteria, plants, animals, and humans, the cell was defined as the most basic structural and functional unit. ",
            "keyString": "347562s44m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which organelles are involved in the manufacture and supply of energy to the cell?",
            "optionA": "  Ribosomes ",
            "optionB": "  Mitochondria ",
            "optionC": "  Golgi Bodies ",
            "optionD": "  Vacuoles ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCells also contain mitochondria and peroxisomes, which are the organelles responsible for producing the cell's energy supply and detoxifying certain chemicals, respectively. Biochemical reactions within mitochondria transform energy-carrying molecules into the usable form of cellular energy known as ATP. ",
            "keyString": "347575s44m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which statement is one component of the cell theory?",
            "optionA": "  DNA is the basis of genetic transfer ",
            "optionB": "  All living cells arise from pre-existing cells ",
            "optionC": "  All cells are composed of same organelles ",
            "optionD": "  Tissues are formed from combinations of cells ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe three parts of the cell theory are as follows: (1) All living things are made up of cells, (2) Cells are the smallest units (or most basic building blocks) of life, and (3) All cells come from pre-existing cells through the process of cell division. ",
            "keyString": "347586s44m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Do plant cells have Mitochondria?",
            "optionA": "  Yes ",
            "optionB": "  No ",
            "optionC": "  Can't be determined ",
            "optionD": "  None ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBoth animal and plant cells have mitochondria, but only plant cells have chloroplasts. Plants don't get their sugar from eating food, so they need to make sugar from sunlight. This process (photosynthesis) takes place in the chloroplast. ",
            "keyString": "347596s44m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Cells which takes part in secondary growth are named as",
            "optionA": "  Phloem ",
            "optionB": "  Xylem ",
            "optionC": "  Cambium ",
            "optionD": "  Medullary ray ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCambium, in plants, is a layer of actively dividing cells between xylem (wood) and phloem (bast) tissues.It is responsible for the secondary growth of stems and roots (secondary growth occurs after the first season and results in an increase in thickness). Hence, Cells which takes part in secondary growth are named as Cambium. So, the correct answer is 'Cambium'. ",
            "keyString": "382706s44m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Bones join with muscles with the help of",
            "optionA": "  Ligament ",
            "optionB": "  Tendon ",
            "optionC": "  Cartilage ",
            "optionD": "  Small muscles ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBones join with muscles with the help of tendon. ",
            "keyString": "382735s44m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which type of permanent tissue helps the aquatic plants to float?",
            "optionA": "  Aerenchyma ",
            "optionB": "  Collenchyma ",
            "optionC": "  Sclerenchyma ",
            "optionD": "  No option is correct ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe tissue which allows aquatic plants to float is Aerenchyma. Basically aerenchyma is parenchyma tissue in aquatic plants. The cells of aerenchyma make a network which has wide air spaces or air cavities for gaseous exchange. These air cavities make the plant light and buoyant and hence, plants can float easily in water.",
            "keyString": "382748s44m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The xylem in plants are responsible for:",
            "optionA": "  Transport of water ",
            "optionB": "  Transport of food ",
            "optionC": "  Transport of amino acids ",
            "optionD": "  Transport of oxygen ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tXylem is one of the two types of transport tissue in vascular plants, phloem being the other. The basic function of xylem is to transport water from roots to stems and leaves, but it also transports nutrients. ",
            "keyString": "382759s44m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Most abundant tissue in the body",
            "optionA": "  Connective ",
            "optionB": "  Nervous ",
            "optionC": "  Muscular ",
            "optionD": "  Epithelial ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tConnective tissue is the most abundant tissue type in the body. In general, connective tissue consists of cells and an extracellular matrix. ",
            "keyString": "382770s44m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is the largest phylum in the animal kingdom in respect of number of species?",
            "optionA": "  Annalida ",
            "optionB": "  Platyhelminthes ",
            "optionC": "  Chordata ",
            "optionD": "  Arthropoda ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArthropoda is by far the largest phylum in the animal kingdom. It includes insects, lobsters, mites, crabs etc. A recent estimate of the number of arthropods on Earth today is 3.7 million species. ",
            "keyString": "418481s44m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "It is stiff rod of special cells surrounded by connective tissue present in the mid-dorsal region and appears in the embryos of all chordates.",
            "optionA": "  Placenta ",
            "optionB": "  Notochord ",
            "optionC": "  Cranianta ",
            "optionD": "  Ligule ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNotochord is stiff rod of special cells surrounded by connective tissue present in the mid-dorsal region and appears in the embryos of all chordates. ",
            "keyString": "418510s44m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is cold blooded?",
            "optionA": "  Fish ",
            "optionB": "  Frog ",
            "optionC": "  Lizard ",
            "optionD": "  All of these ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFish, frog and lizard all are cold blooded. ",
            "keyString": "418523s44m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Higher vascular plants are also called",
            "optionA": "  Flowering plants ",
            "optionB": "  Ferns ",
            "optionC": "  Seed plants ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe vascular plants, or tracheophytes, are plants that have specialized tissues for conducting water, minerals, and photosynthetic products through the plant. They include the ferns, clubmosses, horsetails, flowering plants, conifers and other gymnosperms. They are often called the higher plants or the seed plants. ",
            "keyString": "418534s44m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "A genus can best be defined as",
            "optionA": "  A taxon composed of one or more species and a classification level lying below family ",
            "optionB": "  A taxon composed of families ",
            "optionC": "  The most specific taxon ",
            "optionD": "  A taxon comprised of classes ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA genus can best be defined as a taxon composed of one or more species and a classification level lying below family. ",
            "keyString": "418545s44m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Algae and fungi are collectively known as",
            "optionA": "  Thallophytes  ",
            "optionB": "  Pteridophytes  ",
            "optionC": "  Bryophytes  ",
            "optionD": "  Spermatophytes  ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAlgae and fungi are collectively known as thallophytes. ",
            "keyString": "454295s44m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is true about bryophytes?",
            "optionA": "  They are thalloid  ",
            "optionB": "  They contain chloroplast  ",
            "optionC": "  They posses archegonia  ",
            "optionD": "  All of these  ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAll of these is true about bryophytes. ",
            "keyString": "454324s44m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In birds, some of the vertebrae are fused to form",
            "optionA": "  Keel  ",
            "optionB": "  Furcula  ",
            "optionC": "  Syncytium  ",
            "optionD": "  Synsacrum  ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSome posterior thoracic vertebrae, the lumbar, sacral and a few anterior caudal vertebrae are fused to form a complex bone called synsacrum. The innominate bones are fused with the synsacrum to a greater or lesser extent, according to species, forming an avian pelvis. ",
            "keyString": "454338s44m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "They play a central role in the making of dairy products such as butter, cheese, yogurt etc.",
            "optionA": "  Viruses ",
            "optionB": "  Fungi ",
            "optionC": "  Bacteria ",
            "optionD": "  Algae ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBacteria play a central role in the making of dairy products such as butter, cheese, yogurt etc. ",
            "keyString": "454349s44m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "There are certain bacteria which can fix atmospheric gas named",
            "optionA": "  Oxygen ",
            "optionB": "  Nitrogen ",
            "optionC": "  Hydrogen ",
            "optionD": "  Carbon dioxide ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNitrogen-fixing bacteria are prokaryotic microorganisms that are capable of transforming nitrogen gas from the atmosphere into \u201cfixed nitrogen\u201d compounds, such as ammonia, that are usable by plants. Read about nitrogen fixation. ",
            "keyString": "454361s44m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Biogeographical regions are also called",
            "optionA": "  Zones  ",
            "optionB": "  Epoch  ",
            "optionC": "  Realms  ",
            "optionD": "  Era  ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA biogeographic realm or ecozone is the broadest biogeographic division of Earth's land surface, based on distributional patterns of terrestrial organisms. ",
            "keyString": "490464s44m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Hepatitis virus destroys the cells and may cause the disease",
            "optionA": "  Jaundice ",
            "optionB": "  Malaria ",
            "optionC": "  Typhoid ",
            "optionD": "  Elephantiasis ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tHepatitis virus destroys the cells and may cause the disease - jaundice. ",
            "keyString": "490493s44m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "It is disease which used to exist in the past in most countries of old world.",
            "optionA": "  Small pox ",
            "optionB": "  Malaria ",
            "optionC": "  Measles ",
            "optionD": "  Cholera ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMalaria used to exist in the past in most countries of old world. ",
            "keyString": "490506s44m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Sleeping sickness in man is caused by the organism ",
            "optionA": "  Plasmodium ",
            "optionB": "  Entamoeba ",
            "optionC": "  Giardia ",
            "optionD": "  Trypanosoma ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tHuman African trypanosomiasis, also known as sleeping sickness, is a vector-borne parasitic disease. It is caused by infection with protozoan parasites belonging to the genus Trypanosoma. ",
            "keyString": "490517s44m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The harmful poisonous substances produced by bacteria are called",
            "optionA": "  Toxins ",
            "optionB": "  Antitioxins ",
            "optionC": "  Antibiotic ",
            "optionD": "  Aflatoxins ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tToxins are poisonous substances produced within living cells or organisms and can include various classes of small molecules or proteins that cause disease on contact. ",
            "keyString": "490527s44m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The main function of Henle's loop is",
            "optionA": "  Passage of urine  ",
            "optionB": "  Filtration of blood  ",
            "optionC": "  Formation of urine  ",
            "optionD": "  Conservation of water  ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe principal function of the loop of Henle is in the recovery of water and sodium chloride from urine. ",
            "keyString": "525462s44m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The ultimate cause of water movement in a plant stem against gravity is",
            "optionA": "  Osmosis ",
            "optionB": "  Photosynthesis ",
            "optionC": "  Transpiration ",
            "optionD": "  Diffusion ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe ultimate cause of water movement in a plant stem against gravity is transpiration. ",
            "keyString": "525499s44m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "They protect plants from water loss and abrasive damage.",
            "optionA": "  Leaves ",
            "optionB": "  Waxes ",
            "optionC": "  Minerals ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tWaxes protect plants from water loss and abrasive damage. ",
            "keyString": "525513s44m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The suitable conditions in which the rate of evaporation occurs more fastly are",
            "optionA": "  Low speed of wind ",
            "optionB": "  High humidity ",
            "optionC": "  Low humidity and high temperature ",
            "optionD": "  Excess amount of water in the soil ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe suitable conditions in which the rate of evaporation occurs more fastly are low humidity and high temperature. ",
            "keyString": "525525s44m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The device to measure transpiration in plants is",
            "optionA": "  Hygrometer ",
            "optionB": "  Crescometer ",
            "optionC": "  Potometer ",
            "optionD": "  Clinometer ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA potometer, sometimes known as transpirometer, is a device used for measuring the rate of water uptake of a leafy shoot which is almost equal to the water lost through transpiration. ",
            "keyString": "525536s44m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Study of nose and alfactory organs is called",
            "optionA": "  Radiology ",
            "optionB": "  Rhinology ",
            "optionC": "  Radiography ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tStudy of nose and alfactory organs is called Rhinology. ",
            "keyString": "560069s44m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The size of the pupil is controlled by the",
            "optionA": "  Retina ",
            "optionB": "  Iris ",
            "optionC": "  Cornea ",
            "optionD": "  Lens ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe size of the pupil is controlled by the activities of two muscles: the circumferential sphincter muscle found in the margin of the iris, innervated by the parasympathetic nervous system: and the iris dilator muscle, running radially from the iris root to the peripheral border of the sphincter. ",
            "keyString": "560096s44m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Damage to hearing is caused by sounds which exceed",
            "optionA": "  70 decibles ",
            "optionB": "  80 decibles ",
            "optionC": "  100 decibles ",
            "optionD": "  120 decibles ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNoise is a level of sound beyond the capacity of ears. Normal level of sound for conversation is 60 decibels and lawn mower is 90 decibels that can not harm the ears but very high levels of noise (at or above 120 decibels) exposure can leads to hearing loss. Noise-induced hearing loss is irreversible, the main form of treatment is prevention.",
            "keyString": "560109s44m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Myopia is connected with",
            "optionA": "  Teeth ",
            "optionB": "  Eyes ",
            "optionC": "  Lungs ",
            "optionD": "  Skin ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMyopia is connected with eyes. ",
            "keyString": "560119s44m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Human beings hearing range is ________",
            "optionA": "  50 to 50,000 Hz ",
            "optionB": "  40 to 40,000 Hz ",
            "optionC": "  30 to 30,000 Hz ",
            "optionD": "  20 to 20,000 Hz ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tHuman beings hearing range is 20 to 20,000 Hz. ",
            "keyString": "560129s44m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Of the following, which is the most fundamental generalization in biology?",
            "optionA": "  Microbiology ",
            "optionB": "  Microscope ",
            "optionC": "  Cell theory ",
            "optionD": "  Discovery of Cell ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCell theory is the most fundamental generalization in biology. ",
            "keyString": "596336s44m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Where does protein synthesis take place?",
            "optionA": "  Nucleus ",
            "optionB": "  Ribosomes ",
            "optionC": "  On the cell wall ",
            "optionD": "  All of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRibosomes are the sites in a cell in which protein synthesis takes place. Cells have many ribosomes, and the exact number depends on how active a particular cell is in synthesizing proteins. ",
            "keyString": "596369s44m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Membrane bound pigment containing bodies present in the cells are called as",
            "optionA": "  Chloroplasts ",
            "optionB": "  Plasmids ",
            "optionC": "  Plastids ",
            "optionD": "  Lipids ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe plastid is a membrane-bound organelle found in the cells of plants, algae, and some other eukaryotic organisms. ",
            "keyString": "596385s44m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Lysosome is formed from which of the following cell organelles?",
            "optionA": "  Nucleus ",
            "optionB": "  Endoplasmic reticulum ",
            "optionC": "  Golgi bodies ",
            "optionD": "  Ribosomes ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tLysosomes originate by budding off from the membrane of the trans-Golgi network, a region of the Golgi complex responsible for sorting newly synthesized proteins, which may be designated for use in lysosomes, endosomes, or the plasma membrane. ",
            "keyString": "596398s44m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In the cell of animals, some microorganisms and lower plants contain",
            "optionA": "  One centriole ",
            "optionB": "  Two centriole ",
            "optionC": "  Three centriole ",
            "optionD": "  Four centriole ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn the cell of animals, some microorganisms and lower plants contain two centriole. ",
            "keyString": "596410s44m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Such plants which are adapted to survival under conditions a limited supply of water in its habitat are known as",
            "optionA": "  Hydrophytes ",
            "optionB": "  Saprophytes ",
            "optionC": "  Xerophytes ",
            "optionD": "  Pteridophytes ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA xerophyte is a species of plant that has adaptations to survive in an environment with little liquid water, such as a desert or an ice- or snow-covered region in the Alps or the Arctic. Popular examples of xerophytes are cacti, pineapple and some Gymnosperm plants. ",
            "keyString": "632052s44m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Azolla is a",
            "optionA": "  Algae ",
            "optionB": "  Fungi ",
            "optionC": "  Bryophyta ",
            "optionD": "  Aqueous fern ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAzolla (mosquito fern, duckweed fern, fairy moss, water fern) is a genus of seven species of aquatic ferns in the family Salviniaceae. They are extremely reduced in form and specialized, looking nothing like other typical ferns but more resembling duckweed or some mosses. ",
            "keyString": "632083s44m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Bamboo is classified as",
            "optionA": "  Tree ",
            "optionB": "  Grass ",
            "optionC": "  Shrub ",
            "optionD": "  Herb ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBamboo is classified as grass. ",
            "keyString": "632097s44m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Bios means ",
            "optionA": "  Study ",
            "optionB": "  Life ",
            "optionC": "  Fact ",
            "optionD": "  True ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBios means life. ",
            "keyString": "632108s44m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In mainly which phylum the body of an organisms is usually divided in there regions called head, thorax and abdomen?",
            "optionA": "  Annelida ",
            "optionB": "  Chordata ",
            "optionC": "  Arthropods ",
            "optionD": "  Echinodermata ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tClass Insecta is the largest group of arthropods and includes mainly terrestrial arthropods with a distinct head, thorax and abdomen, one pair of antennae, three pairs of legs, jaws and up to two pairs of wings. This group includes most of the familiar creatures affectionately known as \"bugs\". ",
            "keyString": "632119s44m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "________ being a higher category, is the assemblage of families which exhibit a few similar characters.",
            "optionA": "  Order ",
            "optionB": "  Species ",
            "optionC": "  Genus ",
            "optionD": "  Class ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOrder being a higher category, is the assemblage of families which exhibit a few similar characters. ",
            "keyString": "666600s44m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Subphylum vertebrata is also known as",
            "optionA": "  Pisces ",
            "optionB": "  Craniata ",
            "optionC": "  Aves ",
            "optionD": "  Amphibia ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tVertebrate, also called Craniata, any animal of the subphylum Vertebrata, the predominant subphylum of the phylum Chordata. ",
            "keyString": "666626s44m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "How many vertebrae found in human vertebral column?",
            "optionA": "  22  ",
            "optionB": "  25  ",
            "optionC": "  33  ",
            "optionD": "  42  ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tVertebrae are the 33 individual bones that interlock with each other to form the spinal column. The vertebrae are numbered and divided into regions: cervical, thoracic, lumbar, sacrum, and coccyx. ",
            "keyString": "666640s44m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Biological classification of plants and animals was first proposed by",
            "optionA": "  Aristotle  ",
            "optionB": "  Plato  ",
            "optionC": "  Linnaeus  ",
            "optionD": "  Whittaker  ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBiological classification of plants and animals was first proposed by Aristotle on the basis of simple morphological characters.",
            "keyString": "666651s44m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Bacteria is included in the kingdom classification of",
            "optionA": "  Protista  ",
            "optionB": "  Plantae  ",
            "optionC": "  Animalia  ",
            "optionD": "  Monera  ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn the five kingdom classification, bacteria are included in Kingdom Monera. Bacteria are cosmopolitan in distribution. These organisms show the most extensive metabolic diversity. Bacteria may be autotrophic or heterotrophic in their mode of nutrition. ",
            "keyString": "666661s44m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In most plants and animals, the fluid filled sacs or cisternae of Golgi Bodies may vary from",
            "optionA": "  1 to 2 ",
            "optionB": "  2 to 3 ",
            "optionC": "  3 to 7 ",
            "optionD": "  7 to 10 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn most plants and animals, the fluid filled sacs or cisternae of Golgi Bodies may vary from 3 to 7. ",
            "keyString": "702479s44m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "A cell consists of three main components which is ________ ",
            "optionA": "  Cytoplasm, Nucleus, cell membrane ",
            "optionB": "  Protoplasm, Nucleoplasm, Cytoplasm ",
            "optionC": "  Nucleus, Ribosomes, Plasma membrane ",
            "optionD": "  Plasma membrane, Nucleus, Golgi bodies ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA cell consists of three parts: the cell membrane, the nucleus, and, between the two, the cytoplasm. ",
            "keyString": "702508s44m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "These are rods or filament like very small bodies present in the cytoplasm of all cells of plants and animals.",
            "optionA": "  Golgi Bodies ",
            "optionB": "  Ribosomes ",
            "optionC": "  Lysosomes ",
            "optionD": "  Mitochondria ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMitochondria are rods or filament like very small bodies present in the cytoplasm of all cells of plants and animals. ",
            "keyString": "702522s44m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Through cell membrane, which substances can pass more easily than others?",
            "optionA": "  Peptides soluble ",
            "optionB": "  Nucleic acids soluble ",
            "optionC": "  Cellulose soluble ",
            "optionD": "  Lipid soluble ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tLipid soluble can pass more easily. ",
            "keyString": "702533s44m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following are longest cells of human body?",
            "optionA": "  Pancreatic cells ",
            "optionB": "  Epethelial cells ",
            "optionC": "  Nerve cells ",
            "optionD": "  Epidermal cells ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe longest cell in the human body is the neuron. Neurons are cells of the nervous system that process and transmit information throughout the body. ",
            "keyString": "702544s44m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Pollen grains in plants are produced in",
            "optionA": "  roots ",
            "optionB": "  leaves ",
            "optionC": "  flower ",
            "optionD": "  stem ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPollen grains in plants are produced in flower. ",
            "keyString": "737189s44m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Nitrogen is fixed in ecosystems in ways stated below. Which one of the statements below is false?",
            "optionA": "  By cyanobacteria ",
            "optionB": "  By electrical discharges in the atmosphere ",
            "optionC": "  By industrially synthesised fertilizer ",
            "optionD": "  By denitrification ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNitrogen is not fixed in ecosystems by denitrification. ",
            "keyString": "737217s44m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Ptyalin is an enzyme produced in the",
            "optionA": "  salivary glands ",
            "optionB": "  pituitary glands ",
            "optionC": "  thyroid glands ",
            "optionD": "  pancreas ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPtyalin is produced by the salivary glands, whereas pancreatic amylase is secreted by the pancreas into the small intestine. ",
            "keyString": "737230s44m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Mycobacterium leprae causes leprosy, Corynebacterium diphtheria causes diphtheria and Vibrio comma causes",
            "optionA": "  tetanus ",
            "optionB": "  influenza ",
            "optionC": "  cholera ",
            "optionD": "  typhoid ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tVibrio cholerae (also Kommabacillus) is a gram negative comma-shaped bacterium with a polar flagellum that causes cholera in humans",
            "keyString": "737242s44m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Biotic component of the environment does not include-\n ",
            "optionA": "  Soil system ",
            "optionB": "  Animal system ",
            "optionC": "  Micro-organism system ",
            "optionD": "  Plant system ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAnimal, Micro organism and Plants are biotic components of the environment while soil along with other landforms are non-biotic components of the environment. ",
            "keyString": "737255s44m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The stages between larval moults in an insect are called",
            "optionA": "  Pupal  ",
            "optionB": "  Instars  ",
            "optionC": "  Grubs  ",
            "optionD": "  Caterpillars  ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAn instar is a developmental stage of arthropods, such as insects, between each moult (ecdysis), until sexual maturity is reached. ",
            "keyString": "778682s44m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In which of the following stages of silkworm, silk is secreted",
            "optionA": "  Larva  ",
            "optionB": "  Pupa  ",
            "optionC": "  Egg  ",
            "optionD": "  Adult  ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSilkworms feed on fresh mulberry leaves the silkworm grows in size and then becomes a pupa. In the pupa stage, it weaves a net to hold itself. It then swings its head from side to side, secreting a fibre that hardens on contact with air. In pupa stage silk is obtained. ",
            "keyString": "778712s44m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which is the longest bone in the human body?",
            "optionA": "  Fibula ",
            "optionB": "  Radius ",
            "optionC": "  Stapes ",
            "optionD": "  Femur ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe femur is one of the most researched bones in the human anatomy and forensic medicine. As the longest bone in the human body, it is well preserved in skeletal remains. ",
            "keyString": "778727s44m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The bone of which organ is the longest in the human body?",
            "optionA": "  Spinal cord ",
            "optionB": "  Thigh ",
            "optionC": "  Rib cage ",
            "optionD": "  Ankle-bone ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe bone of thigh called femur is the longest in the human body. ",
            "keyString": "778739s44m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Treatment of body defects through massage and exercise is",
            "optionA": "  Phylogeny ",
            "optionB": "  Parasitology ",
            "optionC": "  Physiotherapy ",
            "optionD": "  Physiology ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPhysiology is branch of medicine that studies towards proper functioning and working of human body. The methods used to do so are referred as physiotherapy. The person expert in physiology is called as physiotherapist. Physiotherapy is done after recovery of bone damage to ensure it's complete working as a normal bone. So, the correct option is 'Physiotherapy'. ",
            "keyString": "778751s44m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In plants, which of the following cells are used to store surplus food?",
            "optionA": "  Chlorenchymatous cells ",
            "optionB": "  Parenchymatous cells ",
            "optionC": "  Sclerenchymatous cells ",
            "optionD": "  Golgi bodies ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tParenchymatous cells are used to store surplus food in plants. ",
            "keyString": "814755s44m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which tissue makes the plant hard and stiff?",
            "optionA": "  Parenchyma ",
            "optionB": "  Sclerenchyma ",
            "optionC": "  Collenchyma ",
            "optionD": "  Xylem ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSclerenchyma is the tissue which makes the plant hard and stiff. Sclerenchyma is the supporting tissue in plants. Two types of sclerenchyma cells exist: fibers cellular and sclereids. ",
            "keyString": "814784s44m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Excess of fat in the body is stored in",
            "optionA": "  Adipose tissue ",
            "optionB": "  Acrosome ",
            "optionC": "  Erythrocytes ",
            "optionD": "  Bone marrow ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe extra energy is stored in adipose tissue all around the body in the form of triglycerides. ",
            "keyString": "814798s44m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Study of tissue culture is useful for",
            "optionA": "  Non-living ",
            "optionB": "  Plant ",
            "optionC": "  Air ",
            "optionD": "  Water ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTissue culture studies have clarified the genetic causes of certain hereditary diseases, and methods have been developed for detecting environmental substances that may cause gene damage. It has been important for plants. ",
            "keyString": "814810s44m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What is the name of a group of similar cells performing a specific function?",
            "optionA": "  Tissue ",
            "optionB": "  Organ ",
            "optionC": "  Organ system ",
            "optionD": "  Cellular organization ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA tissue is a group of similar cells performing similar functions. Each tissue has a specific function. ",
            "keyString": "814822s44m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following structure is not found in a eukaryotic cell?",
            "optionA": "  Ribosome  ",
            "optionB": "  Mitochondria  ",
            "optionC": "  Mesosome  ",
            "optionD": "  Golgi body  ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMesosome is not found in a eukaryotic cell. ",
            "keyString": "891462s44m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is found in plant cells but not in animal cells?",
            "optionA": "  Cell Wall  ",
            "optionB": "  Vacuoles  ",
            "optionC": "  Plasma layer  ",
            "optionD": "  Golgi complex  ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPlant cells have a cell wall, chloroplasts and other specialized plastids, and a large central vacuole, which are not found within animal cells. The cell wall is a rigid covering that protects the cell, provides structural support, and gives shape to the cell. ",
            "keyString": "891490s44m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Prokaryotic cell differs from eukaryotic cell in lacking",
            "optionA": "  DNA  ",
            "optionB": "  Nuclear membrane  ",
            "optionC": "  Cell organelles  ",
            "optionD": "  RNA  ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe primary distinction between these two types of organisms is that eukaryotic cells have a membrane-bound nucleus and prokaryotic cells do not.",
            "keyString": "891504s44m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The prokaryotic cell lacks",
            "optionA": "  Nuclear envelope and DNA  ",
            "optionB": "  Nuclear envelope and plastids  ",
            "optionC": "  DNA and mitochondria  ",
            "optionD": "  Cell membrance and nucleus  ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe prokaryotic cell lacks nuclear envelope and plastids. ",
            "keyString": "891516s44m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which is the only human cell that has a flagella?",
            "optionA": "  Blood cells  ",
            "optionB": "  Sperm  ",
            "optionC": "  Neurons  ",
            "optionD": "  Liver cells  ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAn example of a eukaryotic flagellate cell is the mammalian sperm cell, which uses its flagellum to propel itself through the female reproductive tract.",
            "keyString": "891527s44m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Innate immune system defenses include",
            "optionA": "  Phagocytosis ",
            "optionB": "  B cells ",
            "optionC": "  Plasma cells ",
            "optionD": "  T cells ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tWhen pathogens enter the body, the innate immune system responds with a variety of internal defenses. These include the inflammatory response, phagocytosis, natural killer cells, and the complement system. ",
            "keyString": "927713s44m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "A vehicle borne transmitted diseases are",
            "optionA": "  Plague and Malaria ",
            "optionB": "  Chicken Pox and Tetanus ",
            "optionC": "  Mumps and Common cold ",
            "optionD": "  Eye infection and influenza ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tVehicle-borne transmission is a vehicle that is, an inanimate object or material called in scientific terms a \"fomite\"\u2014becomes contaminated with the infectious agent. The agent, such as a virus, may or may not have multiplied or developed in or on the vehicle. The vehicle contacts the person's body. Plague and Malaria are vehicle borne transmitted diseases. ",
            "keyString": "927742s44m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Plasmodium is a ",
            "optionA": "  Symbiont ",
            "optionB": "  Parasite ",
            "optionC": "  Saprophyte ",
            "optionD": "  All of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPlasmodium, a genus of parasitic protozoans of the sporozoan subclass Coccidia that are the causative organisms of malaria. Plasmodium, which infects red blood cells in mammals (including humans), birds, and reptiles, occurs worldwide, especially in tropical and temperate zones. ",
            "keyString": "927754s44m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Study of the effects of toxic chemical substance on animal and plant is",
            "optionA": "  Toxicology ",
            "optionB": "  Microbiology ",
            "optionC": "  Limnology ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tToxicology is traditionally defined as \"the science of poisons.\" Over time, our understanding of how various agents can cause harm to humans and other organisms has increased, resulting in a more descriptive definition of toxicology as \"the study of the adverse effects of chemical, physical, or biological agents ",
            "keyString": "927765s44m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Main function of antibodies is against",
            "optionA": "  Unfavourable environment ",
            "optionB": "  During deficiency of nutrient ",
            "optionC": "  infection ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAntibodies contribute to immunity in three ways: preventing pathogens from entering or damaging cells by binding to them (neutralization); stimulating removal of pathogens by macrophages and other cells by coating the pathogen (opsonization); and triggering destruction of pathogens by stimulating other immune responses. ",
            "keyString": "927777s44m37h15d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        }
    ]
}